Okay, as you can see, I'm trying use uh
several different ways to record my own
lecture so that I can combine these uh
videos together. Then um if you know um
last year I taught this course before
the same time the spring in 2025. So the
video are on all on YouTube. So feel
free to watch last year's video. The
skeleton of this year will be pretty
much the same at least for the first
half of the semester. Then I try to
extend more content towards the second
half of the semester then to go a little
bit more advanced that fits a like a PhD
level course. Okay. So well the code is
there again. Well at least it's not part
of my recording I guess. So uh how many
of you are undergraduate students?
Uh
f four right four student. Okay. How
many of you are master?
Okay. Three. Four. Then five. Okay. Then
the rest. How many of you are PhD
students here? Okay. So roughly the same
amount of undergraduate and the graduate
master and PhD student. That's good. So
uh this the um this course is advanced
computer architecture. So I guess most
of you have never taken a computer
architecture course, right? How many of
you have taken a basic computer
architecture course? Okay. Okay, there
are several of you. So, how many of you
know what is uh sequential logic and uh
uh combinational logic that you're
comfortable with in this content?
Um, okay. A little bit. Okay. So,
typically when I say advanced computer
architecture, we do not teach uh
sequential logic and combination logic.
But because most of you do not have this
background, I probably will spend two
weeks time to review those content.
Those are not super important for this
course but it's the basics for you to
understand that no matter what advanced
the features that we're designing in
computer architecture they're eventually
uh implemented with basic features.
Okay. So uh what this course is about
this is a full fully lecture based
courses. So we're not expecting uh read
papers or doing presentations. And uh
we're going to cover topics like
starting from boolean logic
combinational logic sequential logic uh
probably ver log simulation risk 5 is
computer CPU core architecture branch
prediction spective execution DRM cache
co uh co coherency and consistency
network on chip and especially GPU
architectures. So a lot of topic then uh
last year we do not really have DM there
uh covered then we do not have much
speculative execution we didn't cover
verog probably this year we're not going
to cover verog again then we covered
coherency we didn't cover consistency
let's see if we have time to cover
consistency or not we didn't cover
network on chip but this year that's
something that I really want to add okay
and if you watched the video last year
on GPU architecture ure GPU architecture
I didn't have slides I just write it
using uh blackboard so um and this year
I'm going to make slides for it now
we're going to have assignment and
quizzes quizzes are more likely to be um
um on Google forms so that you can just
fill in a few selection questions then
that you immediately can get a like a
grading okay then simulation is a core
topic now I'm going to you teach you how
to run uh computer architecture
simulations
Then um for for you to verify if you
fully understand the idea, I ask you to
write some simulation code. Okay, I ask
you to write some simulation code so
that you can like say when we learn
cache, I may ask you to write some cache
simulation code so that then I know you
understand how cache works basically.
Then um in general I consider you can
use generative AI then either to say ask
questions what is a cache how does way
associve cache works if you do not
understand the concepts in the lectures
uh if you write code totally it's okay
to use generative generative are
everywhere then you can use it to help
you learn and uh for simulation um since
since we're going to use the Akida
simulation framework that is a
simulation framework developed by me uh
where you're going to use the go program
language. So if you have no go
experience, don't worry. It's easy. It's
easier than Python. So uh especially
when work with generative AI, it's
um probably
you just don't need to learn. Just see
examples and write code as long as you
can read it is good enough. Uh so on the
syllabus there's a textbook. There's no
need to buy the textbook. I will cover
all the content and I will if you want
to buy it that's okay. is a very good
textbook that I learned the basic things
from that textbook. Um but I will also
provide uh further reading
recommendations. So that textbook is
undergraduate level computer
architecture or even digital design
level. Um it's a basic u computer
architecture textbook for some advanced
fe uh advanced uh features like
consistency network on chip there are
very good textbooks there. So I may um
recommend reading then you can get uh
electronic version from our library.
Okay. So I won't cover the uh syllabus
again. So I'm basically just directly
going to uh cover real content starting
from what is computer architecture. Um
the syllabus is not online. I think you
are all uh you can all see the course
website and you are all in the discord,
right? So that's good. So if you have
questions, let me know. Now what is
computer architecture? And you probably
have seen this type of uh technology
stacks and starting from application to
physics. Now we want to use physics
properties. For example, we have
electrons, we have neutrons or we have
magnets, we have uh electricity. Those
are all physics properties or something
fall from um from above to bottom. Those
are physics properties. And we have
applications. For example, we want to
write documents. We want to write uh we
want to have have AI to help us think.
Those are applications. Those are
something that we want to do. So we want
to bridge the physics and application to
use those physics properties to solve
applications for some very basic cases.
Now we can almost directly use physics
to solve problems. For example, that's a
level and that's a um compass compass,
right? So we can directly use the
magnets to point north and south. that
we can almost directly solve the
problem. Not that hard. Then we don't
really need a technology stack. A single
person may probably be able to produce
these type of tools. But for computer
architecture and for the whole computing
domain, so probably there are some
people working on AI algorithms, for
some people working on making those
chips, for some people working on
producing these chips. There's almost
impossible for a single person to work
on everything. So we divide this whole
technology stack into stack frames. We
divi uh into individual tech layers
there in the technology stack. So some
people work on this layer, some people
work on that layer. Now so if we can
define the interface between the layers
then people can collaborate with each
other and can help us use the physics
properties to achieve our designed goal.
And this is the computing technology
stack. I think this is definitely a
oversimplified version of a computing
technology stack. Um it's probably a
stack may not be the best way to
describe the computing
landscape this year is probably a graph
that there's so many domains that um
that people work on different things and
then they combine so that we can run
generative AI today, right? Um so but
this is a simplified version that we can
see we typically call it when it's
closer to the application we call it uh
on the top of the stack when it's close
to the physics we target on the bottom
of the stack. There's no good or bad
it's just different things. Um so for
example at the bottom we have devices
now we typically transistors right? So
um those t super small things that are
doing on and off switches. Now we have
gates and gates not not gates at least
not that's something you should be
familiar the micro architecture is how
these chips are designed internally and
we have instruction set architecture
we'll explain this later from here on
top we start to go to the software
domain
start from here we start to go with the
software domain for example we have
assembly and the machine code right the
very basic software that we're using to
communicate with the hardware now we
have operating system have program here
program language here and algorithm
those are some course titles that you
have may have already taken then what is
instruction set architecture then
especially when we talk about computer
architecture we say it's somewhere
between this region then instruction set
architecture or ISA ISA you probably
have heard of this name is a protocol
between the software and hardware so
probably you have heard these terms of
x86 or X uh or AMD 64 or ARM or IBM
power PC
um or risk five. Those are all
protocols. Those are the defines say
okay 0000001 means to um add operation
add two numbers together. 02 means a
subtract operation that means to minus
from one number to another uh minus a
number to from another number. So this
is the protocol between software and
hardware. Then if you re uh go back to
the early ages by that time we don't
really have this layer by that time we
probably have much fewer layers right
then by the time then people use a tape
a tape of uh paper those papers with
punch holes then those punch holes
directly represent zeros and ones we
don't really have that number so in that
time every computer may have their own
instruction set their own program
language so if you program for one
computer computer. Then later on we have
a new computer. Then the pro the
software you totally need to write new
software and people do not really care
that much because software by that time
was pretty much disposal that you use
one time then you get the result and
then you're done with this software
right so but later on we want reuse we
want to save time so we write one
program we want to use again and again
and especially when we want to have new
computers then the program still runs
then we added this layer. This layer is
probably the most stable layer
uh in the whole
in the whole architecture right in the
whole stack. Like consider devices we
have three nanometer we have seven
nanometer it's changing really fast then
we have uh something like a mossfat
finfat you don't really need to
understand what those things but those
are totally different devices right but
consider how difficult Apple switch from
power PC to x86 it's very early ages
then Apple switched from x86 from Intel
CPUs to ARM CPUs to their own CPUs then
Apple was the success uccessful example.
There are so many unsuccessful example
is a very hard high cost be because if
you change this thing you need to
redesign everything below and redesign
everything on the top. That's a lot of
work. Okay. Then another separation of
this technology stack then you probably
have heard of this department. Now we at
the Mario we only have computer science.
So in computer science we probably have
to cover more things but in some
universities they have electrical
engineering they have computer
engineering they have computer science
right so where are their boundaries they
typically consider electric anything
below instruction set architecture or
electrical engineering although this
year's electrical engineering department
are doing AI
but typically we consider the basic
things device level are electrical
engineering computer science are on the
software software side, right? But if
you talk about computer architecture,
it's typically the system side to divide
to uh to micro architecture side, right?
So it really depends on the how the
departments are uh defined. Now in term
of computer architecture, we're talking
about this middle layer, right? So when
we talk about this middle layer, you
consider it's like the core muscle of a
human, right? If you want to say play uh
tennis, right? you need to um
um hit a ball hard then you really need
your core muscle. So look at here then
applications are keep changing then
right we have generative AI we have many
many new things like uh the image
generation then we have new software
appearing almost every day then we have
new devices 7 nanometer 3 nanometer 2
nanometer or something like um the
compute in memory right so there's so
many things that happens at this layer
so they de develop rather
independently on their own. they just
want faster and faster smaller low
energy and then this side and they just
develop on their own just say oh we want
generative AI we want to do something
then computer architecture in the center
is connecting these two parts so
whenever there's some new application
new algorithm we have to think oh how we
can make those algorithm run faster then
whenever there's new hardware there's
new device we need to consider how we
can use these things to make uh the top
layer run faster and run more sec in a
more secure way. Um and actually then as
I say it makes things run faster faster.
It's not only about faster. Just think
about AI, right? Think about why AI was
not a thing even before 2012, right? In
what what happens in 2012? Do you know
why I say 2012?
So 2012 marks one thing is the
development of a convolutional neural
network called Alexnet.
Okay, Alexnut
significantly increase the accuracy of
image recognition. It it just like
another level, right? Is whenever the
quartz
watch, right, the watch that runs on the
crystals, right, is so much accurate
than mechanics um than mechanical
watches, right? It's just suddenly a new
type of animal entered the game. That's
Alex Nat. Then starting that point in a
few years you see image recognition are
very mature and in commercial um
products right like face recognition is
probably in every camera after that
point then so
2012 is definitely a big thing it's
probably more important than the year
when chhatt was u released so
why that thing Alex net started in 2012
there are two big reasons. One is
imageet. Image net is from Stanford.
It's a big data set. So people start to
care about the quality of the data set,
the training set. And another thing is
people start to use GPUs to do
calculation. If you consider GPUs versus
CPUs on generative on AI workload, it's
not because the CPU cannot do it. It's
just because CPU is slow. But if we can
accelerate it by 10 times or 100 times,
think about 100 times. If it's a year's
task that you can reduce it to three
days that's you're turning something
impossible to possible right so the
comput so in this sense computer
architecture are enabler of new
technologies
okay so those are the point of computer
architecture and why we study computer
architecture so on as we say computer
architecture is uh
is in the center of this technology
stack. I often compare computer
architecture with um so you you probably
have heard of the people who write very
low code who design circuits. Those are
um rather intra-level jobs. Now what's
the jobs for computer architecture? So
computer architecture are typically
considered a slightly higher level jobs
are research type of jobs or manager
type of jobs. uh uh it can be compared
with something like a software developer
and a UX developer. So UX developer
there it's a um it's a designer and also
u project manager. So in big companies
like AMD or media Intel they have
developers who write very low code that
implements the next generation of their
software right they also have computer
architect who looks one generation
beyond two generation beyond their um
like three years product line say what
features we want to implement at this
layer you just probably have many many
ideas that you not all ideas may work
you just have to discard all those ideas
um then eventually you decide what are
valuable, what are practical, then you
give it to the um entry- levelvel jobs
or verog writers to implement the
circuit. Okay. So at this sense we
really need to understand a lot of
things. We need to understand what
happens at device level and what happens
at application level so that you can um
really design the right thing.
So I don't want to waste time. So let's
start from transistors and see um there
are many things that we need to consider
when we design computer architecture as
a higher level design. So transistors we
know we all know transistors are the
building blocks of chips right. So at
the beginning transistors are something
looks like this. These are not even the
beginning. These are like uh 80s or 90s
and people are built like radios and
they just use this type of um devices.
So whenever we have a transistor we
typically say it's a three pin device.
So three pins one to three right. So
they can they have either output or
input they have just connected to
outside world with the three pins right.
So when we talk about digital logic you
know digital logic we consider zero and
one. So it's either zero or one that is
passing to this each pin. Okay. So when
we consider pins is actually a very
important uh concept in computer
architecture. So
it's something similar to when you are
doing visualization. when you're doing
com uh computer or interactive
visualization the pixels on the screen
is actually a limiting factor that you
let's consider this one is 1024 by 768
that's older standard but that's about
less than a million pixels so that means
you cannot really show you cannot really
show more than one million elements
right that's a hard limiting factor when
you consider
chips the number of pins are the how
fast that this pin can communicate with
the outside world. That's also another
hard limit that people easily ignore.
It's a three pin device. Then you
probably have heard of these vacuum
tubes. Then those are the early type
tubes that are built in early computers.
So I just want to introduce how they
works. So this is a vacuum tube.
Internally is there's no air. There's
nothing in it, right? It's a it's a
piece of glass. So it connects with two
powers actually I I would yeah it
connects with two powers right. So this
is one thing. This is the control side
the control grid and this is the
um I would say this is the load side
that is the where you put a bob or
something then um then we use the signal
on this side we want to use the control.
So roughly speaking, it's a switch. Then
we want to turn it on or off. And how it
works is there's something there's a
control grid. The control grid that if
this power is connected, it's heating
this control grid. It heats it up.
Whenever it heats up,
then this electrons can flow from this
side to the other side. Then exact like
I don't know the exact physics here, but
you just can treat it how it works.
Whenever this the electrons can flow
from one side to other to the other the
circuit is closed then this side is
connected. Right? So even today we want
to have a transistor works in a very
simple way. We have a control signal.
It can be either one or zero. Let's say
one means to connect this circuit. Zero
means to close to disconnect this
circuit. Then that's simple. That is how
transistor works. Although transistors
can be super complex but for computer
architecture that's the basic things you
need to understand. Now with this if
this can represent a zero and one then
we can combine these transistors to make
logics right.
So later on we don't use vacuum tubes.
What's the problem with vacuum tubes?
It's really not it's really big first
right? Think about the early age
computer. It takes the whole room or the
whole building and only can store
hundreds of bits there. Then
it's very and it's very energy
consuming. Consider there are two
things. Heating up something. Heating up
metal takes a lot of energy. On the
other side, this is a circuit that is
keep flowing, right? So the energy keeps
being wasted. It's like a short circuit
here that energy is wasted at this on
this side. Right? So we don't want this
energy keeps running. We want to save
energy. Just consider energy is probably
even more important today than
performance. Why is it? Because if you
consider today generative, you probably
have heard of this generative AI um that
the bottleneck of the capability of
gener is electricity. How much
electricity that we can generate, right?
So if we have more electricity, we can
gen we can if I have more electricity,
we can have more powerful AI. On the
other side, this electricity, no matter
like what type of devices, if we put
electricity in it, if like my laptop
takes like 25 volts of power,
the energy the 25 volt is eventually
turned into heat. Then we have we even
need to have more energy to bring the
heat away. So we either need to use air
conditioner to bring the heat away or we
need fans or to blow the heat away. that
even we blow the heat away. We need we
need air conditioner to to bring it out
from the room, right? Um um and also
sometimes we can just build the
supercomputing center near a river so
the river water can uh can bring the
heat away. There's also proposal that
put data center um under the ocean or
put in the outer space. So there are
many different proposals that consider
how to bring the heat away. So I I asked
someone who built a data center, they
say it takes more energy to bring the
heat away than to power the computer
itself. Okay. So
um and because we can bring the heat
away in a certain speed, we cannot
really generate the heat faster um too
fast, right? If it's generating heat too
fast that the temperature of the chip is
too high is below a certain degree then
it would the chip will melt. So we have
to turn off some cores or some part of
the circuit so that we can within the
power limit. Now because of this if we
can reduce the energy consumption we can
have more parts of like more cores
enabled then we have more performance
right it's not really about uh
conservation it's not really about
environmental like definitely
environmental consider is a big
consideration but even you if you just
consider performance you need to
consider energy consumption
okay so then later on they use BJT BJT
is a semiconductor before that is not
even semiconductor BJT semiconductor
then uh so there's three layers three
ends emitter collector and base then the
base is the control so B if the base is
connected with one then this part are
connected if it's not one if it's zero
then this part are not connected so BJT
solves the heating problem that we don't
need to heat up metal to enable it but
it's still current driven it's not
totally bad it's still useful in some
cases it's just not the the technology
that we use in modern uh computer chip
design today. What do we use today? You
probably have heard of this thing called
SIMOS. It's called complimentary metal
oxide semiconductor.
Okay, let me introduce this part first.
Metal oxide semiconductor. So this is
like the side view of u I call it
something called a gate. But we can just
focus on this part.
So we have a P substrate
um physics don't cons don't wor too much
about physics okay now we have a unwell
and another unwell then here is oxide
right it's not like the electricity
cannot go through now here is a piece of
metal on top of it okay if you apply a
voltage on G there's some magic things
happen in the semiconductor here then
this N and this N are connected
together.
Okay, if we do not apply a voltage here,
this N and and this N are not connected
at all. Okay, so this is how it works.
You just just don't don't consider
what's N what's P. Just just know if
there's a voltage, these two are
connected. If there no no voltage, these
two are not connected. On the other
side, it's the other way around. If
there's no voltage, these two are
connected. is there's a voltage these
two are not connected. Okay. So this is
why we call it complimentary.
So you can consider one side is P uh is
a N MOS one side is a POS. Don't even
need to consider which part is N MOS
which part is P MOS. Just see if there's
a circle in term of C uh in term of like
circuit uh annotation. this means kind
of a not sign that on the input side
that means if it's zero it's enabled uh
on this side if it's one then it's
enabled okay let's look at what's going
on here
let's say if a is one okay if a is one
so vsss is ground is zero voltdd is one
is 5 volt or 1.3 volt uh it depends on
the definition sometimes 12 volt then if
a is one this part is not connected and
this part is connected
this part is not connected just when
it's not connected just ignore this part
just assume this part is not even there
okay then this part is connected with Q
so Q will equal VSSs
question
>> so this is like a electrical version of
mechanical
switch or wire.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It's a it's a signal
controlled switch. This switch is
connected. Just consider there's a wire.
Okay. Only consider there's a wire
connecting these two. There's no wire
connecting from here. Okay.
So, it's zero volt then zero volt goes
here. If it's one, if it's zero, this
part is connected. Just consider there's
a wire. There's no wire here.
Okay, it's disconnected. This part is
connected and Q equals V DD and that
means Q equals to 1. So summarize this.
If A is one, Q is zero. If A is zero, Q
is one.
Okay, so that's a not gate. So Q always
equals to the other side of A.
Okay, comfortable with this design?
So what a problem it solves.
There's no current here. There's only
voltage control.
Right? So the this part is not
connected. So this metal is totally
disconnected with the rest of the
circuit. And this metal is the white
part on the top. It's totally
disconnected with the M part here. So
there's no current going through. WDD
and VSSS are never connected.
Okay, they're never connected. When Q is
connected to VSSS, is it voltage drops
to zero. When VDD connects to Q, the
voltage rise to one, but there's still
no current going through.
So what's the energy consumption? And
typically we say a chip cons
consumes two part of energy. One is
dynamic energy, one static energy.
Static energy means there's no pure
isolation, right? There's always some
voltage, some electrons goes from VSSs
to VDD. It's the current goes the other
way. So that's but in cos this is really
small and no matter is one or zero, it's
still that small. It's still static,
right? But if you consider BJD BJ BJT if
it's one then this is connected and
consumes a lot lot of energy. If it's
zero and not connected it's not
consuming much energy. So here the
static energy is really slow no matter
it's one or zero. Now what's the dynamic
part is those are switches right
switching the state means some electrons
goes from here to there. Then there are
some energy consumption to switch on and
off these uh gates this this the this
these switches right so those are
dynamic energy and static energy and
dynamic energy those are two parts of
energy consumption and summing up these
two part of energy is the total energy
consumption of a chip. Okay. So today we
definitely want to reduce the dynam uh
static energy and static energy today is
actually rather low um this these days
uh it's mainly dynamic energy
consumption. Now if you look at the NAND
gate I think I can leave it as an
exercise for you to analyze how this
nand gate works. But just consider if A
is zero, B is zero. This part is not
connected. Right? And A is zero. This is
connected. This is connected. Both of
them are connected. Then the output is
one. Z output one. So it's
and get the other side of end. Flip it.
Okay. You can do it as exercise. I want
to go too deep on here.
Any question?
Okay. So then consider early days uh
BJTs or transistors are in this way. You
probably have used the breadboard to
build a circuit. you know the pain then
you if you have built it then the even
breadboard the largest breadboard like
when I was undergraduate student I built
a two breadboard and that's basically
two full breadboard that's basically a
clock 24-hour clock that's the maximum I
can do then using PCB is much better
because we have those uh circuit
pre-built
Um so in this way it's not very likely
to build a whole very complex chip in
this way. So then people start to build
integrated circuit and integrated
circuit was first built by people from
this company called Firechild. Although
this company is not there, he's still a
legend because there are many people
coming out from this company is becoming
very important person and very important
other companies in the later time. Then
people start to build this thing called
very large scale integrated circuit or
IC as integrated circuit first. Then
they build larger scale. the larger
scale they have large scale integrated
circuit then then when they grow very
large they go they call it very large
scale integrated circuit so Visi is a
term today that people probably do not
just spell it out but it stands for very
large scale integrated circuit this is
what looks like in this way so uh
you don't really have to understand too
much about that but this different
colors means different things for
example um red may means P well green
may mean Nwell and this blue part may
means copper right those coppers are
wires connected then those X are coppers
that goes down so that it can connect
with the bottom layers so don't worry
too much about this and when people
consider this is basically some like the
process of going from breadboard to PCB
like we want to be able to print the
circuit into something that is really
small.
Okay. So later on we'll talk about how
these are can help uh making a chip.
Then how chips are made.
So then very large uh from Fairchild
there comes two two people. One is
Robert Noise, one is Golden. they
started this company called Intel which
is like really the company that um make
VI or integrate circuit a very important
um business practical business and if
you heard of Gordon Gordon Moro
Gordon
Moore this name you should be very
familiar with one thing that's Mors law
right and that's what he proposed now he
proposed this law at a very early age
when the integrated circuit may only
have a few like tens or hundreds of
transistors there. So what is more slow?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Okay. So let me repeat. So Morris
law at the beginning is in this form.
The number of components per integrate
circuit have can be doubling every year.
That's the original form. Then later on
this is slightly changed. So the
computer performance will roughly double
18 performance. But this performance is
today we measure by number of
transistors. So the number of
transistors on computer chips doubles
every 18 months with no increase in
power consumption. We'll talk about this
part later. This is more on Dar scaling
part. But um this 18 months is also a
modified version that later on that's u
it fits the curve.
So then this is so since 1990 people are
saying oh we're close to the end of mors
law and close to the end of mors law
they say oh our chips are our
transistors are one micrometers large
like 1,000 nanometer large how can it be
smaller than 25 or 35 years later we're
still saying we're at the end of the
mors law but mors law is it still
So there are two figures here. One is
from Wikipedia, one is our own data.
Okay.
So we have a data set that pretty much
summarize all the CPU and GPUs that is
commercially available on the market and
if they release their uh they release
their technical information. Now you can
see on Wikipedia is still rather linear,
right? So if you consider on this side
is exponential, right? is logarithm log
scale. So that is growing exponentially.
Now here from our own data it also shows
that it grows exponentially. that I can
also even explain what's going on here
is basically when Intel like the later
version of Intel they stopped releasing
their number of transistor information
and seems more slow stopped a few years
then when either they start to release
or AMD is catching up then this trend is
still kind of growing
okay so mors law is still there now we
know the uh we know how this is achieved
is by making the transistor smaller and
smaller. Now, how small is our
transistor? You may probably heard of
this uh transistor size that a few years
ago we have 7 nanometer technology.
Today probably the mainstream is 5
nanometer or even 3 nanometer. So
probably next year you can get two two
nanometer technology. But I have to say
um
this number of transistor size is more
and more a commercial term. It's not
describing the real uh transistor size
anymore. Okay.
Um it's not really describing the
transistor side anymore. It's more
especially this is TSMC the Taiwan
semiconductor manufacturing company.
It's their terminology. Intel follows a
different terminology. That's why Intel
is still in the 14 nanometer uh era. And
even Intel is going more and more
commercial. So that their number doesn't
really represent the size of the
um the transistors. But this is
a summary of density per chip. Now we
simply just calculate from our 4,000
chips, right? the commercial available
the number of transistors and the die
size. The die size is how large the chip
is just so that's a uh transistor per
millimeter square. Then pretty much you
can see for every
um transistor size and we only take the
the TSMC
data there um TSMC is something called a
foundry. Foundry is the manufacturer of
the chip. So there are three major manu
uh foundry in the world.
Uh Intel Intel they can produce chips on
their own. Then global foundry
and another one is TSMC. Definitely
today TSMC is probably the best and
Samsung can also produce and ZTE can
also produce and there are several um
other companies but their technology
cannot compete with uh the other three.
So but if you look at TSMC data then
pretty much like for every technology
for every process size their scope is
very small and their density is
consistently increasing right and even 7
nanometer is much higher much better
than 12 nanometer technology. So if you
compare with non uh atom size so what
atom size how large is atom is typically
100 to 200
pometer right. So pometer is one
lightwood below.
So 1,000 of a nanometer. So if you
consider those are tens to hundreds of
atoms per transistor. That's it. So just
it's pretty much atom level control. So
are we at the end of Mars law? Then if
you consider the number of atoms that we
control, probably yes. But if you look
at the trend now probably we can go with
a few probably a few tens of years.
So how are chips made? How can chips are
made so small and just I need to review
the whole process so that you can know
there are some fundamental constraints
um of this whole process so that you
know why we design computer architecture
in this way. Why we need to care about
number of transistors not much care
about energy consumption that much and
care about the dites that much? So
transistors are starting from silicon
crystals. Silicon crystals are made from
sand. So it's a magic converting from
sand to chips, right? But um we
typically start from here. TSMC just buy
silicon crystals from other companies.
Then these silicon crystals are super
pure. That's 99.999 or many nice is much
pure uh much more pure much purer than
the gold that you can buy today. So they
really need super pure uh silicon
because if there's some something that
is not a silicon item there the whole
chip may not work. So it's very
important. Then with this silicon
crystal they slice it into wafers. Okay.
So, it's definitely um
comparable to those cookies, crackers as
wafers. Then, how large is this wafer?
This wafer are typically like smaller
than 20 inches in diameter. So, consider
a mediumsiz pizza or small pizza. That's
about the size of a wafer. Okay. So, how
large is a chip?
Right. The largest chip today if you do
not consider something like AMD Thread
Reaper, a chip is about
um let's say about a cap like that's a
large rather large chip, right? A CPU
chip or something that's about the cap
of this uh whiteboard pan or two of
them. That's a very reasonable CPU size
for GPUs that can be slightly larger.
Uh so how it works is we first really
produce the chips on there then we slice
them okay make them smaller ones and how
these chips are manufactured is a
process called lithography and this is
uh if you heard of this company called
ASML then those are the masters of
lithography then they produce these
tools they're so precise that they
control atoms
so how it's
Now we prepare wafer and we slice it.
It's super clear. They use a lot of pure
water to clean it. Then we first put a
coat of photoresistant is a gel, right?
And we pre-bake some technology just
make the gel more persistent. Then we
put a line and expose. What does that
mean? Is we put a mask
on top of it. So consider how precise
this mask is. A wire,
a wire is nanometer level, number of
atom level, right? And we put a mask on
top of it and we use light to
cast light on it. So this photoresist
material are sensitive to light. If
light cast on it, they will disappear.
Okay, they will disappear. So then we
have this thing. So, so probably here
are the parts that we want to unwell or
pe or copper or something, right?
Then what they do is they use each they
basically use a chemical to wash away so
that it goes deeper. Then they can build
things on it. So they probably also use
some um like use as a target to have a
particle stream to heat it so that they
can start to build things on top of it,
right? Uh so consider this thing. This
is so small. It's so small. Like you
probably have heard of this light may
scatter when it goes through a very
narrow gap, right? So how how much
scatter they have depends on the
wavelengths. The smaller the
wavelengths, the less scatter they have,
right? So that's why you have heard of
probably heard of this uh extreme
ultraviolet today ultraviolet extreme
ultraviolet those are technologies
developed by ASML because the more
towards the ultraviolet site the smaller
the wavelengths then the more precise
that we can control this thing this
these
gaps here and also they have done lot of
crazy things uh to make it precise. For
example, they can really not even the
gap itself they can really not have
control a few atoms. So what they do is
they first each they first each this
side this first only cut this side then
they put another
um another layer then each another time
so that they can um produce a very thin
wire in their um on their chip. So this
whole process is very precise is very
difficult.
Then after that we have something called
packaging. So don't underestimate the
power of packaging. It's actually very
very important. So early days we have
this packaging that the pins on the
side. So packaging is basically the chip
is in center. Then we use wires to
connect with the pins outside. Then we
use a piece of plastic on top of it.
Now, you probably have seen those toy
watches. If you open those toy watches,
there's a big
black thing, like a a round black thing.
So, that's the easiest way to do
packaging. So, they put the chip
directly on top of the PCB. Then, they
drop a piece of plastic or wax or
something just to seal it so that it's
not interfering with the outside world.
So uh so so even like this it it
provides a basic level of protection for
the chip. Even this if you touch the
chip the plastic part of the chip like
the static electricity may damage the
chip. Um but that's something very
important. Then these pins are on the
side but consider if it's on the side
how many pins that we can have right
then later on we have ball pins
underneath. So today
um how many pins are there? Can you
guess how many pins are there in AMD or
Intel CPUs?
It's a roughly rough estimation.
>> Yeah.
>> Pins.
>> Oh, pins.
>> Pins. How many pins?
Um
probably like
>> there's there's a little bit too much.
>> Yeah. So look at here. So basically on
this type of device is on the side.
Yeah. Go ahead.
>> Uh a couple of hundred is u lower
estimation for lower-end chips. That's
reasonable. So higher end ones are 1,000
2,000 that level. Okay. So consider this
on the side is probably tens of them. So
with the bottom ones they can have
thousands of them. But even with
thousands of them that's the number of
number of bits that you can communicate
with outside world per cycle. Okay.
Actually they can do more. They can send
more bits. But probably in each cycle in
one ghahz if it's 1 ghahz there's one
ncond right one ncond then they can
probably send out 16 um bits out from
one pin question
>> yeah so they send out data in many
different ways for example CPU may read
and read and write memory right the
memory and the memory are inerted on
your motherboard. They may send video
signals to your monitor, right? They may
send signals to the Wi-Fi package. They
may send signals to the hard drive. So,
those are all how CPUs communicate with
the rest of the world.
Okay. So, packaging technologies are
developing on its own. So, for example,
today we have this packaging called
multi-chiplet
um or chiplet uh multi-chip module
packaging or chiplet technology. So
consider today the highest end CPUs and
GPUs are all chiplet based technology.
So if you consider one thing
when we say Morse law the original Morse
law saying the number of transistors on
one chip doubles every certain number of
months right does this count
this like by the original definition
this doesn't count because there are so
many chips in there right and they can
comm combine the chips in one package in
one product
so that's Why
in this figure if you look at this
figure there are many of them on this
corner are multi-chip technologies. So
Mors law is growing in many different
ways that Gordon Moore himself cannot
imagine by that time. There are many
different like
u creative ways to continue mors law
and we'll talk about why multitude
module is so important this years. Then
uh TSMC also announced a technology
called wafer system on wafer s then it
should be announced in 20
um
2027 so next year. So what's the
technology? So you can see here this is
called a package and this is called a
interposer. Sometimes we call it
interposer sometimes we call it sub
substrate. What is a interposer? is
basically a layer that provides
communication of these chips. Right? So
um we say chips or three there are three
tiers of network in chip network in
package network and off package network.
So each layer consumes like the lower
the layer they consume more energy and
they're slower right. So with the
interposer it provides faster network
than going off chip going to the PCIe
bus or something else right that's why
this technology is so important.
>> So is this the same thing as the system
chip? Um
no system chip is
is basically you have different modules
different IP cores what is IP cores for
example uh Wi-Fi module uh memory
controller those are different IP cores
or CPU cores GPU cores accelerators
those things are integrated into one
circuit that's a that's a
uh SOC system on chip Um so a chip can
is not only about the CPU it's
everything. So that's system on chip.
Then uh system on wafer is more uh like
a packaging terminology. So it doesn't
really have to be a ter uh it doesn't
really have to be a system. For example,
a manufacturer may just want to produce
a super large GPU. Yes, they can. They
just many many GPU chips and they put it
on a wafer right that's possible. So
it's just different terms in different
domains. But as you can see the
interposer is a piece of silicon. What's
the largest size of a silicon? It
depends on the wafer right? So the wafer
is the maximum size of a silicon. That's
because that's the piece that we can
slice. So system on wafer is probably
the largest net we can imagine on this
type of technology that's expected to
deliver high performance communication
between chips. um probably we can see
super expensive devices coming out in
2027 or 2028.
When we talk about chips design, we have
to talk about uh defects and yield. What
is yield? Yield is on a piece of wafer,
right? This is a wafer and when they
produce chips, they actually produce all
of them together, right? They produce
all of them together.
Then um
later on they slice it.
So
there are several thing um so sometimes
just imagine a piece of dust or a hair a
piece of hair that falls on it. A hair
is micrometer level or even
millimeter micrometer level right. So it
can hit thousands, millions of
transistors like pretty much a hair
falls on a piece of chip that chip,
there's no way to use it. So we talk
about like dust may just randomly fall
on these wafers when they manufacture.
Even they have super clean rooms that
have airs keep blowing from top to
bottom. They have to wash and then put
on those special clotheses all day long
um to work in a super clean room. then
um low yield may be always there and
especially when we have smaller and
smaller transistors the yield is getting
lower and lower. So if you consider we
build a we build a wafer and many of
them we have to discard the cost of
manufacturing a chip is rising right but
if you consider like where this dust
falls it's a distribution is follows
something like a gshian distribution or
like a 2D poson distribution then the
larger your die size each chip the more
likely that a piece of dust fall on it
right then that means the larger die
sides generates low yield
okay so that's why larger high-end chips
are so expensive because while you were
producing this number of chips a lot of
them have to be discarded and that's one
thing
now see these are patents of this wafer
which uh part of the wafer is not
So this is very likely a piece of hair
that falls on it or a piece of long
things that falls on it that makes this
stripe not working. So what's going on
here?
This is very likely caused by a reason
that your mask is slightly like like a
few
um arc second twisted in the center.
It's okay. It's not that bad. But if
it's not perfectly aligned on the side,
it just have no way to work. Okay.
And this is probably more like uh
something happened in center, something
happened here. This just about
um probably some misalignments or
something falls on it. But this is a
very common pattern. Then it's always
like this that the center tiles are more
likely to be good ones than on side are
likely to be the bad ones.
See what's next then. So what's the
largest D size that we can see today?
And this is also from our data set. And
you can see there are a few large ones
that's one kilo 1,00 millimeter square.
But those are multi-chip multi uh multi-
there chiplet technologies, right? The
combined we have to combine all those
chips together. For single chips, that's
pretty much 80 800 millime square. So
Nvidia H100, Amidia A100, those are all
fall in this region. We have no way to
continually increasing this number
because of the yield difficulty. And
another thing is because the light comes
from a single source, right? So it
somehow needs to be scattered a little
bit, right? So if it's scattered, it's
not that precise. So we cannot really
have each each of them
um very large.
So that's why the number of the largest
dice size pretty much limits the number
of transistors that we can have. The
only way to increase transistor is to
make the transistor smaller.
Okay. And they're doing something even
more crazy. They know probably there's
always there's no way to avoid
problems with those chips, right? So
what they do, I don't know if you heard
of this. This is a screenshot from
Apple. So they sell
8 core CPU with four performance cores
and there okay they sell 8 core GPU, 10
core GPU and 10 core GPU.
Why they have two different versions?
Yeah.
Yeah, that's right. So, they may detect,
okay, two GPU cores are not working.
Rather than wasting it, let's sell it as
lower-end devices. Okay, that's why you
see MacBook Air has this weird seven
core GPU design. It's probably just one
GPU core is not working. Okay, and
actually chip pinning
is almost always there. And sometimes
they even do something like this. The
demand of this is really high. People
like to buy low-end devices. But the
yield is pretty good. Then we produce a
lot of these things. What they do is
they just use software to disable 2GPU
cores and sell as this thing. Then
there's always hacky person hacky
people. They just say, "Oh, we can use
some software to turn it off so that we
can pay the price of this one, get the
quantity of this one." So there's always
something called a chip lottery. So you
buy a chip not all the chips are the
same. They are this different than that
difference, right? Um so even you see 10
cores perhaps what they actually have is
12 cores. When they you say 2 megabytes
of cache they probably build 2.4
megabyte of cache just for redundancy so
that they can sell um reasonable device.
Okay, this thing is called chip bin and
sometimes this chip bin may impact
performance. Let's say these 10 cores
are may connected with a network, right?
Maybe this network these two are closer
to the center faster. These two are fast
away from the center slower. Just
examples. Then you might you buy a chip
that the center one is broken. Then I
buy a chip the side one is broken. So
they both have 10 cores GPU but they may
have slight different performance. That
can happen.
Okay. Then on the other side, uh we're
talking about energy consumption. Now
what's the energy consumption? Today
we have this term called TDP, thermal
design power. So this thermal design
power is not the actual power that is
design that's consumed by this this
chip. If we really want this chip to run
faster and faster, if we can use a
liquid nitrogen as a cooling method,
then we can make this it consume a very
high power and make it run really fast.
But this TDP is designed to say in a
typical case I want my chips to work in
this way. Let's say uh my laptop is
running some reasonable like Figma,
Microsoft Word, Adobe, Photoshop, then
my my computer will consume 100 watts of
energy. Okay. It's it's the suggestion
to suggestion for what type of cooling
method we really need.
So
it's stuck. It's just slow. It's
probably
large
large image. So with less than 25 volts,
we probably can just use passive coal
cooling. 45 volts we need a fan. 200
watts we need a liquor cooling right
it's just suggestions but what's the
typical um TDP so at early age you see
the TD TDP are at this range right and
the blue ones are CPUs the orange ones
are GPUs CPUs are rather stable like
tops at about 100 then these years
they're definitely growing and we want
more and more powerful devices then GPUs
at the beginning are only low-end GPUs
then start we start higherend GPU and
GPUs because it's more flexible that you
you always buy the whole thing from one
company like including the cooling
technology they can have much higher um
TDP so typically that the highest TDP
today we see are 300 volts or 350 volts
but still there's a limitation that we
cannot have that much energy consumption
then so remember uh when we say go uh
the mors law. The last part actually
that part is describing this thing
called Dar scaling. So what standard
scaling says as transistors get smaller
their power density stays the same.
So in other words, if I have a 80 8 mm
square chip, no matter if I use 3
nometer technology, 7 nanometer
technology or 20 nome technology, they
should spend the same amount of energy.
Okay. So is standard scaling still
holding then
pretty much if you can see these are
energy consumption watts per billion
transistors.
So
and on this side is watt per millimeter
squared. So this thing is actually
reducing. So per transistor energy
consumption is reducing. Then transistor
per
uh energy consumption per millimeter
squared is rather stable other than 7
nanometer technology.
So these are rather old data when 7
nanometer just comes out. Then I took a
data I took a new data relative
recently. It's not as good as the
previous one. But as you can see here u
as we increase the die size the TDP is
somehow increasing right it's somehow
increasing. As we increase the D size so
the TDP is somehow increasing. So I
would say Der scaling is not as
um valid as Mors law today. So standard
scaling is seriously being challenged
and even you look at this one it looks
like is rather stable right it seems
standard scaling is there
but when der scaling was first
introduced it's supposed to be a
device level matrix that means no matter
what we do we don't need special
technology we build that chip that chip
will consume that energy that amount of
energy
Today den scaling if we really do that
thing den scaling will not hold because
we have one thing called dark silicon
effect. What is dark silicon effect?
Dark silicon effect means if you want to
consume that amount of energy if you
want to stay within TDP we cannot have
our whole chip to be working at the same
time. So we either have to turn off some
cores, turn some part of memory, some
caches or we just turn some fine grain
registers off to save energy.
So this is called power gating. That
means we just do not provide power to
part of the chip so that it can stay at
the stay within the TDP level or
sometimes we even reduce the frequency.
So for example, you pro probably have
most experience if your phone gets too
hot it feel really slow right. So that's
an example that der scaling may not
simply hold that we may need system
level software level technology or
architecture level technology to help
these things to keep holding to help
scaling to keep holding.
Okay.
So morsel and der scaling are probably
the most important um guidance for the
performance that we can achieve today.
So I would say der scaling is a more
like a physics law. Morris law is more
like a psychology or business law is
because people are expecting is growing
that fast that I have to do I have to to
win the competition. have to reach that
level and they just start to think about
new method to reach that level.
Okay, just a conclusion takeaways for
today's lecture. What is computer
architecture? It uh it connects the
device technology with applications.
It's the center of the computing
technology stack. It's uh leading the
chip design industry. So we're
considering a few generations away then
it's the backstage hero some of some
ultra fast chips. So you may think oh
the power comes from smaller and smaller
transistors but to make those
transistors to work then we may face
lots of lots of new challenges that we
have to use some novel architecture
solutions to solve those things. For
example, power gating or fine grain
power gating. Those are all technology
architecture level technology that we
have to have those new technologies to
make 7 nanometer, 5 nanometer, 3
nanometer technologies to work.
Okay. So next week we're going to start
with combination logic and sequential
logic and uh a little bit on the boolean
logic.