okay welcome back to machine learning
compilation hello everyone so
um in the last week we started our first
lecture and giving an overview of the
whole process of machining compilation
in this lecture we're going to talk
about a particular component in the
machine learning compilation process
which is called tensor program
abstraction okay let's be
so here's the over outline of today's
lecture
to recap in the first lecture we'll talk
about
what are the key elements in machine
learning compilation first of all
there is multi-dimensional tensor or
multi-dimensional array that help us to
store the input output and intermediate
results of model extrusions and then a
tensor function encodes the computations
among the input and output
and
usually these two are really key
elements that can that you know
encapsulate the process machine and
compilation a lot of the optimization in
cmlc is about how can we take a set of
cancer functions transform them and
getting more optimized ones to be able
to
help us to get other more optimizations
minimize dependencies and solve other
goals that we have in mlc
among those set of tensor functions one
of the things we're going to look closer
today is what we call permittive step
so when we're excluding neural network
or machining exclusions
they are it usually involves several
steps for example in this particular
example of a two-layer neural network we
have the first linear layer
that
then followed by a bias add
through a non-linear activation function
another linear layer and a softmax so it
contains really several steps
a successful machine learning framework
will be able to interrogate
implementations from
different parts and being able to
execute that model uh exclusion
end-to-end
however one of the very important
components here is how do we implement
this specific step and how how do we
implement a specific add function here
and
this particular element is called
primitive tensor functions or primitive
functions in certain cases people call
them tensor operators
and usually these are
tensor functions that correspond to a
single unit of computation if we look
that look at it from this from end to
end view of course you know there can be
more detailed implementation of this
particular parameter function but from
this global neural network or machine
learning model extrusion point of view
is this operation is kind of permitted
so our question
here today is you know again coming back
to key elements of machine learning
compilation
and the idea of abstraction and
implementations the question we all have
today is you know
what are possible ways for us to
represent a primitive tensor function
and what are the possible ways that we
can use to optimize
a
parameter tensor function okay
so um just like we talked about in the
last lecture the perimeter tensor
functions
appears in both in mlc process and in
all cases it also appears in common
machine learning frameworks from home in
that particular case of of a lens 128
we could do something like now getting
true python tensor together and then
called patch.f function so in this case
torsion and that can be viewed as a
primitive tensor function in a pi
portion
of course under the hood touch that l is
a bit more complicated that also still
handles things like output memory
allocations type conversions and so on
but in this particular usage we are
trying to restrict it so that we are
only calling it for
an input array of
lens 128 or 108 we're going to store
that directly onto open area that that
up that is previously pre-allocated
so
um a question that we have you know of
course touch dot ad itself is a way to
represent the permitting function what
are the other ways we can use to
represent a primitive function
so
this comes back to our conversation
right with
in terms of abstraction implementations
uh in the last lecture we talked about
you know the abstraction refers to
different ways we can use to implement
the same system interface
so for a permitted function like add
we can implement in in ways like torch
dot add which is kind of like a one way
to directly represent that as you know a
call onto a library function which then
get dispatched onto
some of the underlying implementations
of that addition function
of course we can also directly express
a set of operations we need to perform
in order to
realize this addition function so for
example in this particular case we could
write it out
just like a python code that expresses
you know hey in order to compute this
array computations we are going to do a
for loop over a range 128 and we are
going to you know do this addition
functions based on the iterator
that we have on it
or more commonly actually um you know
there will be
usually those operators are implementing
more like a highly optimized low
low-level
primitives
and those low-level primitives can be
implemented in either from a c language
or sometimes assembly language so so you
might want to you know try to
implement this using a c function
so at least you know in this particular
style we already got three ways to
implement the same tensor operator
function or tensor parameter function
that adds the true vector of
length 120 to 28 and you know they are
different abstractions right so in this
case uh the on the left hand small torch
add add is just a symbolic placeholder
that says you know i'm going to call
harsha add function in the middle it's a
poison function that uh
that represents the the computations
that we're having here and on the right
we can view the c as another way another
kind of abstraction we use to represent
the the primitive functions
so the question that we have
and want to keep in mind is no as a part
of mlc process
which abstraction we want to choose to
represent primitive functions and how do
we can how do we do effective
transformations among us okay
but
okay now assume that we have a
an abstraction for
permittive functions what what can we do
with those abstractions what are the
typical
mlc process that i involved
in using those primitive functions
um so a common way to to inform uh
permit function transformation in mlc is
simply you know you take in uh
uh you know deployment form of
machine learning model extrusions that
contains a specific primitive function
and try to map that onto another one for
example one one possible optimization or
possible transformation we can do
is say on the left hand side and this is
addition function
that is written in a plain for loop
and we're going to transform it
to on through the right hand side
of course this pseudo code is not
exactly the
code that you will expect to write in
python but just to give a higher idea
what it means is that you know we're
going to parallelize
this outer loop hopefully through using
multiple calls
and then we're also going to
uh we're also going to you know do those
additional computations you know enough
in a unit of four so the idea is that
you know if i have a vector
that
contains 128 element
what we're going to do is we're going to
divide it into pieces where each of it
contains four elements
and
each computation in here will try to
load in
four elements from a
and another for element
from b
i'm going to use this function to
perform a addition of that four element
in a single shot right so in that sense
uh the
the primitive function
implementation on the right hand side is
certainly can be more efficient than the
primitive function implementation on the
left-hand side
so
in all cases many machine learning
frameworks offers you is the ability to
be able to
look at the primitive functions that we
are using in our machine learning
executions and try to dispatch that or
try to or try to you know directly
translate them onto more optimized ones
based on the targeting environment of
interest for example if we are looking
at environment like cuda environment
maybe what we want to do is want to call
into libraries if while looking at a cpu
environment like arm maybe you want to
make use of things like a vector
instruction like a neo instruction that
are native to the arm platform
okay so this is primitive function
transformation is kind of like
i would say the most straightforward one
of the most straightforward
transformations that we will apply
in an mlc process
one interesting thing that you can find
is that in this particular case
the only difference between the left
hand side and right hand side are
this
realization of the addition function
assuming that all the rest are the same
for the purpose of the
of of this particular example
of that what we need to do is we just
need to pay attention on these permitted
functions themselves so we don't need to
worry about the overall execution
because effectively as long as they
present the same interface hopefully
they can be incorporated in the same
overall execution process
so
what we can do here
is
we can look at
the permitted function transformations
along independent from the overall
end-to-end computation
remember that this is not the case for
all the mlc transformations we'll in the
future we'll talk about transformation
like operator fusion that's going to
involve both the changes on
the permitted function side as well as
the changes on the overall extrusion
side but for the purpose of the today's
lecture and for the purpose of a
particular transformation we just need
to
think about how can we take a primitive
function and you know effectively
transform it to a more optimized version
now different approaches that most
frameworks and mlc system takes
of course the easiest way that we can do
here
is to simply remap it to library calls
foreign if we are doing
adding a cooldown environment
what i'm gonna do is we're not going to
write out this for loop so so
effectively there's no this follow you
just get
originally at your high level you will
know that it's the add function and what
you are going to do is you are going to
directly map that
onto a
cuda
function which
you know we can implement in cuda or you
know in or you can directly invoke the
native libraries that implement that
effectively
this is the most common approach in
most of machine learning information
this is still a very important one
uh
that ensures that we gather good overall
efficiencies and we'll discuss that in
the incoming lectures as well
and
on the other hand besides this kind of a
call string mapping that you want to
detect take is the barcode
box operator you move that onto cuda ad
operators we also
want to do
more fine-grained program
transformations
which you know
in this case
assuming that in the original program
can be written as a for loop how
effectively can we find a way to
transform that onto a possibly more
optimized implementation
and
remember that you know depending on
approaches
whether you are doing simple library
mapping or fine-grained transformations
is a core sequence in terms of countable
abstractions that we are going to use
example if we only care about
library call mapping
the abstraction we can use for
these machine learning executions can
stay at a relatively high level we just
need to know that this is uh add
and you don't need to unbox that to say
hey here's the looping here
but if we want to be able to do more
fine-grained transformations
like no we want to be able to start from
a loop and and transform that onto
this uh onto this parallel for
implementation then we will need a
different kind of abstraction
of course you one might ask you know why
do we need more fine-grain
transformations
this is because there are always
trade-offs in terms of complexity for
example you know if we are going to
simply map every single library course
then we will need to create that mapping
for every high level primitive functions
to
every platform target and a lot of those
have to be
manually implemented which consumes a
lot of resources
but if we do more fingering
transformations maybe we will find out
that the transformation for
add is similar to the transformation for
say a subtraction so that we can reuse
that
approach
to let to be able to optimize more
tensor primitive functions
as much as possible okay so that's the
general motivation on why we might need
different kind of abstractions for
fine-grained primitive function
transformation
okay so hopefully right now we kind of
understand what is a primitive function
is and you know that's the need of being
able to transform between implementation
or parameter functions next we are going
to talk about an abstraction for tensor
permanent function which is the tensor
program abstraction
so specifically
a tensor program abstraction focus on
transforming the loops transforming the
loops
and the loops and layout
of possibly fused
primitive operators
and so so the this is a code
that
expresses the possible
tensor program
for this vector additions of 128 so this
is the example program instance
in tbm framework
there are a few key features that a
typical tensor program will exhibit
so first of all
uh
you know there are three key elements in
here first of all
uh you know the tensor
program usually contains
a multi-dimensional input and output
buffers in this case it definitely
contains input output for the input
output
on the other hand a lot of cases we can
also have temporal buffers that hold the
intermediate results
the second element of the tensor program
is that it will usually have a loop net
that try to you know iterate over
multiple dimensions and try to derive
the compute compute iterations
across these multiple dimensions
and finally
for the given loop that will be
corresponding compute statement that
that runs the corresponding computation
these are like the three key common
elements of a tensor program
of course you know this particular
example is
in tbm which is
one of the machine learning compilation
framework
uh depending on which framework you are
gonna look like look at or you know the
approaches specific platform might take
the specific cancer program
abstraction might look slightly
different however all the three key
elements are always here so we're
looking at loopness computations and
multi-dimensional buffers so of course
in this particular case we are looking
one dimension so it's a single
dimensional buffer but we could imagine
that we can also do additions for
you know two-band two-dimensional matrix
or a three-dimensional tensor as well
okay so once we have
a tensor program abstraction
uh one of the things we want to think
about is what we what can we do with
with it so
um
why do we need a tensor program
abstraction as opposed to simple
expressions as a high level
high level
high level permittive like just playing
at
or another question we can ask is
you know what if we just directly use
lower level
uh code to as an abstraction for our
parametric tensor program vampo i could
directly say use a c program or buddha
program to express the same tensor
program computation is that possible the
answer is
it depends in a long cases you know the
answer is maybe uh because remember our
goal here is not only to be able to
represent
um
a permittive tensor function
we also want to be able to tran
effectively do transformations among
them of course but if my implementation
is a low level c program we will be able
to take that low level c program for one
variant of implementations and we can of
course implement another variant but
that that will cause additional
engineering so the question is now can
we actually leverage some information
and do
effective program transformations
to be able to get a more optimized
version so we're going to do very soon
in the next slide
so why do we need a tensor program
abstraction so the key here is now i
want to be able to carefully design
the tensor program instruction that
enable us to be able to do what we call
program-based transformation so instead
of
instead of having
developers to manually write them to
manually write like one form of code on
the left-hand side
and then another code on the right-hand
side
want to be able to have a way for us to
explore
possible program optimization so that
for our initial state we can apply some
program based transformation which will
explain the next few slides
so that we can you know take initial
state you want to apply the
transformation and eventually will get
through the other state
and i want to do that using using
program rather than you know having
another engineer and go and craft this
this additional part because you know we
there could be a lot of possible
uh implementations of the primitive
function and our goal is actually go and
find a relatively optimized one
and supply that i want to be able to
explore
that possible space of of primitive uh
programs being in this case
and and one of the cool one one of the
key thing here is i want to be able to
carefully design the abstraction so that
it help us to do this kind of
transformation
but before talking about the key points
in abstraction let's you know
dive into possible examples we can do
like what are possible transformations
we can do for a given tensor program
that contains multiple loop tests
buffers and computation
the most common transformations we can
apply to this kind of tensor programs is
what we call a loop transformation
in this particular case we are using a
pseudo code to demonstrate know what are
the possible
what are possible transformations we can
apply
to a permanent tensor function
so here is a
code example for adding two
vectors together
and we're going to do some programmatic
transformations in this case i'm going
to say that i'm going to obtain this
loop i'm going to call split to split
into two loops okay so if you are going
to run this
of course this is pseudocode so it does
not directly christmas directly
roundable case
um but it will give you a lot of idea of
what kind of transformation that we can
apply on those tension programs
so if we rule this
we're going to get
uh another variant of of programs you'll
find that
instead of x in here we're going to get
x 2 and x i this particular iterator is
is being split onto
two possible iterators
and
we can use this same
expression to recover the original x
right so this is called loop splitting
so we'll be able to split the loop
iteration too of course if we only look
at loop splitting it's not so
interesting right because
effectively we are doing same kind of
iteration you know over one directions
a loop splitting is kind of like a basic
building block for what we can do next
in the next few steps okay
so after we do the loop slit the second
thing we can do is we can go and reorder
some of the
loops
in in this case you know we got get this
original program
and assume that i want to reorder the
two order of looping here
it's going to give us
the code or on the left on on a downside
what you can find that only difference
we're going to reorder the iteration of
these two loops
for this particular
additional example actually these two
programs are equivalent to each other
except that the iteration order is
slightly different
and actually depending on
how we are going to
the underlying implementation you know
these two variants could have like a
different kind of extrusion efficiency
so you can find that you know this kind
of program transformations is an
effective way for us to get
different variants of programs without
having to directly express them on
directly writing down you will be able
to directly use
a transformation permit to transform
amount
and
there could be more pragmatic program
transformations but when these are kind
of like two examples of possible program
programmatic transformation that we can
do
and finally you know
if you are familiar with gpu what you
can do is you can try to bind some of
these
some of these iterators onto
the gpu strap blocks and then eventually
you will get something like a gpu kernel
that
that allows you to run this particular
code on gpu okay
so to come back at a high level what we
can find is that
you know
in order for us to be able to optimize
the permitted function we will get
these tensor program abstractions that
allows us to represent the loopness
computations as well as my on all
multi-dimensional buffers will get a set
of transformations that allows us to you
know
transform
this code on left-hand side and
eventually through these sequence
transformations it's going to give us
another code that's you know implement
the same purpose but likely you know
depending on your implementation it
could be more or less efficient
and this is a great way for machine
learning compiler to be able to explore
possible
kind of optimization transformation that
we can do on the on on target
environment
okay
of course we cannot arbitrarily
transform any program in for example if
my uh if i'm going to change my program
slightly
on to on this one
that where b kind of is dependent on
uh the iterators of
of of a different loop domain of a
different loop location so
yeah in a previous program regardless of
what xo and xi are
these statements this computer sigma are
going to execute independently from each
other
but in this particular case if i'm going
to reorder this tool you'll find that
the program is no longer equivalent to
the previous one
so in compiler this is called loop carry
dependency it means that you know if i'm
going to do loop iterations like one
iteration second iteration or so
iteration there could be some
dependencies that among those loops in
this case because the b is going to look
ahead
uh a local value that's ahead of you
know it's exercise iterations and simple
cause problems we're going to reorder
this too
that's why we cannot directly use
well there are two approaches here so
first one kind of approaches we can go
and analyze the program really try to
discover and discover hey there's these
dependencies that we
so that we cannot do this transformation
and there are uh class of works that go
and do that
and uh and in certain extent it's it's
also very useful to go through that
approach
another approach that we can take here
is we want to try to add extra
information in a tensor program
abstraction so that we can
we can avoid such kind of transformation
so we'll be able to discover that hey
you know
in this particular case it's not
something i want to transform but
most of the cases are interesting don't
have this kind of loop carry
dependencies in most cases
in a lot of dimensions because of the
nature of tensor computations we can
perform a lot of them in parallel so we
kind of really
will benefit us to have that kind of
information
so coming back to the
to the tensor program abstraction
examples we listed in the in the in the
beginning
um one of the key things to hide in here
is that you know this is called tbm
script so it's a way to express tensor
program in a python ast
and then in this particular case
it looks like a python but there's
additional
annotation here that says that no
i'm going to
have a vi which is iterator that
corresponds to
iterator of lens 128
and in this case i'm going to assign i
to vi but i'm also going to assert that
hey this is the iterator and my
requirement for iterator is that they
have to be
the here spatial means that you know
where is spatially independent so so if
we have like a two-dimensional uh output
matrix or output computations we have
like two spatial axis
and and the idea is that for any
uh for any iterator locations like from
if i choose
vi to be zero or if i should choose vi
to be a one and i if i exclude an
arbitrary order they can be executed
without any dependencies among each
other so this kind of like this
additional information that we add in a
tensor program instruction that can help
us
that can help the system to be able to
reason about this this information and
leverage them to be able to do
optimization example if i know that hey
these particular computations
only contains
spatial iterations that are independent
from each other then there's a great
degree of freedom that we can go and
parallelize most of these
iterations either through gpus or
through cpu thread pools
okay
so we've talked a lot about uh tensor
program transformations and what a
tensor program is
now uh let's start to try to you know do
some real cool examples and see what it
really looks like in a
machine learning compilation framework
now that we have talked about the tensor
program functions and abstractions
uh let's start to try to see you know
what are the possible things we can do
if you want to try things out in action
so
today we're going to
do a quick walkthrough
of a tensor program and tensor program
structure and tensor program
transformations on a real machine
learning combination framework tvm for
the particular purpose of this course we
are going to be using some of ongoing
development that
are not yet upstream so
we'll provide
a packaged version for mlc in particular
so that we'll be able to talk about some
of those connections when we are
building those upstream together and
some of those additional
additional features will also become
part of tbm in the new future
okay
so to begin with one of the things that
that we want to do is we want to be able
to construct a tensor program and
transform them
so
in specific in here what we are going to
do is we are going to
import so the first step we are going to
call pip install mlci nightly that gives
us a package that contains all the
necessary dependencies that are needed
for this particular course
and then
in here what we're going to do is i'm
going to import tvm
and
in this particular module what we're
doing is we're trying to use a feature
called tvm script
that uh
try to you know take a tensor program
and trying to you know
convert them onto an in-memory
representation in this case it's my
module
although this code looks uh
like a python code it's not exactly
a python code that runs on python
interpreter
it's a code that which kind of leverages
the pricing ast so we're embedding the
tensor program abstraction in python and
we'll be able to also you know take
actions on them like building a
roundabout module that right here
actually later okay
so once we have this um
have to have these modules in in place
there are few things we can do with it
but
the first thing that i will do is that
we're going to check the type
of
my module here
and if i'm going to run this it's going
to tell me that you know this is of a
type of ir mode so in this case ir
module
is a container that we
it's a data structure that we use to
store
a collection of tensor functions so this
is going to be
uh
you know you know also in the future
lectures we're going to come back to
this concept of our module effectively
contains a collection of functions right
so in this particular case it only
contains this main function here
but in other cases in the future
lectures may contain more than the main
function itself okay
once we have this r module there are a
few things we can do with it
um of course in in this case we don't
have to exactly inspect what it is
because you know there's already
this uh declaration here but in other
cases if you get a module then you don't
you don't know if i if i'm getting a
modem you're going to transform it i
don't know what it is then what i can do
is i can try to type
type of um sorry not type i can try to
print out
a
script function
here
and what it's going to do it's going to
convert that back into tv and script
format so you can find in this case
roughly this printer alcohol looks
exactly the same as coding here
with a few additional information like
um like if you look at the code below it
contains information like uh
the
uh reason rights or these annotations
that annotates for this particular
compute
block that's going to read the
corresponding regions of a and b and
write on the corresponding region of c
these are informations that can be
helpful for us to go and run
transformations of the code
okay
so another thing that we can do is you
know we talk about
uh tensor program abstraction and how do
we transform it so so the one of course
the next thing that we can try to do is
can we go and try to transform this
tensor program
in particular case now calibre and
transform this ion module
to do that we're going to need a concept
called schedule
so
which is a helpful object to help us to
be able to
transform a mod so what i'm going to do
is we're going to create tbm
tier.schedule which is a auxiliary
helper class that help us to go and
train allow us to do operations on them
if i directly do schedule the module
it's a bit it's a contains a current
state of transform code
so right now
if i directly do script on module.script
it is the resulting modules you can find
that you know this is going to be
exactly the same as the original one
but as we start to try to change things
things can become a bit different
so the first thing we want to do is we
want to be able to split the loop just
like you know in a slice so what i can
do is i'm going to first get a block
so i'm going to do schedule dot get
block of c
it's going to be give me that block
and once i get the block i can get a
corresponding loops so i can say i
equals
schedule
dot
loop
and
of that particular block and in this
case because i only have one
one loop so likely it's going to return
an
array of last one i'm going to unpack
that online
okay
oops uh there's no get looped i got this
to get loops instead of that loop
because we can get many loops from here
bingo that's right so once again loops
the next thing that i can do is i kind
of
um
schedule the split
now we're going to ready to split the
loop so i'm going to split
the loop and we can say factors
so on this particular example let's
assume that
i'm interested in
[Music]
what do i do i'm interested in split
into a factor of four just like what we
did in the lecture so in here what i'm
doing is i'm going to do
things like i zero
i want equals
maybe maybe i'm going to split into even
more you'll sing here instead of two
loops
so
i like to
i'm going to split it in this way okay
so up this operations
and let's try i'm going to do
print
of
schedule.mode.script again
you're going to find that this
particular program is is different
from my previous probe
so you can find that
this is a first of all there are three
loops in here
that correspond to i0 i1 and i2 so so if
you look at this line and here they have
three loops like i zero i1 and i2
and secondly and if you look at original
one original loop is length of 120
the second thing is you can find that in
terms of loop loop length
is four four eight right so this is
because
you know the this this first point with
a four here
this corresponds to the four here
and eight is automatically deduced
because
128 divided by four and four times one
is eight okay
the service thing is that
uh the iterations are mapped correctly
right so so the new bi equals i zero
times 16 plus i1 times 4 times i2
so after this operation you can find
that the schedule.mold.script
gives you
a different
tensor program that is equivalent to the
original one what we are effectively
doing well we will transform the program
by splitting the loop okay
we can do a few further steps besides
loop splitting for example another thing
we talked about in lectures we can do
loop reorder so we can do things like
reorder
then i want to reorder i2 and i1
there's two loops
and after reordering
let me try to print out again
and you'll find the change is quite
subtle right you have like you know i2
and i1 instead of
i1 and i2 so the order of the loop get
changed
and we can even do some further
operations like from huawei things that
was quite typical we want to be able to
parallelize on the outer loop
so we can do things like arrow
i zero in here
and then
[Music]
try to print
out the code again
and you'll find that
the outer loop here becomes
a parallelized loop okay
so what it shows you is that this
ability for us to be able to construct a
tensor program abstraction and using
this schedule right as a tool for us to
be able to incorrectly transform the
tensor program
to different states and these
transformations will help us to get to
some of the final optimized program
there are more examples on the so you
will be able to find the code example on
a notebook being provided there are more
examples that you can try out including
how we can go and construct
these
this tensor tensor tensor program
functions using uh expression dsl as
well as how can we you know take that
further try and do some optimizations
for
the
uh for the machine for the matrix
modulation code
so one final thing we can do is we talk
about how we can transform the code
right but effectively after
transformation we still want to be able
to turn it into a suitable form
so in order to do that what you do
is you do things like rt mode equals tv
and your build
so the build function
is going to take a ir module
on the left hand side
and
in this case i'm going to specify target
equals lvm because lvm is
is a target that we are going to use on
cpu
and so once you
compile so this is a bit like compile
function it's like invocations of a
compilation that takes in a module
which you already transformed
so so you know if you if you're feeding
the module of schedule dot mode it's
going to compile something that
leverages since like parallations are
outside if you are going to feed it into
the original module then it's going to
be the code that doesn't leverage for a
privatization so
so once we have that we'll be able to
get a function out from the runtime
module
here
and then
so in this case this function
is uh what we call runtime pack function
so this is a type that that in tbm is
used to represent
a function that we can go and run
exclusions on okay so we will be able to
invoke this build function in python
shortly so the same we can do we can say
a equals tbm.nd dot array
and we want to construct data from numpy
so
i'm going to construct it from numpy
here
load
and let's say
the
i'm going to do
once
then
okay
the time equals
so these two will will construct two
arrays that
that we can use as input
here's array a
and here's array b
[Music]
and let's also construct the output
array
t equals c equals tvm dot nd dot array
the reason that we want to construct the
output array as well is so that we
simplify the burden of a lower level
tensor primitive function so we only
need to now they don't need to worry
about computations without worry about
like a shape allocate
data allocation and so on okay
so we're going to construct this array
and uh
of d type equals
32.
now we have these three arrays
what we can do
is
let's see
okay so i think it is because the shape
is expected to be
tuple
now we have this three arrays what we
can do is we can
go and uh try to run through a function
function a b and c
are three arguments that we run
and then finally
if we go and check the result of c
you'll be able to find out that you know
actually see
actually this particular function
actually that code correctly
okay
so what's happening behind the scene of
this build
is that
we are going to take
this function of again we are going to
take the
schedule dot
mode dot
script
so what's really happening in build
is
effectively we are going to
fill in this module
onto a build function
that gives me a runtime module
which contains a collection of things
and among them right
they contains this particular function
here that i can go and invoke and this
particular function
uh
kind of implement this particular
set of
tensor program
that is describing here
so a typical mlc process
uh what we can do is we can take in an
existing tensor permitted function
in uh in in the tensor program form and
we can run a set of transformations like
do reordering splittings
and the parallelization other
transformations
and and then compute function to get a
corresponding runnable functions that we
can run on the on the only on the
operators of interest so this is kind of
like an overall flow
of tensor program abstraction and how we
can leverage test program rejection to
do program transformations and
optimizations
so you'll be able to find this notebook
on the course website that contains a
few more examples you can try and play
and hopefully you enjoy the first
attempt here
okay so um come back to the summary
uh in today's lecture we'll talk about
uh
two things right first of all we talk
about the concept of primitive function
and how it relates to
the overall executions of n to n mole
extrusion
and secondly we talk about tensor
program abstraction which is a effective
way for to represent primitive tensor
function operators
the key elements of tensor program
include multi-dimensional buffers loop
nest and computational statement
and one more key here is to enable us to
do program-based transformations that
allows us to optimize tensor programs
and
in those cases the actual structure
inside a tensor program abstraction can
help us to perform provide more
information to enable such kind of
transformations because today's lecture
does not cover all the possible
optimization transformation that we can
do on has a program is just to give us a
first step towards the tensor program
abstraction part in the next lecture
we're going to talk about how we're
going to teach everything end to end
and then we're going to come and iterate
to bring more advanced optimizations
onto the tensor programs and end-to-end
workloads as well
thanks for attending today's lecture and
i will
hopefully see you all next week
you