Okay, so before the spring break we talk
about cache. So let's finish the basic
cache introduction. Then we go back to
the pipeline design part. Okay. So um as
a quick review, it's still in the same
uh slides. So I didn't start a new file.
I didn't share a new link with you. Uh
but this is the same file. So if you
access the link from last time, you can
still go with this
uh this set of slides. So we started
with talking about the interface of the
caches. So basically caches are
typically designed in a programmer
transparent way. So if you want to
access data, you access into the memory.
You give it a address, then it will
provide the data for you or you give you
a if you give it a address and the data
you can write a piece of data into the
memory. Then you're writing into the
cache. You you actually don't know if
you are writing into a cache or writing
in the memory because the cache is fully
transparent to you. So what you can
guarantee is you write into a cache you
write into the memory system later on
read from the same address you should
get your updated data right that's the
only thing that is guaranteed by a
memory system. So cache is designed in a
transparent way that only for
performance improvement. So we talk
about what is actually stored in the
cache. Since the cache stores a subset
of data, not only we store the data in
the cache, we also need to have extra
information for what data is being
stored there. So we need to store the
addresses as tags there for as part of
the caches, right? So we know okay this
piece of data is typically 32 byt, 62,
64 byt or 128 byt which is called a cach
line. that what which cache line it is
identified by the address.
Okay. So we then we have talk about
three different caches and direct mapped
the cache way associative cache and uh
set ass way associative cache and fully
assoc associative cache. Okay. Okay. So
what's the difference is basically you
can consider them as the number of
comparators um that is
equipped within this cache unit. Okay.
Then there are two key terms here. One
is the set.
Okay. Go to that slide.
One is the set and the one is the way.
And you can consider this if for a cache
line for a piece of data it can go to
multiple locations. So there are several
ways to go. There are two ways to go or
four ways to go or or eight ways to go.
So if it can go to eight different
locations then we're saying there are
eight ways to go and this is a eightway
cache right for a piece of data. Then uh
what is a set? A set just consider a
dictionary, a map or set in a uh data
structure concept. A set basically
stores a group of different things,
right? So every element within a set
stores
different cache lines. So how many sets
are there? Then it really depends on how
large your cache is, right? So the
number of by side the bite size the cach
line size the number of sets and the
number of ways when they're multiplied
together is the total cash
size. Okay. So um
just a this is a quick review of b
assessive cache and it's probably one of
the most important part for you to
understand how cache works in a computer
architecture.
um
in in the domain of computer
architecture. Okay. So way associve
cache you can consider this is the basic
design or the midground design and then
if we push it to one end then we have
the fully associative cache. If we put
it to the other end we have the direct
mapped cache. Um there are two extreme
of the spectrum. Direct mapped means um
there's only one way to go. So a cache
can a cache line can only be stored in
one location. Now fully associative
cache means there are n way to go. N is
the number of cache lines within this
cache. The number of slots that's
available within this cache. So for a
cach line it can store anywhere it
wants. Okay. So what's the cost here is
the comparator. You really need a lot of
comparators in a fully associative cache
for every cache line. So just consider
how much data you're consider you're
storing in the cach line. you're
probably only storing 64 byt of data,
right? So that's 64
64 byt that's 512
registers 512 bits, right? Then 512
bits. Then you consider how many how
many gates are there. Now a comparator
also requires the certain number of um
transistors. So the overhead is really
high there. But if you have a directly
mapped, you only have one comparator no
matter how large your cache is. Right?
So going on that end of the spectrum,
we're designing high performance caches
with more resources, high energy
consumption, uh large die size uh
requirement. On this side, we reduce the
die size requirement, but the
performance is lower because we have
more chance for cash lines to conflict
into one cash line. So more likely we're
find we're u in CPU or GPU design we
want to use some midground. So we use
four-way associative cache, eightway
associative cache. Occasionally we have
16 way associative cache. Uh we only
super large cache we have seen um 32-way
caches. Then almost almost no more than
that. Okay. So some for some really
small caches or some high p high penalty
caches then we can use fully associated
method.
Okay. Then we talk about replacement
method. So uh because the cache can only
store a subset of the memory, we have to
say when there are some when we bring in
some new data, we have keep some
existing data out, right? So how we can
select the uh victim and there's
different ways but the common ways are
uh LRU the least recent used but there
are some um not as commonly used method.
not as commonly used method as um first
in first out or random or most recently
used uh um eviction method. Then if you
want to develop some special eviction
method then it should be no okay it's
not something super strange.
Okay, so last time we stopped here. We
want to talk about missing status
holding registers. So let me slow down
and this in today's lecture we're going
to only focus on two parts. One is
missing status holding registers and
search. The second thing is write
policies. So so far everything we have
been talking about are how we how we
read from the caches, right? So we want
to talk about how we write into the
caches and writing is much much more
complex than reading. So let's go with
here
still um review here.
So let's see this when we have a cache
read the A then we if if it's a cache
miss we send the request to bottom right
then we set we when the bottom memory it
takes a few hundred cycles it can take a
few hundred cycles and to return the
data the A is stored in the cache then
we respond to the core so but while this
while the core is process waiting for
this data to return. The core may keep
going may issue another request or
sometimes the cache may be not serving
one client it may be serving multiple
cores or multiple upper level caches at
the same time. So the cache may be
processing other type of request then in
just look at this example when we are
accessing A we the core may send another
request B to the cache. So can we proc
process B? Can we even start the process
of B before A returns? And we want this
thing to happen because we can improve
concurrency, right? We don't really have
to wait because the cache is not doing
anything. The cache itself can do
something while the memory is doing the
work. So we want to do something. So how
we can do it? Um the thing is we need to
understand what is going on with the
cache interface. What is between the
core and the caches. So this is a little
bit the u going into the domain of
network on chips. Then this is the
typical
interface between two components how
they communicate with each other.
And so this is we typically call this
type of design a
specific interface. Right? What does it
mean by specific is we have something
like address bus, data buses, available
bits and the ready bits, right? These
are specifically designed for memory
access. Uh but there if when we talk
about NOC we can either use this type of
specific buses specific interfaces where
sometimes we can have a generic
interfaces. So then if it's generic we
can only we are only sending bytes or
bits to the destination without really u
that we can serve for multiple goals.
For example we can do address
translation or we can do memory access
or can send other type of command
through the interface. Uh so here this
is a specific bus for address trans uh
for memory access. So that's why we have
address bus data buses available bits
and ready bits. Data bus are two
direction. Address bus is always from
the core to the C sideite.
Okay. So then network on chips or
networks are
sequential logic or combination logic.
So we cannot bypass these type of
things. So what is going on is basically
we have a set of registers.
Now the core will just when the core
wants to send some data to the bus it
will simply write these registers when
it write into this register next cycle
the register data will be popped onto
the wire so it can be read from this
side right on the other side for the
ready bus is always go from this
direction then it's the same thing for
data bus it can be birectional but here
let's only talk about from core to cache
side.
So
what's going on is basically we have a
cache we have a combination logic here.
This combination logic will take some
input from the core side then will send
the generate output either to the data
bus or to the ready bit or to some other
wires that can tell the core say the
data is ready or the process is done and
you can send another request.
Okay. On the core side there's another
combination logic.
This combination logic will take input
from the cache side and generate input
and it will also take some input from
the core side. Say the
um the address generation part it will
generate request and put a request into
these registers. So in the next cycle it
can be sent to the cach side. Then just
be careful this is a loop right? There's
a loop. then it's very okay for it to be
a loop because the
communication always happen in the next
cycle. So in cycle one for example in
cycle one I send some data onto the
register then in cycle two this
combination logic can read from that
registers can receive it. Okay.
So
now but but you also need to consider
the cache side. It's not only a
combination logic. It's more complex
than that. It's a sequential logic here
because it cannot really complete
everything in one cycle, right? It can
either go to the bottom or locally do
local heat. Even a local heat is not a
single cycle thing. It may take multiple
cycles to load data. So we can consider
in this way. This is a combination logic
for read it will take data from here
then it will send let's say for example
readmies right it's the readmies it will
send a request to the bottom the memory
this is cycle one then some cycle later
in cycle end we send the data back right
now we can go for data ready we can send
through the data bus
then So when we are sending the data to
the core we actually need to know the
context. So say which request that we
are responding for uh
just consider sometimes we need to bring
a request ID back to the core site and
sometimes we're not only serving one
core we're serving multiple cores at the
same time. So we need to know where
we're sending the result to. So in this
case we need to know we have we need to
have the context for this information.
That means when this data returns here
when we're ready when we're sending the
request response back we actually need
to refer what's going on with the
original request so that we can prepare
the response properly for the core side.
That means
this register cannot change data because
throughout this transaction we need to
refer to the data there. It's like a
note there that stays there that we keep
need to refer it back. So that means if
there's a register needs to hold a
context that means we cannot move
forward we cannot really update this
data right we cannot update this data
until our whole transaction is done. So
how we can just tell the core say
um how we can tell the core say oh
you're ready to give us a new request
it's done by this ready signal. So when
we're done when we don't need when the
cut side do not need this information
anymore we'll send a one bit signal we
send a one to the core side. Then in
cycle one,
in cycle one the ready is sent,
right? In cycle two, the core will know
ready,
it's ready. Just con imagine the core is
a combination logic. whenever on the
cycle it receives this ready it also
receives um probably a queue of
transactions that needs to be sent to
the cache site right so also in cycle in
cycle two we can access the queue
of transactions or at least the some
memory that stores what's the next
memory transaction we need to send to
the memory so then immediately in this
cycle We can send
request two.
That means we write into the register.
Write it into the interface
register.
Then in cycle three, the cache
will receive
new request.
Okay. So this is a handoff process. So
it starts by the cache
sends a ready signal to the core side.
Then when the core side receive a ready
is one that is ready to remove whatever
that is in this register side. We don't
need to delete everything anything. We
just write new data to the registers in
the in cycle three. The cache can start
a new cycle a new transaction.
Okay. So
this type of design
is a very common type of like onoff type
of network on chip design. Then say if
there's a buffer on the receiver side
and there's a buffer on the sender side.
Then we always send a ready signal. Then
you tell me when it's ready when there's
a buffer slot open then we can send one
piece of data to the destination side.
Then yeah at this side we also have a
one available right. So at cycle two we
also need to set available
I should write to here available
equals to one. We set available equals
to one on the receiver side. We know
okay there's a new uh request
that arrived at this cycle.
So that means we cannot really remove
the data in the register while the cache
is processing data, right? Because we
need to know the context. So we need
them but we really need the cache to be
able to process in parallel. How we can
do that? We can simply set another set
of register on the catch side so that we
can remember the context. Okay, we can
remember what is going on. So then we
can
we then we can if we have another set of
register on the cache side we can allow
this set of register to change
independently. We can always remember
the context when we send the data back.
So how we can do that? Let's look at
this. The first thing is when there's a
cache me when there's a cache heat
it's almost immediate. It's very fast.
Then we have no way to paralyze much.
Right? So in this case we can simply
surf first check in tax then go to in
the storage then we can get the data and
we send the data back to the core site.
And here I I just want to add a little
bit more thing here. Uh previously you
see the block diagram right? We write
there is a comparator and there's a
multiplexer.
um this type of block diagram that's
really a textbook level cache design
that's basically considered a cache can
be done in one cycle because there's no
basically there's no sequential logic
there other than the cache itself right
there's no memory there so remember we
can use uh like half cycle tech
technique or rising edge or down edge
technique to be able to load data in one
cycle so on the textbook we can really
load the data in one cycle time. In
reality, it's not that easy. If the
cache is large, we need some multiple
cycles to read the data. Then in also in
reality, we probably need multiple
cycles to look up into the tag. Then
there are many other things can happen
within the cache. So what is actually
happening is even the cache itself is
pipeline this pipeline. So while one
transaction is looking up cash tax the
other transaction is probably accessing
the storage. So it works in a pipeline
style. It's a in reality how cash are
designed but I don't want to go that
deep. Let's just stay it like this.
If it's a cash heat we consider it's
very fast that we cannot paralyze
things. So we first look into the tax to
see if it's a cash heat or a cash miss.
Okay. It's a cash heat we go to the
storage. Then the transaction the
request the data can go back to the core
side.
Then if it's a miss what we do is we put
a set of registers.
This is ms missing status hold
registers.
What it holds? It holds missing status.
Right? So we have a cach miss. We hold
the context of this cache miss in this
set of registers. We record say which
cach line we eventually want to write
it. What's the request ID? Who is the
original sender? It really depends on
the architectural design. But the data
here is rather flexible. Just record
whatever data that is needed. It serves
as a context. Right? Then
so when there's a cache miss then we on
one side we write the
context in into this missing status
holding register MSR on the other side
we can immediately send the ready to the
top.
Then when we send the ready top this set
of register is free. Then that means we
can send set we can write another
request into this set of registers. Then
the core side and the cache can process
the second request in parallel.
Okay. So you can consider this register
missing status holding register is a
shadow of this registers. It actually
contains more information because it
already go through the tag. It stores
eventually on which cach line which way
which side we want to write the data
back.
But whenever this missing state host
holding register writes data then this
register can be freed up then so that we
can write another request there.
Question
>> yeah we'll talk about that.
So it's write some data there. So
um let's look at how it's used and we'll
talk about its limitations there.
So situation one,
let's say if there's a miss, we check
the tag, we immediately know it's a
miss, right? Then we need to go to the
bottom to send a request. But while
we're sending it to the bottom, we write
a transaction here.
We write a transaction into the missing
status holding register. so that the top
registers can be freed up for another
transaction.
At this time while the bottom the memory
can take hundreds of cycle to return the
data we can process other requests. In
this case if there's another request
comes in and it's a cache key we can
directly respond to the top. Okay, just
be careful here. We are introducing
we're introducing a reordered response,
right? Which is a reorder response. That
means
the transaction two,
we receive the transaction two after
receiving transaction one, right? But we
respond to transaction two before
transaction one.
So is this allowed? It depends on the
core. Okay. So some cores can allow this
type of out of order return. Some course
cannot determine this type of cannot
accept this type of out of order return.
Okay.
So in this case how we can deal with
this problem? If the core let's say if
our core cannot accept out of order
return what do we do?
Yeah, that's right.
Everything can be solved by one extra
layer of indirection.
So
if our core say or architecture is level
or micro architecture level say we have
to return in order what we do is this
say this is a core
we add extra layer called RO or re
reorder buffer here.
Okay what is a reorder buffer? Reorder
buffer is a buffer right let me write in
this way ro it's a buffer
so when the core send a request to here
to this interface
it just first go through a RO stage you
can consider RO is a stage of the catch
or consider it as an independent
component so we write into a slot they
say if these slots are occupied it will
rise into the next slot that is not
occupied
will right here. Just basically record
whatever that is in this set of
registers. Then
it will
this is a cache, right? Then it will
just send request one by one to the
cache side. Okay. Then the cache
in this case we have to have a request
ID. So then we when we return we know
where we need to write it back, right?
Otherwise because it's out of order
returning so we don't know where it's it
is um we have to have the request ID so
that we can know where we're returning
to. They say if we return in this order
we first return here. Can we send this
one to the top? Now quick answer is no,
right? We cannot really write this to
the top because this is out of order. So
we wait. We just write this response
here.
Okay, we have we write the request here.
We also write the response here. Then
hold it. We hold it until this is the
beginning of this buffer, this queue.
Then let's say if after that we get this
response.
Okay, if we get this response, we
actually don't need to write this set of
registers because it's at the head of
the queue. So in this case, we can
directly write this to the core. send
this response to a core and say okay
this slot is freed up.
Okay, this is a reorder buffer. The it
always respond from the beginning of the
header then sends down in order. Then
here this is out of order response.
Then this is in order response
then a reorder buffer can achieve this
type of goal.
Okay. Then comes to the question
when you write a software when you write
a program especially when C++ or Python
or Go is available you consider a slice
is infinite in size right you can just
fill whatever that is into this um into
a slice uh into a array into a list then
for hardware design it's never infinite.
you really need to consider what's the
larger what's the size of RO so for
example if I at the beginning I design
this is a 32 entry RO
I can only store 32 entries right now
when this RO is full what happens
when this RO is full we just stop we
just cannot send the request from the
core to the ROB what we can do is just
hold it here just hold it in the
interface register
never move forward. Then if it's stops
the instruction pipeline, yes, just stop
it. Okay.
And this is the first time you hit one
term that is called back pressure.
What is a back pressure? Let's consider
there's some resources here. Okay, just
consider if this is MSR.
If MSR is full,
it will stall the RO. The ROB will start
to start to build up. When RO is full,
it will
impact the pipeline in the core,
right? It will impact the pipeline in
the core. So the pi the pipeline in the
core cannot move forward. So this is a
back pressure from a downstream buffer
to a top to upstream buffer.
Okay.
So, back pressure is something that's we
typically observe. So, there's one way
that we typically analyze performance.
Just look at the pressure. Just look at
buffer pressures. Then if buffer
pressure at one place is high, that
means something below it is not draining
fast enough.
Okay? So, just look at the buffer level.
It's a very it's a very quick way to
identify performance bottlenecks.
Okay.
Then let's come back to here MS chart.
Situation two double miss on the same
address. What do we do? They say
transaction one we are missed on address
A for example.
Then we send another transaction
accessing the same cash line. It doesn't
have to be the same address. It just the
same cach line.
Then what do we do?
Then the question is do we really need
to send
with MHR? We do can send two request to
the bottom, right? We can send two
requests to the bottom. And the question
is, do we really need to send another
request to the bottom because we're
running reading one piece of data,
right? So when it returns, it will be
the same piece of data anyway,
right?
It won't be another piece of data and
then it will be have the same content.
So what we do is we simply write into
MSR. We record a second transaction into
the master jar. Then we stop there. We
don't send the transaction to the
bottom.
Okay, there's no need to send the the
second transaction to the bottom because
the MS chart we know there's already an
ongoing transaction to the bottom level.
The data will come back sometime later.
So as so we just wait.
Then in this case we have two different
ways to design this MS chart.
So what are the two different ways?
Two different implementation ways. Let
me draw this here.
So the first way is we can design in
this way. This is MSR entry right. We
may store request uh we may store
addresses
a DDR
uh way
set this type of information. This is
where eventually when this data comes
back where we need to uh write this data
where we are going to write into our
local storage
uh multiple request. Okay. Then we can
have a list here. So for example we can
have four slot and we have recq ID recq
ID recq ID recq ID. Okay. So that means
we can at most call us four transactions
into one
MSR entry.
Okay. So one way to design it
if we set this request ID to four. Okay.
There's another way to design it is just
to do this
add
way
set
request ID.
Then have another MSR entry DDR
way set request ID and so on.
Okay.
So I typically I don't think they're
very very different but just consider
one thing.
If you know how many times
it's very likely to call us, then this
is definitely a better way, right? And
this saves space because we're only
storing one side of address way and set
and
this common information.
But if we have multiple request ID more
than four that accessing this, then what
do we do? We can have two different
ways. We can e either just stall it, do
not let go through, then wait until it
comes back or we can go back to this
way,
right? To write another entry.
Um, it's also okay. So, this way works
for the case where we have a lot of
concurrent requests to to the same
address. If we're doing this, then we're
assuming this do not happen very much,
right? do not very happen very often.
Two different ways to design the uh MSR.
So we say MSR is a natural coaler here.
What's a coaler is to combine multiple
transactions into a single transaction.
So if there are multiple requests going
from the top that's accessing the same
cache line can be different address
within the same cache line then we can
combine them and we can only send one
transaction to the bottom so that the
traffic the pressure the load to the
lower level of cache or the memory is is
lower.
Okay. So yeah, I should have another
slide. But anyway, if you consider when
this comes back, when the data comes
back, what do we do?
On one side, we definitely need to write
into the storage, but only need to write
into the storage once, right? I only
take one cache line. So we have no way
to have two cache lines that is going
two cach lines storing the same address.
Then we write into a storage. Then we
send two responses in two different
cycles, right? Send two responses to the
core side. Send two responses. So the
first one is for the T1. The second one
is we simply look at the transaction
into MSR. Then we send we say oh there's
another request that is requesting the
same cash and we just send another
request to the core side. Okay.
Sometimes the core is smart uh enough so
that it can re it can ask you to only
send one if it's co coalable.
Um some cores are not that smart. You
have to send two request two responses
back to the core side.
Then it can even just consider if the
cache is serving multiple clients then
it's even better right you send it once
here you send it once there but you only
have one transaction going to the lower
level memory.
Okay, let's look at situation three.
Let's say if we have a M T1 transaction
one, that means transaction two. They're
accessing different addresses. In this
case, we need to take two different MSR
slot. Let's assume we only have two MSR
slot and two when there are two MSR
slot, we can have two transactions going
to the bottom. So the m the number of MS
chart determines the parallelism that
this cache can provide and how how many
transactions how many paralyzed parallel
transactions can go on at the same time
to a lower level of memory.
Then in this case if we have another M
T3
what we can do
then we we need to allocate a MSR slot
before it can go on right in this case
there's no MSR slot available so what we
can do is we hold it in the tax stage
right it's just a pip a pipeline stall
now we have to say just the the tax will
stay there and doing the check the MSR
is available is available
check again and again until the MSR
becomes available then this can this
miss T3 can keep going right then
consider a back pressure problem it can
go back to the core and eventually cause
the core pipeline to stop this something
that you want the least
so when there's a data ready T1 comes
back to the core side we we write into
the storage we send to to the top and on
the other side we also send this
information to the um MS to the MSR.
Then the MSJR knows oh this transaction
is done. Then we just remove this entry.
So mark this entry as available. Then in
this case when it becomes available T3
can go through then storing the T3
information in this MSR slot.
Okay. So MSR resources can be a scarce
resources. Okay, there are a lot of
scarce resources and the storage can be
scarce resources. The MSR slots can be
scarce resources. The reorder buffer can
be scarce resources. The interface the
memory interface can be another uh
scarce resources. There are many scarce
resources that we need to
t the typical design is we need to
balance those scarce resources. We want
them to be used up at the same time
rather than say
MSR is full but everything else is
empty. This the something that we want
the list.
Just consider this example.
If we have two caches,
okay, two L1 caches,
then we have two MSR
and two MSHR
here, right? Then there's L2 cache.
What is the
reasonable number of MS char this L2
provides and what is the reasonable
um
like parallelism or how many
transactions this L2 can provide
So and just give some MSR count for this
L2 right one two 3 4
5 6 7 8 what is a reasonable number here
or at least what numbers we can
immediately the cross out.
>> H one seems bad. Why?
I have two of them. Okay, we can cross
out one and think about eight. Do we
really need eight?
So
L2 eventually connects to memory right.
So if it's L2 means it must be L1 means
because it arrived at L2
right. So how many interest at most this
MS chart can have.
So this L2 can at most process four
transactions at once. Right? Let's only
talk about read at this stage.
So that means
if a read go through
it will take one MSR space another read
it will take one MSR state right the
same here this read and read it will
take MSR state so at most four read can
arrive at this one before it can be
resolved
right So in this case the number of
misses that this L2 can have is also at
most four. So I write smaller than equal
to four. So basically there's no there's
no point to have more than four MSR
because we'll never use those things.
Right?
Then do you really need four? And
sometimes you can if you expect this L2
to have very low M rate
but for most of time I would keep it
about two or three to make it good
enough right so let's consider this L2
cache will some have some heat some
misses right so we don't really need
four now we'll choose this is a probably
reasonable range for this one for this
L2 cache
okay at least
Are you okay with this? L2 will never
process more than four requests at the
same time. Right? So we have to done
complete one then we can take another
one.
It's like a batch processor that we have
to complete one before we can take
another one.
Okay. So this is MSR. Now we go with
write policies.
First time we're dealing with right how
to write data into cache they say how
writing happens there's something that
we can consider here are some examples
that are consider writing
uh not all the possible cases so let's
say when you write we also know it's
address right we know the address what
do we do with right heat
or at least what are our options for
this action
Right. He hit
we know okay this cach line is storing
this address
then yeah.
Okay.
So if we're considering other cache
lines that's a prefetching issue. Uh
that means if we need we access one cach
line do we need to access other cache
lines? Then
uh let's keep it simple for this stage.
Let's do not consider let's consider
every catch line is um in independent
um
okay if you really need let so one cach
line is already 64 byt or 128 byt we
already consider spatial locality so if
you really have larger spatial locality
just increase the cach lines
so here we have two choices one choice
is we can write into the local storage
where we can write directly right to the
bottom level right um so there's there's
something that we can decide right so if
we write only write into local we have
one problem so we have a different
version of data in the cache and the
memory if we only write into the local
okay so in this case we call this cache
line dirty and this one is stale both of
them are bad but dirty is not bad is
only saying the version in this cache is
newer than the version that's in the
memory.
Now if we have another cache, we have
seen this problem in the GPU side. If
there's another cash wants to read the
data, then if it has a stale copy of
this data, it will get incorrect value.
Okay, then this is a cache coherency
issue. It can only be solved by cash
coherency protocol. So this is not
something that we are u talking about.
But at least eventually at the end of
the program we need to write the data
from the cache to the memory.
Okay.
Now on the other side for write miss
what are our cases? What are our
options? The first option is we just go
through we just write to the bottom
layer directly without even writing into
local storage. Just skip it. just
assuming we'll never use it anymore. Now
on the other side we can
on the other side if you consider a
special case if we really want the data
to stay here to stay in the local
storage because probably we're only
writing four byte of data right if we're
only writing four byte of data and we
want this data to be stored in this
storage we really need to
read the data first from the local level
then get the data so that we can merge
merge into the storage. We'll talk more
detail here. So it becomes really
complex. So I'm just saying there are a
lot of things to consider for the
writing process uh of a cache. So there
are a few policies typically are two
families of policies. One is called
right through policy. One is right back
policy. Let's talk about right through
policy here.
So right through policy let's consider
right heat. Right through policy says
if there's a right heat
we write into local
at the same time we also write into the
bottom that means for every right no
matter if it's cash or cashme
always directly right to the bottom
level okay it makes the coherency easier
to manage
then let's say If we're doing a write
miss
assuming it's a 64 byt line and we only
write four byt of data for CPUs this is
very common it's very unlikely we're
writing a lot of data right we don't
really know the rest of the data so we
write only a few bytes
so how we can write to the bottom
the first choice is we just write we
don't even do anything at a local at
local level. Okay, just write to the
bottom. Then we skip local storage. This
is the easiest way. So this is where the
right through method comes.
Okay. Then a second
method is if we really want to
eventually want the data just keep it in
the storage.
What do we do is
because we only have four byte of data
but we want this cache line
in the storage to contain the most
recent version of data. We have to read
from the bottom to get the other 64 byt
of the data. Okay, we read this request
and for every read we consider it's a
miss. Although this is not the original
miss transaction but this is a right
miss. So for every read transaction we
go through MMS MSR we take a slot we
read a to the bottom.
Okay. And in this case when the data
comes back the data ready a comes back
we do the local right by merging the
data ready from the bottom and the local
right take four byte from the original
transa transaction 60 byt from the
bottom response then merge them and
write into a local then this this cach
line becomes available then in the
future we can keep working on this cach
Okay. So this process is called right
allocation. What's right allocation?
Right allocation means when we write in
case of right means do we allocate a
cach line a cach line slot for this cach
line. If we do allocate and we say this
is a right through with allocation.
Okay. Right through with allocation.
Then the other case,
the other case if we only have this
transaction. Now we don't have local
right we just directly write into the
next level next level cache. We say this
right through without right allocation.
Okay. There are two different versions
of right through caches.
There's a special case we need to
consider is a right miss. Sometimes we
can write the whole cach line
and this is the ideal case. This is very
uncommon for CPUs but common for GPUs
because GPUs is so wide and that we're
writing so many things at the same time.
After coalesing we can easily write
whole cach line at the same time. In
this case we can do right allocation but
we have the updated version the whole 64
byt ready in the request. Then we can
directly do the local right. We can
directly go to the fifth stage without
going to the third and fourth stage
without reading from the next level
cache. Okay. We can directly write into
the whole cache line here.
Then what about eviction? Eviction is
something that we need to consider how
we can evict a cash. So in this case, if
there's a cash line, this is a cash line
that takes the cash line slot that
eventually want to occupy,
right? So this cash line stores another
piece of data, not the current address.
So what we do with it? We evict it. How
we can evict it? Then eviction
since we we since we know this is right
through cache that means the next level
cache always have the most recent
version of the data right this version
is not newer than the next level so we
don't need to have another right to the
bottom level we can directly say use one
flag one bit to represent if it's was
valid valid means it has the newest the
data we can use this piece of data. We
can convert it from one to zero to
convert it from a valid state to a
invalid state.
Okay, just convert from zero to one.
Then we know okay this cach line is not
valid there. Then don't use any
information including a tag and
including cache from there.
Okay. So we directly mark this as
invalid. Then we can change the block
pack. We can change it to the data to
the address of the data that we want to
write into this storage directly. So we
mark okay here this this is another
cach line that is stored in this slot.
Okay. Then right around.
So right around this is a weird name.
Sometimes you can hear this name. Some
people talk about these names. Some
people do not even talk about these
names. So, uh, right through is a rather
standard name. Right back is another
allocation then everyone who have
received the computer architecture
education should understand what it
means. Okay. So we have talk about right
um the previous one was right through
with right allocation.
This right around is right through
without right allocation. So sometimes
you need to be careful about right
through because right through is not it
can be a like right through on a broader
sense or right through on a narrower
sense.
So basically right around is right
through with without allocation for when
we want to write the data
then we just write through no local
storage don't need to allocate a piece
of data. So we don't need to consider
those reading process, merging process.
This right always go to the next level.
Okay. The right means
here's another design decisions that you
can make. Although I don't think it will
make a lot of performance impact here.
So when you write do a right miss it can
for whole cach line write miss you can
either write into the storage or not to
write the local storage.
So write through and write around what's
the like what's which one to choose. Um
so it depends on how likely that you're
going to read the data that you have
written before right. So for GPUs
typically within one kernel you read
some data you write some other data they
never overlap. Very rarely GPU have in
place right back.
uh in that case right through is not a
reasonable design right around is a more
reasonable design for GPUs okay for CPUs
that typically we have something that we
write the data then we keep working on
this piece of data in a loop right then
eventually when we're done we write this
data store flush this data back to the
main memory in that case a right through
data is more likely then later on as
we'll talk about right back cache Right
back cache is much much more complex
than right through cache. So if you
design a CPU core then basically
very likely at the beginning you will
design it with a right through cache
without a right back then only using
right back as a performance improvement.
Okay then we'll talk about right back
cache soon.
So what's the problem with right
through? Why we need a right back? The
first thing is write through latency
because the next layer you don't know
what's the next layer, right? The next
layer can be really really slow. So you
for every right need to take the whole
latency to the bottom layer. If you can
say I write something then this right
can stay within this cache right locally
to the storage. And then I can tell the
core that the right is done. Then the
latency here is really low. So it's very
friendly to read and write loops, right?
Read, write, read, write these type of
loops. But here if we have a high load
to the memory that we write a lot of
data to the memory, then the latency may
be a big problem. So in that case,
especially for CPU designs, we consider
more on the right back side. write back
policy. So we keep the data local as
long as possible. So we want to avoid
writing to the next level cache. We want
to process everything within this local
level.
Okay. So what is rightback cache policy?
Writeback cache policy is talk about
right heat.
When we do a right heat,
we only want to write it to locals. we
don't write through and this is
something that we want to avoid the
latency right so just consider if we
write into this piece of data again and
again it's always stay local the latency
is really low here
then at this stage just remember we have
a dirty version of this cach line right
then the next level or the memory has a
stale version that we can we cannot
direct use and eventually We need to
write this data back to the main memory.
What about right means
when we need to write the data to the
main memory, we do two things. One is
the time when we evicted this cach line.
The second thing is when we want to
flush the whole cach line, we just write
everything every dirty line to the uh
next level cache to the memory.
So we have to talk about this extra data
that is in the
tags right in the tag array. So what's
in the tag?
What's in the tag?
The tags will store the addresses.
Right? I'm I'm drawing this part means
we don't really need a full addresses.
We only need a useful part to identify
which um address it is. Right?
Then
what else?
Valid invalid bit. Right?
We need to have one bit to know if it's
valid or not valid.
What else?
We need to know
if it's dirty or clean, right? We have
to store this information, right? If
this cach line is dirty, then that means
the memory is older than me. It has a
previous version, then whenever I need
to remove it, I cannot delete it.
Deleted means convert from V to I. We
cannot really delete it locally. We have
to make it persistent to write it to a
lower level. So we have to have one
extra bit to record if it's 30 or not.
Um for right back policy you really need
this extra bit. For right through policy
you don't need this bit. Okay. Then
later on as we talk about cache
coherency you will see there are many
other bits that we can have within one
tag. So sometimes we consider the act
the overhead of this data that is stored
here right we everything that is stored
in this cach line is the real data
everything that's stored in the tag we
consider those are overhead
this address bit
yeah it's the address Let's store say
which address that we're storing in the
that cach line.
Yeah, the data
that the data is the big part.
So we're only talking about tags here.
So we can consider this tag lookup is a
process of address translation process
from what address from the external
address to the internal address. Right?
So we need to do a lookup a table
lookup. Say we need to find oh where
this data is stored in the internal
address. Then the internal address we
don't really need the address but we
only do uh we know which way which set
then we basically know which address it
is right and we don't we don't really
need to store way set information there
right because the
because it's a big array then this is
always say way zero set zero way one set
one way one set zero and so on. So we
don't really need to store this
information in the tag. It's just
pre-arranged.
So when there's a right meat in the
right back policy,
we really consider
the the whole goal is to avoid
transaction to the lower level of
memory. Right? We want to keep all the
transaction local. In this case,
we have to have right allocation.
There's no right back policy without
right allocation. It's always right
allocation in there. I cannot imagine a
right back without right allocation.
So in this case the thing is more
complex.
So a a right at this level cache will
actually trigger a read to the lower
lower level because we need other set of
another part of the cache u another some
other part of the
cash line.
So here I just want to give you an
alternative.
Um we only have 10 minutes left. Let me
quickly give you an alternative. If you
really really really don't want a read
to the bottom, it's very weird, right?
We have a right but we have a read to
the bottom. You can do one extra thing
you. So this is a tag array other than
the address
and flags
and these are flags. Okay, those 30 bits
we can have a dirty mask.
We have talked about dirty mask before,
right? We know this is valid. Okay, but
you if dirty mask is there, we know it's
valid but with a condition. You need to
check which part is valid. So I probably
don't call it a dirty mask. A valid mask
is a probably better name. That means if
it's 64
byte, right? we use one bit
to represent four byte
that four byte is valid or not. So then
we need a 16 bit
mask.
So if we write zero
uh 0 01
in hex
or let me write f to prevent you think
this is a binary number. If 000 f what
does that mean? That means
16 byt
are valid.
48 byte
are invalid. Okay,
that is possible. Then the overhead is
higher in storage but we can reduce our
rate to a lower level. Okay. But I I
consider this is a not that common type
of design. This is a more common type of
design that we uh read from the bottom
and we merge the data back into the
local storage
and eviction is more complex here. Then
we need to they say no matter if it's a
read or write, we have a cach line
allocation process that happening. If
there's a free slot, a free slot marked
by the I bit, right? If it's it's a VI
bit,
if it's invalid, then we consider a free
slot. We don't really need to kick
anything out to use in this cache line.
But if that set or if all the ways that
eventually we can store too, right? If
all the ways are valid, then we have to
find one active victim and kick it out.
In this case, we have to start this
eviction process.
The eviction process need to look into
if this cash line is dirty or not. If
this cash line is dirty,
if this cash line is not dirty, then we
can simply also just do a V2I
conversion. Just change one bit. Then we
say, "Oh, we just delete this cash line.
We don't need to do anything."
But
if the cach line is dirty, we need to do
a write. Okay.
So this original read transaction
just say this is a read miss. Okay.
Actually needs to trigger two
transactions to the bottom. One is the
eviction process. one is the read for
the new data process. Two transactions
goes to the bottom. So in this case it
can have a even higher penalty than
write through.
Okay. If every transaction if if you
catch a cash cach miss rate cash heat
rate is zero every transaction is a meat
mean and your cash line is always dirty.
In extreme cases, this is really bad.
It's worse than right through. Okay, in
write through eviction is super easy,
right? Because you just always convert
from B to I don't need to write
anything. But in this case, a simple
read, you expect it to be really fast,
but actually it generated two
transactions to the bottom. One is for
evicting the dirty data, one is to read
the data. Okay. And eventually we have
this data ready back. Then
pros and cons is really should have
higher performance especially for CPU
design and for CPU designs it has high
perform high performance. then it has
lower lowering the transaction the load
to the memory to the next level unit but
the cost is is much more complex and
right through right through cache then
as I'm talking to you I spend about 10
minutes talk 20 minutes to talk about
right back cache probably only 10
minutes to talk about right back cache
but when I write a simulator for every
cycle what's happening at every stage
It's really really complex to guarantee
that things happen at the right
sequence. So the
one of the most annoying thing is
if there's a cache comes into the t
right there something that comes into
the tag then we need to evict something
then at this moment we already modify
the tag address and in this case we need
to apply some locks to this cach line so
that this cach line before this data
returns we cannot kick this cach line
Okay. So when we when we read something
this is when we say oh this is a cach
line that eventually we want to occupy.
So this cach line is in a transit state
that the new the old data needs to be
written back and new data to be loaded.
So just consider this timing sequence
before between this load and write
relationship. It's really really hard to
maintain this relationship. Sometimes
what happens is
say
this new data is comes back right this
this before this data comes back there's
another read that reads won't read to
this data at that time the tag is
already updated but the data is not
updated if we don't apply this log
probably we just
read another cache line it's very
annoying thing okay so let's write back
cache then it's just complex then is
expect to have higher comp um higher
performance especially for CPUs in GPUs
typically what we have is L1 cache is
right through L2 cache is right back um
in CPUs what we have is every level at
least high high-end CPUs every level
is right back caches okay the right back
cache So introduced a lot of coherency
issues. So that's something we'll talk
about. And when we have multi then multi
multiple caches may catch the same cache
lines and it's getting really complex.