hello everyone welcome back to mlc uh
thanks everybody for waiting so after
one
weeks of break we are coming back to our
machine learning compilation lectures
this is lecture six
and we're gonna talk about how can we
you know integrate everything we learned
so far
and trying to ask the question about how
can we tap from existing machine
learning frameworks such as you know
python jacks and other frameworks
onto a machine learning compilation
process
which we will then be able to use the
techniques like all of my program
optimizations and a few other deployment
techniques that we're going to talk
about in the follow-up lecture okay
so
again this is more like an interactive
course so we're going to do a more
interactive session today with ipads and
notebook
the notebook will be available on the
course website and you're more than
welcome to go and check it out in the
meantime we're also going to have
companion exercises possibly a few days
after the lecture so hopefully you know
you also try to try things out by
yourself by running them through those
compiler exercises
so to begin with um we are going to
still install necessary dependencies in
this lecture we are going to uh
actually use pytorch as example so we
are going to import pyth
and specifically we are going to use a
torch
practice module called fx which we are
going to use to capture some of the
input computation graph from pi culture
but before we do that let's review a few
of the high level concepts
uh some of them we have actually you
know used some of them in our
assignments exercises but hopefully now
we want to actually go deeper onto some
of our backgrounds so that
at least for a lecture you'll be more
prepared for
uh understanding what's really going on
so anyways we are going to talk about
this
api called test expression or te
which is a domain specific language that
we use to
that we use to help us create
uh create a set of
a set of tools for us to be able to
create a test
okay
so to begin with we are going to talk
about
okay so to begin with we're going to
talk about uh
api called tensor expression that help
us to create um a set of cancer
functions
okay so i'm going to walk you through
some of the test expression api we've
touched a point
in some of our past lectures but we're
going to review it so that we can get a
better understanding of what's going on
here
uh first of all we're going to import uh
td from tvm database
and we are going to create two
placeholders in this case this two
placeholder effect will create
two temporary nodes in a computational
graph what we're going to do next we're
going to try to connect them
with the matmo function that's we're
going to
we're going to introduce next
okay
so
each of the t place holder in here is of
type
t dot cancer
and in here the t tensor simply
represents a possible
state of nodes in a computational graph
that we can use to compose up the
tensile r functions
each of the t tends to have its own
shape field and d-type view so in this
case we already specified the shape is
128 so we can find that a dot shift
equals 128.
in order to compose up a set of
computations one of the things that we
can do is through an api called
t.compute
with the following signatures we're
going to specify output shape and how
we're going to compute each element
of the output matrices
and we're going to do that through this
particular function so you can find that
in this particular function what we do
is we take two t tensors and b
and and what we are going to do is know
we are going to compute a result of n m
so in this case
a is a strips and by say n by b k
and b shape is k by
m and we're going to compute the result
with shape is n by m
and we the way we are going to compute
matrix multiplication is through this
formula so what it says is that for each
of ij element we're going to compute a
iq times bik and sum it along
the reduction axis will shape is a dot
shape
one of the things you might notice is
that when we write this particular
t methmo function
actually we do not directly say that n m
equals under 2h so this is a generic
function that's actually going to work
for
any a and b with different kind of
shapes and this kind of a common pattern
in tensor expression library that help
us to build up generic tools to compose
those programs and generate cancer
functions so once we define t maximal
we'll be able to call c equals t methmo
and that gives us another computational
graph so after this computation
effectively what we're going to have is
we're going to have a and b
in here
that points to
c as a combinational graph node and the
operation here corresponding to
effectively this
metamod operation or this this
particular compute operation that we
have here
um
so tpm create tools allows us to you
know
take this combinational graph and try to
convert it into
uh into a prime function or tensor ir
function electricity
so because each of the loops each of the
compute here describes a set of loops uh
effectively we're going to convert some
of them onto loops and computation so
let's let's see what what's what happens
one thing we can do is we can call t
create prime function by passing all the
parameters of interest in this case by
passing in both the input and output
parameters
and there's a new api called show that
allows us to directly display the
highlighted code of the in the tvm
script form so let's try
so you can find the aqui core cream
print function it gives the prime
function if you show it you'll find that
the crease form to a tensioner function
here that corresponds to
a
b and in this case the mathematics of my
output c buffer
and there will be a list of you know
input
uh there will be list of loops that
generates a matrix multiplication
operation that we are interested
so one of the things you can find is
that actually test expression is the
it's a way for us to concisely describe
some of the tens expression operations
there will be cases in that we might
still need to write test our functions
and in the future actually we are going
to interplay some of the you know
tens ir uh test our functions in tbm
script together with the test expression
api as well you can view like tens
expression api is
it's a way for us to stitch together
some of these expression computations
and we can convert them onto a tensioner
function of interest
so right now we have done the matrix
multiplication function let's create
another function called relu
in this case we can leverage some of the
python features to actually create a
generic reality function so we can find
that you know in here it is a lambda
function the star i means that you know
we can take any
set of positional arguments so so
effectively what it says is that you
know i can do
lambda i
uh result of a of i
and it's also another function that
lambda i1 i2 two arguments a of i1 and
i2 and so so effectively this
particular
t dot compute actually works for
a of arbitrary
dimension actually in this case
we can also try it out for example i can
allocate uh a of
one dimension with shape 10 by time
and you know we can pass it through t
dot value
you can create problem function you'll
find that you will get the result that
computes you know this value of of input
you know 10.
we can also pass being another x with 10
by 20 and you can find that the same
function works
so you can find that you know this is
kind of like interesting pattern
here we are using uh we using a test
expression function that help us to
effectively generically create different
kind of programs that fits into
different input shapes and other shapes
another thing that t api allows us to do
is allows us to compose up and create
some of the fused operators
in a single tensor function
for example what we can do in here so we
can you know create a measurement
allocation and apply real
and
and in this case we're only going to
create a uh
final tension function with the input
and final output so we're not going to
uh well so the only input output
interesting we're going to input a and b
and we're going to output d because c is
an intermediate result we're not going
to include in the parameter list in this
case the crit param function is going to
automatically create the intermediate
temporal value so you can find that as a
and b
and this value
and there is going to be a metamode
which is temporal variables that
correspond to c that allocates inside
the function
and here's a mathematic followed by a
random logic
so this is a way for us to create
a tensile function that uh that are kind
of like having the matrix multiplication
rather few fused together
normally we don't have to do it in the
model ingestion stage however this is a
very useful tool in certain cases where
you know
that you want you know that fusion is
going to be helpful it's also a useful
tool for us to generate
fused operators in some of the future
transformations
in the in the last example we actually
we did not pass intermediate results
into argument list and
in some cases you know we it can be
helpful to also parsing c which means
that
we are going to say that hey i'm going
to create a function where the memory of
c is also not being allocated inside the
tensile function i'm going to allocate
outside
and you know you can do that and you'll
find that this final function is going
to contain additional argument called
metamod that correspond to c
and then this this is a program that
runs
in most of cases we want to avoid
passing intermediate values so that you
know the allocation happens inside there
are more optimization opportunities but
in certain cases you know there are
there are use cases where you can
directly pass in c as well
okay so far we'll talk about how we can
create a single test cell function
through tensor expression api
so moving next in order to build the
antenna extrusions we still need to be
able to connect multiple tensor
functions together through a
computational graph
let's talk about you know the block
builder which is a tool that helps us to
incrementally build a relaxed function
so as a first step what we're going to
do is i'm going to declare what called
relaxed variables so in a computational
graph
every node a
and b
correspond to a relaxed dot variable in
here
that
is just a variable placeholder that
points to that particular combination
ground
so first we're going to create two
relaxed variables
with the corresponding shape and in here
we're also indicating the general type
so so in this case we're indicating the
number of dimensions here and the data
type of the of the particular relaxed
variable here
in order to build an end-to-end
competition graph function we are going
to use what we call block builder
and here's the code block that
constructs an ir module
so you can find that it contains several
steps
there are a few scopes that we can
define to
that creates a certain function scope
within that particular computational
graph function
recall that particular data flow uh
construction refers to that you know
everything every computation inside that
block is going to be
is going to not have side effects so
that creates more combination of graph
functions
and then we have
several operations in here that
correspond to combinational graph
operation that we're going to walk
through later and if we run this you
will find that we are going to get an ir
module in here and it will show here's a
module so let's let's try to screw it a
bit you can find that it looks quite
similar to what we have done manually in
the past electrics right especially if
you look at this particular function
this corresponds to the combinational
graph part of it and then you have t
matmo and t value that corresponds to
the particular tensile function that
runs through
we take a quick look at this particular
condition graph function you can find
that you have
input arguments in here
and the first thing we do is we're going
to do chord here that calls into this
particular
test expression functions
using using what we call destination
passing convention that we talked about
in anti-execution section and then we're
going to do call revenue that calls into
this particular function
finally we're going to return so in this
case we are marking this gv as a global
output a variable that's accessible
outside the airflow block and then the
return value of function is gb here
so this looks quite similar to what we
write manually right and if you compare
the particular set of block builder code
that's needed to generate this
particular module you can find it
certainly shorter in a sense so that
that's one of the reason why we want to
use uh
builder to be able to incrementally
build up okay
so let's take a deeper dive in the block
builder api in this case it's helpful to
look at both the block builder code as
well as the corresponding uh relax
function on by side by side so so here's
the corresponding relax function i'm
emitting i'm omitting all the uh all the
tensor functions
if you are interested you can scroll up
to see the original tensor functions
and then there's the relax function uh
there's a block builder found uh set of
procedures on the left-hand side we can
find that there's almost a direct
response between the left-hand side
right-hand side right so you have
function here
function
data flow block scope which directly
responds here
and you know this emit t e t metamodel
corresponds to
this line
this line corresponds to this line and
so on so you can find that it's almost a
direct response between the builder part
as well as
the generated tbm script code
if you look at the elements in here you
can find that first of all there are
scopes in a block builder that indicates
that now hey here is a here's a set of
scopes i'm interested in
i i mean right now and as a result the
follow-up actions like those emit
actions is going to generate
a a instruction or
or actually in this case it's a binding
within that data block
another thing to note is that all
intermediate variables
in the ir module construction like c
here
is generally divided function called
emit te
and this function uh what it does is
that it will try to create
this call to tier to the to the tier
function actually you know te metamount
in here is different from this t event
mode the tmap mount here is a test
expression function that we defined
earlier
and then the t maxima on the right hand
side is the tensor ir function that sits
within this ion module
what's happening here is that when we
call immediate e
under the hood the block builder is
going to create a t placeholder and
tensors
run that t metamod compute then use crit
prime function that we just mentioned
earlier to create that particular tensor
function put it into the ir module and
then create a chord tier into that so it
does quite a lot of steps in here
uh
and in the end it will it's going to
return a corresponding
data flow variables in here and c is is
a particular pointer or reference to
that data flow variable
so
uh so you can find that sales type data
flow var
the data flow var is a special instance
of relaxed variable so as we mentioned
before
this computational graph looks like a
b
and
goes to c that corresponds to t macmo
and then goes to d that corresponds to
result of t ready
right and each of these intermediate
result
is being pointed as a relaxed
dot variable
and data flow var is simply a subclass
of relaxed variable it indicates that
it's intermediate value within the data
flow so it's not going to be referenced
by anything outside
if
so it helps us to kind of bond the scope
right so so we know that c is you know
inside the data flow block inside a
computational graph
for a variable to be referenced outside
need to be marked as output so in this
case uh gv is a variable that can be
referenced by outside and returned to
the to the other blocks or be used as a
input to another data flow block if the
function contains multiple data flow
blocks
so we've already talked about what's
happening under the hood in the midi
call variable if you take
this particular line is generated by you
know c equals bb dot emit t e in here
and under the hood immunity that
separates first of all it will create t
dot placeholder for a and b
which are less variables and then it
will run us through the t e mathml
function which is tensor expression
function we use to generate the
corresponding test expression
and then it will according to crit prime
function to create to create a
corresponding tensor function and
finally it will try to generate a call
onto the corresponding tensor function
through chord tier
so result communication graph contains
two intermediate values including the
result of t maxwell
and the result of the t red loop
operations
we also mentioned that you know
we can create output variables of each
of a data block blocks through the emit
output that will say that will create
output variable that can be referenced
by outside of data block the reason that
we do this is we want to try to
distinguish between
what are the intermediate or with uh
internal
uh combination graph node that are not
being referenced by outside and what are
the combination graph nodes that are
being referenced by outside so as we
start to try to change the content of
data flow graphs we normally would only
change the internal node of the data
flow
finally on the function side we will be
able to mark the return value of the
function in here
in a block builder there are two ways to
mark return values
the first way is that we can we
the first way is when we mark the return
value we can also you know specify the
parameters to the function so in this
case a and b are being specified when we
emit output
this is actually a very useful way to
specify things because in a lot of cases
the number of parameters is unknown as
we start to build these functions
through translations we want to collect
them on the fly so you're just going to
do it in the end
on that if the terminals are known
beforehand actually it's also helpful to
do in another way right so directly
specified in the
width function so it looks a bit more
like a function of signature that we
have and in practice we kind of
encounter both so the api support both
modes but you can either do one way or
another otherwise you will cause an
error in the block barriers
okay so we have learned so far all the
basic tools of building a computational
graph
using a block builder and the test
expression apis moving next let's start
to talk about how can we leverage those
tools to really interface with the
machine learning frameworks in
particular in this lecture we're going
to talk about how can we bring in models
from pytorch
onto
the ir module as well as a consequence
the following up mlc flow that we're
going to use in this lecture
and follow up lectures
so to begin with let's define a model in
pi torch so here i'm assuming that
you are familiar with python there are a
lot of uh online materials that
that teaches about pathology but
interesting to check out but i'm also
going to walk you through the code uh uh
in here so in this particular case
um this is an example that defines a
mathematic which is the same as the
mathematical that we use as a running
example in the first part of lecture
and
this torch.module
that defines a mathematical operation
right so you can find the first one and
specify a parameter as a parameter
specify a weight as a parameter then it
will run through metamode and value in
here in this forward function
so
once we have this what we can do is we
can create this and dot module and we
are going to use a specific uh utility
inside python called project
fx the torsionfx is a way for us to
actually symbolically trace
the corresponding python model
as a computational graph module here
and this is a relatively new feature but
it's a very useful feature for us to
inspect what's really going on in a pipe
model there are certain limitations like
the combination graph can cannot contain
control flow it has to be a pure data
flow graph but it's useful for a lot of
machine learning models that we see
today and in other cases where you want
to inter interleave things like you know
control for others and to waste the
combinational graph we can also try to
use torture fx to trace part of the
model
doing mlc within that pattern model and
try to put that back onto the pi touch
flow
so in this case i'm using torsion fx and
we're going to use a symbolic trace api
to trace a particular fx module
within the fx module it will have a
graph representation
that
effectively shows what is the
combination graph view
of this uh model we can find that in
this case there's two operations metamod
and relu and his output specifies the
input
so effectively the combination graph
looks like x
w which is a weight
we will have
a
match mode
in here
and then the result of metamodel
goes into relu so effectively this is
the combination graph we are looking at
so what will go is you know of course
one thing i can do is i can try to
directly
use irbu to construct
the same function right but on the other
hand the main purpose here is we want to
try to define something generic
so that we can not only translate not
only you know doing manual translations
of this particular python model but we
also want to create a tool so that
allows us to be able to translate almost
arbitrary or a majority set of fx
modules that are being traced in python
okay
so the way to do that is we would we
want to do a you know it's effectively a
translation step that starts from a
python fx module and combinational lab
and try to turn that on to ir module
that tdm recognized
okay and and to do that the first thing
we're going to do is we want to try to
create a few metrics a few things we
want to map through
the first thing is we want to be able to
map the parameters in our original
combination graph
onto
onto the corresponding uh onto the
corresponding constants in this case of
of the of the target project because
we're using constant to embed parameters
in here
and this is the first thing we're doing
here so this is called map permanent
function what it does is that takes in a
torsion parameter and it's going to
create a relaxed constant in this case
we are going to get a numpy array of
that constant and the type of the
constant is
if if the dynamic tab they have a
dimension and for here let's assume that
i'm only going to convert floaties uh
32-bit floating points of course i can
make this more generic so that you know
the data type corresponds to the data
type that to the parameters launching so
but for simplicity we are going to make
a simpler implementation here
um and another thing that so here this
handles the particular parameter part
right and next thing we are going to do
so i'm going to iteratively iterate
through the combination graph for each
of the combinational graph note here we
will try to create a mapping that maps
the uh
the original computational graph in the
torsion axis in the title fx dot node
we're going to map it onto the
computational graph node type that we
recognize in a block builder which is a
relaxed variable that represents a
translated node in the corresponding
function
and finally we do want to be able to
with and and as we iterate through the
the fx graph we want to be able to find
the output of the node um
we want to find the mapped output of the
node given the input okay
so
i'm going to walk you through this
translation function it's going to be
slightly long but
i think it still fits into roughly one
screen so hopefully it's still a
reasonable implementation okay the main
uh the main logic is this from fx
function in here
and let's take a look at this function
so what it does
is that it takes the fx module
that's a that's a module that we have
which contains the computation
representation from pytorch
um
because we're going to create something
that's specialized to input shapes we're
going to give a input shape
uh list of input shapes in here that
help us to
know that information also helps to
reduce intermediate shift
and and usually you know the input shift
only specifies
what's the shape of the input to the
model not parameters so in this case
it's just the input x
and then there are two additional map
maps both are dictionaries
that tries to map uh it's it's a
dictionary that that that says you know
for each of the core
torch function and call torch module how
do we handle that so we are not going to
define the corresponding mapping
function here but we're going to define
them in a later part and let's now
assume that the snaps are available in
here okay
and then
what we're going to do is we're going to
walk through the logic so first thing
we're going to do is i'm going to create
a block builder
and in here we're also going to
create a node map so the node map tries
to map from the original fx node onto
the translated node in the target
combination graph
and what we're going to do in here is
you know first of all we're going to
create this function called main and
because fx is the pure idea flow block
where and chris want a pure data
computational graph we can just
encapsulate inside as a combinational
graph block okay
the next step we're going to do is i'm
going to iterate through the nodes in
the fx graph in this case it knows an f5
graph already in topological order so
it's safe to just iterate through in
this topological order and we're going
to handle
the translations of each kind of node
the first type of node is placeholder so
this
correspond to the input of the
computational graph in this case we are
going to just get to the shape of a
corresponding input and this input index
is the state force is constant how many
input we encountered so far
we're going to create a relaxed variable
with the corresponding name
shape and the type that corresponds to
the number of dimensions and data types
in here
and we're going to also
you know collect it as a list of inputs
to the particular function
and then we're going to say that you
know i'm going to map this particular
node onto this input variable so in this
case
uh
for this particular graph this is x and
x type is placeholder so that's i'm also
going to draw the combinational graph
here for clarity
so this is uh
maximum x
weight here and the placeholder here is
you know why we encounter x is going to
be
hitting this line okay the second thing
is get at her so this part we can simply
skip it actually in this case get
actually effectively try to fetch
a weight within the within um
fx module so this attr function that's
implementation on top you don't
necessarily have to read it it's a
utility that specifically provided by
the fx example code and what it does is
simply tries to do
fx
mode dot weight
in here it simply get that get that
attribute okay that attribute is a
parameter we're going to call map
parameters to map that to a relaxed
function and i'm going to record the
corresponding mapping here
what's more interesting is when you
encounter things like core function and
call module
and this particular is in in our
particular case of this example actually
i'm going to encounter
a core function and in this case when
you encounter call functions this call
function can be
part
the co-function node target can be
torch
dodge
uh you know relu
or torch.magma okay and here what i'm
going to do is we're going to you know
uh using dictionary to define the
corresponding translation logic because
there are so many charge functions that
you know we can we that that need
translations
and the translational logic we're taking
a block builder a node map and the
corresponding touch node
so what's within within the translation
function what happens is that the
corresponding translation function say
touch value is going to look up
the inputs of the node and uh and in the
node map so to get a translated inputs
and then use block code block builder to
view the translated output and return to
here we're going to put that back on the
onto the original nodemap
similarly uh there there is the call
module
in this case the module corresponds to
an earn dot module
and
um you know we'll be able to actually
get the corresponding module here so the
only difference here is that module can
contain weights right that are implicit
so so besides the
original uh besides the noting here that
that contains the inputs to the module
we also need to pass in the name module
in the translation function and we're
going to look at this particular case of
translation function later as well and
finally it's the output i'm going to
record output in here this translator is
specific build assuming that there's
only one output and it's not hard to
generalize it to multiple outputs
actually
and
and then i'm going to emit my output in
here
and find as an output of combinational
graph and finally the function output
is being recorded here one thing to
notice is that we are using a pattern of
collecting the function
parameters during the translation phase
right so so that's why we are you know
putting the parameters in the end here
we are getting our module in here okay
so so far so good at least this fits
into one screen hopefully it's the
reasonable translator we can do to bring
functions from pi torch to the ir motion
now we have these functions what we can
do is we can go and apply the
translation apis in particular
um remember that you know we will still
need to specify the core function map
that there is you know that specifies
how we're going to map each of the torch
function
and then we also need to specify called
module map in this case our particular
example don't contains uh module calls
so we are only going to specify the call
function
and here's how we're going to
implement the matmo map right so
effectively the logic looks like this
first of all i'm going to take f x node
know the arcs correspond to the inputs
of this particular function and you know
the r0 is the input node
of of so far and r0 likely corresponds
to x
and
in my previous translations already
populated node map to map x to the
corresponding relaxed variable so i'm
going to effectively get the christmas
relax variable here and relax variable b
and then i'm going to call emit t of t
mathml in here to create
another computational graph node that
that runs the maximum operations okay
so here's how we translate metamode
similarly we can do call immediate
entity relu to translate the
corresponding value function
uh if i'm going to run this
oops from portrait effects not defined i
need to
run this function first
and try this again
and you can find that we get an ir
module
that looks almost like you know what we
would manually build right so you'll
find that you know we will have a relax
function that corresponds combinational
graph that calls into matmo
relu
and
and the corresponding mathematical
function here
okay so far so good
so to to summarize
the general idea of how we interact with
the existing machine learning framework
is almost most of machinery vermax
contains some form of computational
graphic notations
what you can do is you can do a
translation step that takes in a
conventional graph or sometimes a sub
sub computation that also can represent
a combination graph
do a
topological order transversions right
and try to create a mapping from an
original combinational graph node in the
combinational graph in the framework in
this case pi torch
onto a combinational graph node in our
module in this case a relaxed variable
and then we use block builder to
incrementally build up
these corresponding functions of course
a lot of stats block build also help us
to build
things like tensor functions the
particular implementation of many
functions in here right and uh one thing
another thing to notice is that we can
easily customize the translation rules
for example in certain cases maybe we
are interested in
not mapping magma onto a test expression
function but i'm interested in mapping
that on to say direct cause onto lip
torch
or according to a lower level
functionality then we can easily
customize that either in the translation
step in other cases you can translate
first and then do further
transformations to transform the ir
module to leverage the other kind of
abstraction that implements the same
feature
okay so so far we've learned about how
we
we have learned about simple examples of
you know bringing in communications from
pytorch onto
our ir module and mlc flow
next let's coming back to the fashion
avenues example that we use in the past
few lectures and see now how we can
how we can bring our somewhat real-world
python model
it's not a real world it's toy model but
you know
a model that can predict
specially aminos
classes
onto
grammar modules in this case
oh it looks like a sandal
hopefully
i i it is the center maybe that and the
recorder what model right our model is a
two layer linear neural network we have
used this model in the past few lectures
we can build it up
using a mop model in here
and then i'm going to populate the
weight manually
using the numpy arrays that we had in
before
and then i'm going to
one thing that we can do is we can you
know run them around the code through
the mlp models get arc max and that
gives you the right prediction so this
is the pythagoras prediction in here
now let's try to translate it uh
from pythog onto the onto our ir module
and see you know if we can use the same
set of logic to
to if we can reproduce the same sound
logic okay
and this particular case
this models actually leverages
earn.module so so it does contains uh
named modules within this particular set
of computation
and
so as a result we will need to be able
to define what we call core module map
that that tells the system you know how
i'm going to map each of the modules
in this in this case you know linear and
value in here okay
and here's how we're going to define
mapping of linear redu in particular the
mapping of linear is quite interesting
so besides the mod besides the fx node
we're also going to have a module so
that's crisp one to the end module we're
going to invoke
one of the things that we care about in
the module is the weight right so i want
to be able to map parameters of a weight
to create a constant in here
there's a node map
uh in here
and then in this case there is some bias
so we also need to map the biostem
and one thing i'm using here is it
remember see i'm calling on topi.n.dan
so so in this particular case a top high
is a set of predefined test expression
apis that defines this a set of
operations effectively it's is it's a
predefined thing so that you will be
able to directly according to them to
construct a set of test expressions
and top eigen.dense directly equals 1 to
x
matrix multiply of x and w transpose
and then what we're doing linear is we
are going to do matrix multiply and add
function here so in this case we're
translating saying we're translating
linear as a single functional block
right that contains both mathematical
transpose and and and bindset
in other cases you know you don't
necessarily have to do that
we will be able to actually translate it
into a single oh actually in this case
actually we are translating into two
functions so there will be a dance
function here and an add function here
but if you choose to do
in another way we will be able to you
know construct a single test expression
function that does fuse dance and add
which is also possible
and if you look at the
uh renault function it's actually simply
called into macro loop because the same
mapping logic in here
and if you're going to try this one
you can find that
we are going to get
slightly longer ir modules that contain
several functions so you have add here
dance here
value function and another ad that
specializes to a different shape
and another dance tool that specializes
to different shape as well
so this is our main function in here and
you can find that it contains a dense
operation at relu dance at
and the constants are the corresponding
constant that we created through map
parameter
okay
once we have this ir module
what we can do is we can try to
run it through our
compilation flow and then try to run the
prediction using our tool right using
the ml3 flow and you can find that it
gets the same prediction okay
okay so while we have walked through you
know several ways to interface with
machine learning frameworks
and and up until now we are trying to
map
most of these
python operations onto causing to test
our functions which is relatively low
level and it's more it's quite flexible
that allows you to create different
mappings
for optimization purposes it in
sometimes it's actually helpful to
translate
those uh computational graph node not
directly into calling to test out
functions but also according to building
primitive operators
and in this particular case i'm going to
customize the original mapping function
a bit so let's say i'm going to say that
instead of trying to map into a test
expression function for now i'm going to
call relax dot opt or relax dot
and those ops are just building ups
that that relax have
and if you run this you'll find that it
will it's going to return you a concise
relax function that i have you know add
dance relu in here
and this is a typical actually this is a
more typical combinational graph that
you will see in a traditional
combinational graph rumor
so so in the tvm we support both the
higher level abstractions like this
primitive building intensive operators
as well as causing potential functions
throughout a multi-process eventually we
will want to convert those high level
perimeter operators onto lower level
implementation so that will mean that
we'll need to convert those higher level
operations onto calls onto library
functions
or onto a test setup function that then
get code generated
and
and normally
uh if
if uh we are doing translation step
usually it's sometimes helpful to
convert those operators first on to
those building higher level primitives
when possible because there are also to
prefer certain decisions for example
if i have relaxed add on here i can see
that i can map that on to a say theodfl
library or a code generated code later
so so i can defer that decision
um using a when when i get a high-level
permanent just advantage of high-level
perimeters
on the other hand and a lot of cases the
higher level primitives are not always
available so while we're doing machine
learning computation there always needs
to create a different kind of
combination and in certain cases you
know maybe i just want to write things
like understand some operations and
other operations
and in a lot of those cases actually
it's much more convenient to directly
specify tensor functions and we also
encourage you to do so because a lot of
optimizations that photo apps actually
can work with the test ir course
directly and also offers a broad range
of coverages
in other cases there are opportunities
to actually directly specify you know
hey i'm just want to try out what's the
effect of directly using cdn in this
particular case so you will be able to
instead of translating that into a high
level function you can directly
translate it onto a library call in this
case
usually what we find is we can get the
best result by combining a mixture of
high level operator because hence our
library obstruction during translations
or you know actually doing those
transformations
after we ingest them on twice
we'll discuss those tradeoffs and follow
up vectors but one take away here is
that you know there are certainly
different ways to do translations and
they're trying to represent the same
operations
and one of the things in mlcs we want to
enable those different ways in the same
abstraction and being able to translate
among them uh being able to build them
and translate them on them throughout
the process
okay so
to summarize this lecture actually today
we are going to what we talk about
mainly is the process trying to develop
so how do we take in
machinery model of interest and put
bring them onto the mlc flow so it's
kind of a development part
we start different ways to get models
from machining firmware onto our module
our past lectures talk about
abstractions you know there are
different abstractions we talked about
hence ir there is a primitive tensor
function library course as well as a
computational graph that represents high
level computations we also talk about
you know in this case we we take a
glimpse at high level primitive
operators so that just like a
placeholder to indicate that he has
operational perform
um
a lot of the future lectures again i'm
going to come back to transformations on
how we can
transform ir module to make it more
optimized hopefully it is complete the
picture in a sense that you know we have
already talked about the developed
transform and build and run flow already
and
and you know you kind of know what the
entire mlc flow looks like
moving next we're gonna just enhancing
the flow to making sure that our
transformations becoming more and more
powerful and there are other topics that
are also interesting as well as you know
from how we can interface with formula
frameworks in different ways we're also
going to touch the point that postman in
the future lecture
and perhaps in some of our supplementary
materials
okay so here's the summary of today's
lecture you are more welcome to check
out lecture notes as well as ipads and
notebooks we also release certain
exercises in a few days to help you get
familiarized with the content hopefully
you enjoyed today's lecture
i will see you next week