Last time uh we have been talking about
the
risk file ISA then to understand how
software works at least the the next
level software right above the the right
above the micro architecture that how
the software works at the ISA level
right so if you write a C program Python
program eventually it compiles into risk
five ISA then this ISA is being executed
on the risk five core core. So today
we're going to go deeper into the micro
architecture direction than to check how
a core is designed. Now we're basically
designing a CPU core as a sequential
logic. Okay. So uh let's just have a
reminder has review of these uh
instructions. So for every risk five
instruction they are encoded by four
bytes and this data this instruction or
the encoding of the instruction is
stored in the main memory. Nothing
special from the data memory but just
a part of address range that is
dedicated for instructions to be
executed. Right? So we need to load
these instructions so that we know what
actions that the core needs to be per
need to perform.
Then we have certain operation that is
defined by the op code. Then the oprand
is the operator that we want to process.
Now we typically consider only two type
of operant. One is the register and the
other is immediate value. Immediate
value are consider directly encoded in
the instruction itself.
Okay. So let's see what we have. So we
actually skipped a little bit in the
combination logic and sequential logic
part because we didn't spend a lot of
time to talk about memory and register
files. But let's just consider them as
special
um unit
and group of registers that works in a
certain way. Right? Let's look at the
instruction memory. Instruction memory
takes one input and returns one output
because it's a read only memory, right?
We're not supposed to modify instruction
at least when we execute the program.
We're simplify this core design here. So
we take a 32-bit in input that's the
address that's the program counter right
we take a program counter then it will
return us the data of the instruction
and how how many bite it returns it
returns 32 bit and four bytes right
that's one instruction so every time we
fetch we fetch for one instruction and
we also simplify this process to assume
that it can be completed in one cycle or
in the current cycle with a rather short
amount of time and in reality
instruction fetching if it's a cashme it
can take some time but we're not going
there yet
then let's go step by step just from the
simplest one to the most complex one
data memory is slightly more complex but
not too complex so we have address right
so we call this address bus then because
it's a 32-bit in in input and there are
32 two wires that is defining the
address. So this is the address bus.
Then uh we still have the data the read
data right the data that output from
here.
But this data memory needs to support
both read and write. So we have load
instruction that read the data from here
and store instruction to write data
here. So we also need a incoming data
bus. Then in a more realistic case, the
data bus, the right data bus and read
data bus shares the same group of wires.
But still for simplification, we just
use two different type of two different
wires here. Okay, two group of wires
here. So write data is 32-bit and right
read data is also 32-bit. So every cycle
it can fulfill the requirement of either
read or write one register.
Um there is a special thing called WE
which stands for write enable. So how do
we know that if we're writing data or
not? Because for most of the time we're
not writing data. We only write data
when we're executing the switch the
store instruction. The S SW
S SW is store word not switch the store
instruction. So for most of the time
we're not storing data but just consider
these wires there's always wtages on
these wires even if you consider they're
all zero. So this unit need to tell
should I write or I shouldn't write or
the right wires have garbage on it.
Right? So we need a right enable signal
only when right enable is a one then we
write into the data. Okay. We write into
the data memory. So it's controlled by
write enable.
Okay. So now we go with register file is
just more complex but not really
different. So here we take three
addresses.
Now what's the width of the address
here? It's five five bit right remember
last time how many registers are there
defined by the standard
risk five ISA and there are 32 of them
whenever there are 32 of them five bit
isn't good enough to identify which
register we're referring to.
So if you can if you look at the data
bus then we actually have three data
buses right we have a read the data bus
and read one read two and write three
right so if we have three group of data
buses that means we can perform these
three actions at the same time in
parallel so what does that mean is we
have
A1 matches RD1 if we say we want to read
this register then it will the RD1 will
return the data from that register.
Okay, the data stored in that register.
A2 maps to RD2 and A3 and the right
write right enable three and the right
data three are another group that works
together to write data into this
register file. By the way, we never
introduced the register file. So this is
a standard register file. What's a
register file? Reser file is a group of
registers and this group of registers
share some input and output data buses
together. Okay, this is a register file.
Then the simplest one, the simplest one
is just one register. And when we say
one register is not storing one bit,
it's not one flip-flop anymore. It's
storing one number. And this number is
program counter. program program counter
stores the address of the next
instruction that we need to execute.
Okay,
so there are 32-bit in this case. So
we're only considering a 32-bit machine.
So today we're running a 64-bit machine
for most of the time. So in that case
the all the addresses should be extended
to 64.
Addresses are extended to 64 but data it
really depends on the design. Okay.
Okay. So let's start from the beginning.
We want to do load the instruction. We
know we need to know which instruction
we need to execute, right? So what do we
do is simply connect the PC with the
instruction memory address bus. Then the
instruction memory will automatically
return the data for us.
You can consider this as a sequential
logic sorry as a combination logic at
this stage. um only the P
yeah you cannot really consider this is
a combination logic because at least we
have a PC we have register file we have
data memory two memories okay it's okay
so uh we have instruction memory the
instruction memory will return the
instruction right let's first look at
one type of instruction the load
instructions the load instruction
include a few different
Uh so first of all op code then we
assume we already know the op code that
is a load instruction then there is a
there's a x6 right so x6 is a register
and there's a x9 x9 is another register
and the minus4 is an offset so we offset
the address that is stored in x9
so if X9 stores the address two 20004
it hacks representation then minus4 will
change it back to 2000 0 right so it's a
modifier so sometimes this is super
useful because if we're accessing a
strct then we know which piece of data
we're accessing then we just directly
use the registers store the strct the
initial address then use a offset to
store
the offset to represent which field that
we're accessing.
Okay, in this case we have these a few
values, right? The first thing that
we're processing is we take address, we
take bit 15 to bit 19 and what is bit 15
to bit 19 is actually storing the x9 the
address there. Right? So this is an
advantage of risk five. Remember risk
why risk five is encoded in such a
strange way. Yeah, because no matter
what type of instruction, we always know
register 15 to register 19 represents a
register,
right? So we don't need to decode it. We
can just directly split the wires and
some wires goes there, some wires goes
to another location, right? So we can we
don't need a decode stage here. Remember
in GPU we have a decode stage here. We
don't need a decode stage. We can
directly connect to
A1.
Okay. Then
on the other side we have 20 to 31. This
stores immediate number. But remember
the whole instruction is only four by
long and the address is another four by
long. So we need to do this is a special
symbol called sign extension.
What is sign extension? Is basically
extension the width of a number but
maintains the sign. So previously it was
FFC then after extension it becomes FF
FF fc right it's minus4 so they both
represent minus4 but they have different
width why we need to do this because
eventually we need to calculate the data
in X9 minus 4 they have to have a
matching width so that we can do
calculation
Okay.
Then next we do calculation.
Calculation. Now we have talked about
alou for many many times. You can
consider is a group of combination logic
can perform the operations for you. And
in this case we are performing and
operation right. Sum operation and
subtract operation are the same group of
register or same group of logic. Okay.
So we just put source A and source B
into the AOU unit.
Now we can output the final number.
Here we need the first control unit,
right? What is a control unit? Control
unit,
what is a control signal?
The control signal represents what ALOU
operation that we need to perform. So
here we're not performing logic log
shifting. We're not performing a
modification. If it supports
modification let's just this is a
internal encoding like we can use 0000
to represent add instruction add
operation then the AO will perform the
add instruction and generate this output
as the final address that we want to
access
okay
and let's keep going so eventually we
have the address then we can connect
with the data memory right to load the
data this directly feed into the data
memory. Then
once there's a signal clock signal then
we can read the data
and we read the data we get the result
and this result will come out then we
can write back to the register because
it's a load that X6 is a destination
right X6 is a destination so we load the
data from this particular address and
eventually write back to X6
let's do is let's connect back what
we're connecting back. So here we have
the data that is that is loaded from the
data memory and it goes back to WD3
uh data data bus. On the other side we
need to know which register we're
reading. So in this there in which
register we're writing. So in this case
we need to consider 7 to 11 to A3. And
remember risk five has this encoding
that the destination is always
represented by 7 to 11 right. So in this
case we can directly
connect this group of wires these five
wires. So this requires a wire splitting
the bus splitting. So it goes into the
A3. So we know we know which register
we're writing into.
Okay. Now here we need another signal.
We need to enable register right or
write enable signal. Then when right
enable signal is set now we can allow
this data to write into the register
only a3.
Okay.
So this is the whole cycle of the first
instruction.
So what actions we have performed? We
load the instruction first. Then we lo
we read from the register or load from
the register. What does this read mean?
It's basically we're convert we're
populating the register value into this
RD1 wire. Now consider there are 32
registers in this register file. Right?
So what is actually happening is
basically a big selector or a big
multiplexer that select which register
should have value passed onto this bus
here.
Okay.
Then we do the calculation. We perform
calculation. Then optionally we perform
the memory operation. If it's a load or
store operation, we need to perform the
data memory operation. If it's a regular
calculation operation, we can skip the
memory me data memory stage. Then the
last stage once we have done we get a
result, we have a destination, we have
to store the result back into the
register file as a result. that
completes a whole cycle of one
instruction.
Okay.
So let's consider a few different Yeah.
Okay. Don't forget this one. So if PC is
not updated, we stay there. We execute
same instruction again and again. So we
just add
a simple adder here. This is we're still
using ALOU but it doesn't really require
a control signal because it always
performs the add instruction. So add by
four right add by four. So four is
hardwired into this source input and on
the other side we have the PC connected
to this source and the destination is
connect back to the PC next in the next
cycle. in the next cycle we execute the
next instruction and it will
automatically go down.
Uh so in this stage don't think that
much think about super old first
generation of computers that
uh it doesn't really have cache just
consider this is a
me piece of memory s memory that can
give you the data in one cycle time okay
I would say this is a at this stage is a
high level abstraction okay a simplified
structure of a computer architecture
Okay. So in real cases, yes, this is
likely to be a instruction L1 cache. And
in real cases, it's likely to be a
little bit more separated between the
front end and the back end. So what what
do I mean by separated? It's more most
likely that the fetch can sometimes be
faster, sometimes be slower, right? And
also on the other side, execution can
sometimes be faster, sometimes slower.
So if you want to keep both side busy
the method that you use is to put a
buffer in between so that these two
parts can work on their own with their
own progress until the buffer is becomes
empty or overflows. Right? So in modern
architecture what is happening is
typically there's a buffer there and
there's a issue stage. So the buffer
here the fetch will keep fetching the
instruction into the buffer. There can
be several hundreds of buffers waiting
there. Then a issuer select which
instruction can be issued into the rest
of the pipeline. Okay, this is part is
the back end. That part is the front end
that connected with a buffer. But here
we don't want to go that complex. Just
keep it simple.
Okay, then let's consider one more
thing. What if we want to store a data?
So this is a SW instruction, right?
store an instruction. So the basic
calculation is the same. So we still
have x9 and we still have an offset.
This time it's number eight, but the
logic is basically the same. We didn't I
didn't update the example here. But here
you can see in this case x6 is no longer
a source. It's no longer a destination
but a source. And it's A2. So we connect
with A2. Then 20 and 24 A2. Then we go
the output comes out from RD2 and this
directly go to the R WD
memory stage.
Okay, it directly go to the WD the data
write data box. Then the rest is the
same and the other only other thing we
need to be careful is in this case right
enable needs to be one. So we need to
allow it to let the right happen.
Okay, then it's a load and store
instructions. Then we do calculation.
The calculation is actually simpler or
it's the most common type of
instructions that we're considering. So
here we're considering X5, X6 and X4. So
you can see these are the most common
type of instruction and that is why we
need two input port for register five
and two. So two read two read paths for
the register file and one write path to
the register file right. So these three
operations can happen in parallel. In
this case we don't need to do much.
In this case we don't need to do much.
Then the whole register connection can
stay the same thanks for thanks to the
uh stable the stable risk five encoding.
It's only here RD2 and RD1. We need to
consider RD2 no longer goes to WD, but
RD2 needs to go to source B. Right?
RD2 RD1 goes to source A and RD2 goes to
source B. So what we do here is we add
this multiplexer. Why? Because source B
can come from two different locations.
It comes from two different locations.
One location is from RD2 and the other
location is we still need to consider
immediate data. Right?
So we still need to consider immediate
data.
Then the immediate data and the RD2
need to eventually go on source speed.
Once we have two input, one output and
decide which one to go to output, we
need a multiplexer. So here we need a
small 2 to1
multiplexer. Right? Then we need a
another control logic to select which
one to use.
Right? A source is which one to use.
And here you can see right before ALOU
we have some complex circuit right. Then
typically this type this group of
circuit at this position at this place
is called opand gathering. Then operand
gathering here is a really example case
but in real hardware operand gathering
can take a rather long cycle can take
some time can can take a few cycles so
that we can have all the operants ready
for the alus and then we can per perform
the calculation operation. In this case,
we're only gathering source A. We
guarantee source A is ready. We
guarantee source B is ready u from two
different loca from two different
sources. Then we can perform the AU
operation.
Okay.
So then another type of instruction
this is not our type instruction. This
is a branch in type B instruction. It's
a branch instruction.
The branch instruction is special
because it perform operation on the PC.
Right? Whenever we do branch, the PC
needs to be updated. So what does this
mean? Is
uh equal.
If X4 and X4 are equal, okay, in this
case, they're always equal. Not a big
problem. Then we need to jump to L7.
Okay. How is L7? This label is encoded
in the instruction. It's nothing special
but immediate number, right? It's a
relative
address from the current location to the
label. So what do we do is we need
another AO to perform the PC operation.
So what we do here is like this.
this PC go from here
to this add
AOU to this adder. Then you may ask can
we reuse that AO? The quick answer is
yes. And for most time it's more likely
to use that AO reuse that AO. It just
makes the wiring even more complex
there.
But just imagine here is a AOU
operation. that it's on one side is
extended immediate value on the other
side is the original PC in this case we
just go back right so here
we have two sources one is the plus4
result one is the branch taken result
right is the calculated new PC so which
PC we should go in this case the PC
source is another source that we need to
consider it's another multiplexer we
need to consider where have two two
input wires and have one output wires.
So this control signal needs to decide
this control signal needs to decide if
the branch is taken or not taken. If
it's not taken we use the plus4 value.
If it's taken we use the calculated
address value. Okay. Then there's
something that I didn't say here is
is here. So there's a logic operation
other than this add operation, right?
There's a comparison operation. It's the
comparison is doing is this x4 and x4
are doing this comparison. So where this
comparison is performed and is performed
in this alou.
Okay, we need this AOU to calculate the
result so that this result can
eventually go back to the PC source to
select to decide if it's taken or not
taken. So a branch operation is also can
be time consuming in a CPU core design.
Okay.
So we have talked to so many control
signals at this stage right this
everything that connects to the top
these are either single bit or just a
few bit to decide what to do. Then how
this what to do information is
determined is generally we need to know
the instruction and to determine how
this
control signals are defined. Right? So
what it does how it works is basically
we need a control unit. What it takes?
It takes the whole instruction. Actually
we don't really need the whole
instruction. We don't need the um the
source registers the operand information
or the immediate value right but we need
the rest of the instruction. So this
instruction this information the op the
fun 3 and fun 7 should go into the
control unit. What's the output is the
PC source right result source right
memory right AOU control AOU source and
the uh immediate source then a few
signals to decide how the whole control
flow works right so
nothing really complex here you just
need a really large truth table list all
the possible cases then for every case
there should be a predefined output a
group of output right once Once you have
a big
truth table, you can convert them into a
combination logic and you can do the
calculation to generate right signal
that goes to different part of the core
design.
Okay,
so that's a slight still slightly
oversimplified risk 5 core but at least
I think I have explained the whole
architecture of how a risk five core
works in general. what are the necess
necessary components in the whole data
path. Right? So in theory then if you
take some time to design this thing then
in theory you can get it to keep working
keep working until the whole program
executes. Right? Okay. Then we need to
consider performance considerations.
So we need to consider the performance
using this way to understand the
performance. So the total execution time
is the number of instruction divided by
the number of instruction multiplied by
cycle per instruction. The cycle per
instruction is probably the most
important uh parameter or matrix that
defines how efficient a core is. Right?
Cycle per instruction is what's the
throughput of your um CPU core
with cycle per instruction here. So
cycle per instruction we typically write
it as CPI cycle [snorts] per
instruction. So some in some cases we
will care more about CPI sometimes we
care more about IPC
CPI and IPC
right they are basically equivalent just
u inversed.
So CPI is more about talking about it's
more about the latency right. So we care
say oh we shoot one instruction on
average it takes three cycles or four
cycles
right now IPC typically talk about the
throughput consider per cycle in every
cycle how many instructions that we can
finish okay so it's convenient in
different ways but essentially they are
pretty much the same so in this case we
we actually just simplify it do not
consider this signal here. Do not
consider this signal here. Just consider
their individually controlled position.
Yep.
So, so that's okay. The question is how
cycle by cycle instruction instruction
cancels out. Then
consider this is one variable this is
another variable right in terms of unit
then we will get execution time equals
second and this matches right then but
second per cycle is one value and the
cycle per instruction is another value
right so CPI IPC is a cycle per
instruction right so
Um
so in this design if you consider that
we can precisely control the clock
signal here and we consider the whole
thing is completed in just one step
right I want to say this is a single
stage core design in one cycle we
complete to one instruction which is a
very ideal case um
but a simplified case right and in early
design This is actually how a CPU is
designed in early ages. It really
completes in one cycle. Now what's the
parameters here? If everything can be
completed in one single cycle, the
single one single cycle is the only
cycle that controls the PC. Okay, you
can just say oh instruction memory is
another register. This is another
register. This is another register. Just
consider uh the PC works in this way.
The PC signal has really slow frequency.
Then we
occasionally trigger the instruction
memory.
We trigger the instruction memory in
this way. Then we trigger the register
file slightly with a slightly delay.
Okay. If we can generate a slight delay
and this is we can complete the whole
data path in one cycle time right. So
early CPUs are designed in this way.
So in this case cycle per instruction is
one single cycle data pass is every
cycle we complete one instruction and
for every instruction it takes one cycle
to complete.
Then the second term second per cycle is
frequency that or how fast our clock
cycle can go right. So here if you need
to consider the whole data pass it doing
a lot of task it reads memory perform au
operation do the control
um and also write data to the register
and write data to the memory. Think the
amount of task that is complete in this
cycle determines this cycle needs to be
rather long, right? We need really long
periods. So the frequency needs to be
rather low. In this case, we require a
long cycle a long cycle time. And
so this is not the ideal design, right?
Because of the long cycle time. So what
we can do if we want to reduce the cycle
time and improve the performance to
improve increase the frequency the only
thing we can do is to reduce the task
that is completed in one stage then in
one cycle then we can design a
multicycle core design we design a CPU
core as a sequential logic but a little
bit more sequential than before.
So we slightly change the
uh the design. So this time we combine
the instruction and data memory.
So uh in early stage
the instruction and the memory and the
data memory they don't want to have a
different set of circuit. They just
think oh we just want because the the
basic functionality are the same. So in
early WOMA architecture
uh instruction and data memory
is combined together. So the core of
architecture says that the instruction
is part of the memory. It just stored in
the memory. Then when you say non non
vanoyman architecture then this is
something that is being challenged.
Okay. Although venoan architecture has
other definition but that's the most
important part.
Okay. So what we do here is let's say in
the first stage we just want to do
uh lo we just want to load the
instruction or only want to do
instruction fetching. So this is what we
do. We load the instruction and this
instruction need to be memorized through
multiple multicycle execution because
for multiple cycles we're still
executing this instruction right. So it
needs to be memorized because later on
we need this read data to also generate
regular memory reads. So here we need a
register. We need a memory we need
registers and these registers are
register for instruction.
We need a IR right signal. This is
enable signal right? It's a right enable
or the register enable signal. If this
signal is not enabled, not no data can
be write into it. Right? So this is a
instruction
register write signal to control in
which cycle we can write into this
register.
Okay. Then this design has nothing. It's
not really special but we just do the
load instruction. Then we just put one
part of the read address or the register
selection signal here and on the other
side we do extension. When we get a
result, we need to hold with the
register because we need to use this
register result to do something else.
Okay. Then once we hold it, we do source
A and we have source B. We do the ALOU
control. Then still we need another
register to hold what the data are
there. So immediately you can see there
are some registers that can be
controlled by the user that some
registers cannot be controlled by the
programmer. When I say user is the
programmer. So for example the what's
the data in the register file can be
controlled by the programmer. The
registers that cannot be controlled by
the programmer are this registers that's
called a structural register.
Okay those are structural register. So
programmer has no control to it. It's
always just temporarily holds the data.
So that data pass can be complete.
Now even the PC we consider is can be
controlled by the register but just with
special branch and jump instructions.
Okay. The AOU result eventually goes
back to here.
Uh
okay this is address calculation
then on the other side. Okay. So this
what what this happen what's here what's
happening here is this AO result
remember we take this adder do you
remember this adder there when I say oh
we can reuse the alou this adder this in
the previous example that calculated
address this adder is removed we only
have want to have one aou in our whole
circuit right so this alou is
calculating address then this address
goes back to there Then we need a
control signal a multiplexer to select
are we do are we reading a PC or are we
reading our address
right
now and in this case we're reading our
address then this address signal
there we're reading a piece of data and
this data also goes into this address
and comes out from this read bus and
here we have two different directions to
So when we do splitting we really don't
really need a lot of circuit. We just
can connect to all of them and we just
use um enable enabling signal to decide
which to write to. Right. So here we
write into the data and this data goes
all the way to the destination to here
so that we can decide where we we get
the data.
Right. Then just make it slightly more
complex. Uh
how do we write the data? Then
see here we we need the right we need
the second op right the second operand
is read the data here. We need to hold
both of them on the other side. Um this
result
can go back can write to the result
then go back can go back to the
uh write data can write the data back to
the instruction memory. Okay. So it just
consider if this is a store operation it
goes back here.
Okay. conditional branching it's getting
even more complex it goes from here the
PC goes from here then it goes to this
is this stores to old PC then it goes to
source A and it also being processed by
ALOU and the ALOU calculates the new PC
and this new PC needs to be stored back
to the u to the PC next right so we need
to select which one then it goes back to
the PC next
Uh so here as you can see the operand
gathering stage is getting more and more
complex.
It's getting more and more complex
because there are more type of input
that can state can get into this stage
and we really need to select which
source of data that goes to alou.
And here we have even more control
logic. And consider this control logic
is no longer a single cycle control
logic, control unit. It requires a
really complex
control logic, really complex
sequential logic so that can generate
the signals in the right way.
Okay. So it still it reads the
instruction data. It reads the
instruction the instruction data
to decide what this control signals
needs to be.
So this design control unit is a state
machine and we need to go through this
state machine a little by little and you
can match here.
I know I I fast forwarded the some
design on the right side. So let's look
at some of the design paths using the
state machine. Okay.
So the first thing we need to do state
zero is always fetch. We need to fetch
the instruction. So fetch instruction is
we required address source
selection right. So address se source
what do we select? We select from the PC
and IR right is one.
Okay. So that means we allow the
instruction to write into this register.
So this is the data path for this cycle.
For every cycle we start from a register
and we end with another register. Then
we start with from a register and we end
with a register so that we can always
consider something in between as a
combination logic. Okay. A a minor thing
here that you may ask is oh there's
another group of register in between
right this group of register is here and
also if you like look later the register
file is another register that between
this instruction register and this uh
open register register result register.
So how it's handled
is typically handled in this way. We use
different edges to trigger
different registers.
So that's remember we say registers or
flip-flops typically can be triggered by
either riding edge or down edge right up
edge or down edge. So we need to decide
if it's you want it to be triggered by
up edge or down edge. And sometimes you
can control both of them. So what is
happening is for PC register
or for any other structural register
we use up edge
then for other registers or user
programmer control register
I'm a little bit simplified this case
here program controller
then we use down edge.
So what is happening is for PC right
then in up edge we trigger it
then
another up edge we trigger it right. So
it always start with this register and
end with this register. So that when we
have another up edge we guarantee the
destination is already stored with the
data right but for the data let's just
consider it's a group of register we
consider the data is triggered by don
edge
then
whatever result that's required before
this
whatever is required before this
instruction data
should be ready before this time.
Okay, it should be ready by this time.
And on the other side, if we read or
write the register the the uh the
memory, then because it's triggered by
that time, then it should be ready by
this time.
Okay. So we need to consider this half
cycle behavior
here.
So that's something that we can complete
kind of a two-stage thing in one cycle.
It's just use a different edges to
control the
um to control different type of
registers.
So for every cycle we start with a
register and when we end with another
register in the at the beginning we have
a fetch stage.
Okay. Then what we do here is we finally
have a decode stage.
We have to have the decode state. What
does decode do? Right. What the code is
doing is
it mainly
go up to here to the control signals so
that we can generate the control
generate the the control signal for the
back end of this pipeline. Then also we
load the data here and we
do some sign extension here at stage.
Okay, it's a complex stage. We say it's
decode is a little bit simplified but
it's actually doing multiple things but
they can go through different paths so
they can happen in parallel no problem
and we also start with a register and
end with another group of registers.
Okay,
here's no register. I know this is a
problem is kind of intentional. We'll
talk about that later. Then on the
control unit it all should also have
internal registers that we're not
showing.
Okay. In the decode stage then here we
have another state that is memory
addressing stage
or memory addressing state. In this case
we have AO source A is select from RD1
from here. This AOU source A and AO
source B. AO source B is comes from the
immediate value comes from the immediate
value on the other side comes from the
register data one. Right? The AOU
operation is a sum operation.
So we perform a sum operation that
starts with a register end with another
register.
Then next stage
is the memory read. We really do the
memory. We perform the memory operation.
We start from this register the ALOU out
because this ALU out at this time stores
the calculated addresses.
Right? Then go back to the address part.
But at this stage we need to change the
ADR source the address source from PC to
this from this path from the AOU out.
Okay. Then it goes to data. Now here
also something that didn't say is this
instruction enable should be false and
we're not allowing to write into the
instruction it goes to the data.
Okay.
Then finally we do this right back start
with a group of registers and end with
another group of registers. So since
this is right only it should in theory
stop here but we just because it will it
will just stop here. So we didn't draw
draw this part. So we start from here
and we have this destination address and
we have the data and so it goes to the
data
it goes to the register data bus. Then
we write the data result back. Okay,
consider this actually goes two cycles
through the whole system to complete
this instruction to complete this load
instruction.
Okay, it's only load instruction. Let's
see if we have more time to talk about
more instruction. Then once we're done
with this load instruction, we go back
and we do fetch. Then we perform the
next instruction.
Uh let's see if we want to go towards a
more complex situation.
Okay,
we can we can check here. This is for
store instruction, right? Then according
to different load or store instruction.
These are state transition diagram. For
load and store instruction, we go to
this state. For load instruction, we go
with this path. For store instruction,
we go this path. And for store
instruction what we do is we start with
this register and this register. On this
side we have the address ready.
Right? We still need to calculate the
address. On this side we have the
register ready.
Have the register ready. So on one side
this register go back to right data.
on this side the AOU out go back to
address. Then we can once these two
sides are ready then we write into it.
Okay.
Okay. There are more type of instruction
type instructions.
So with S6, stage six is the execution
stage, right? Just consider the code
stage already allow us to read the data
from the register file. So we have this
register ready.
Then we both of them comes from the
register data path and they do aou then
we store the result in a out.
The next stage is alou writeback. What
does AO write back do is we go from here
the AOE out then we go back to the
register data bus. Then also on the
other side we select the register which
is still being locked in the instruction
register for multiple stages for
multiple cycles. This instruction
register need to store the instruction
the 32-bit of the instruction so that we
can use it in later cycles.
then I will skip the rest. I think
they're basically the similar style.
Okay, you just need to consider they
start from some location. They they pass
either through some register files or
pass from some AUS then eventually go
back to another register file and
eventually we can store it either back
to the PC or store it back to some
destination registers.
Okay, it's a very complex state machine
that hopefully can can basically
represent the whole um
risk five execution
and consider the top the control logic
is basically the control big control
block
implement this state machine.
Okay, so you know how a state machine is
is designed and how state machine can be
converted into sequential logic and the
sequential logic can be converted into a
combination logic. Then you know in
theory if you have a lot of time you can
design it but it's just you we can only
design high level things by forgetting
low-level things. Okay, just don't
consider too much low level things where
in just in your mind you need to know
okay we can implement this these are
possible
okay now we do a little bit more
performance analysis I think that's the
last point that we can do before the
quiz so we still do this performance
analysis now with sequent with uh the
number of instruction number of
instructions is not changed because we
have the same program the pro the
program is defined by Right is the
compiler and the original program is
something as a micro architecture we
typically do not have much control on.
Right? Then second B cycle or the
frequency the frequency can be higher
because we're breaking down the whole
things into multiple cycles.
Well like in one cycle read register in
one cycle we do the ALOU in another
cycle we store into the memory. So the
frequency can be higher but on the other
side it takes three to five cycles to
execute one instruction
right three to five instruction to to
execute one instruction.
So the ideal way is we want to have very
high frequency and we still want cycle
per instruction to be one. Now how we
can achieve that?
Now what we can achieve is a pipeline
processor and instruction pipelines.
Okay. So we talked to two different
extremes. Now we can introduce how
pipelines uh how pipeline course works.
So I think I have to stop here. Then
pipeline can be really complex. that we
can spend a few um lectures to talk
about um we can start with simple
pipeline design then go into some really
complex pipeline design uh
considerations. Now when we're dealing
with something like out of order
execution, you probably even have to
forget the design at this level and it's
going one extra higher level right but
the general idea is the key elements are
there and from register another register
is the the job job that we need to
complete in one cycle. How cycle works
is basically by splitting the works with
by splitting the works with registers.
Right? So always always start with from
register and end with another group of
regist.