okay hello everyone welcome back to mlc
um this is the lecture 10 and the the
last lecture of this course
um powtown flies and it's a great
journey to work with everybody
here in this virtual course walking
through the content of machine learning
compilation and to be honest this is the
first time first course of scan likely
and we also had a great deal fine of
exploring how we can teach it and how
can we make the related course content
accessible so thank you for working with
us throughout the journey we will
continue to improve the course content
iterate
on the course future versions
in the course and you can continue to
follow mlc.ai for the latest updates in
the meantime you're also more than
welcome to try and use some of the
systems that were built throughout the
course namely apache tvm that can help
us
hopefully can also help you to do future
machine learning deployment use cases
okay so today we're going to do a
summary and recap of what we learned so
far
one of the things that
that we learned about machine learning
compilation so in this central scene
mlc is a process that for us to take
machine learning models in its
development form in a lot of cases the
development form can happen in
frameworks like tensorflow pytorch
injects
and we are going to do a sequence
transformations to bring those machine
learning models onto a deployment form
in certain cases the deployment form can
be the same as development for example
if you are just going to build and run
models in tensorflow pytorch those
models will just run locally on the
machines that you have
on the other cases if you want to go and
build and run the models on a different
platform but
if you want to go and write on android
devices or other devices there are
different complications being involved
including things like fitting the new
model deployment onto the api interfaces
building a set of libraries
that allows us to have a minimized
dependencies
so that we can execute on the target
device as well as being able to make use
of the lower level runtime libraries
like androids opencl runtime or enjoy
and elaborate really accelerate our our
executions
and
a lot of machine learning frameworks
like machine learning diploma inference
framework frameworks and machine
learning training frameworks also can
take benefit of this mlc paradigm as a
matter of fact
if you think carefully most of the
machine learning influence deployment
framework are doing some form of mlc
inside the box okay
and in order to it's really hard for us
to cover all the possible instances of
machine learning process on those
frameworks
so on the other hand the main theme of
this course is trying to get us the
basic elements and common terminologies
so it helps us to be able to talk about
what are the possible mlc
transformations and what are the
possible abstractions out there
the second goal is one to be able to
make use of those elements so that we
can compose different optimizations even
for our own system okay so one of the
key
elements in machine learning compilation
is of course tensors that serves as a
runtime component
help us to be able to you know pass in
the data across different layers
as well as tensor functions that encode
the computation among input and output
importantly the mlc is mostly about
transforming
um different forms of cancer functions
uh either in we have we have learned
about computational graph form of tensor
function that coordinates how does each
of the elements you know take your input
and compute to output according to your
data flow dependencies
in other cases we have also seen tensor
functions that represent
a loop level computation and we will be
able to reorder the loops to get us
better cache localities we have also
learned tensor functions that
correspond to gpu selective model and
making use of some of the gpu
programming and help us to accelerate
machine learning workloads are more than
accelerators
all those things can be viewed as some
variant of tensor functions
and
one of the key thing in mouse is we want
to be able to build
abstraction to represent those tensor
functions
and also transform amounts so that we
can get you know a tensor function
that's very generic that represents you
know maybe a relu operator but without
specifying how do we implement operators
to
another variant types of some tensor
function that maybe you know fuses in
together
and
have a detailed implementation on how
exactly you are going to do that on a
low level power
so the key elements in measurement
components in the tensor tensor function
in the past 10 lectures hopefully we
have gone through many variants of them
on how do we represent end-to-end
machinery model
and
most of the mlc process can be viewed as
transformations among those tensor
functions because in in usually in
development forms when we think about
machine learning models we think about
them abstractly in a lot of cases we
think about it as our linear layers
softmax layers
and uh and regular layers so we would
not think about hey how i'm going to
implement this linear layer using the
avx 512 instructions on the on the
hardware or how i'm going to use full
acronyms we implement the softmax
function
so when we when we're developing things
we are thinking about things as a much
higher level
however when we start to go and really
deploy them we will need to start worry
about
how what is the target instruction that
i'm going to
diagonally use right am i going to you
know fuse the linear redwater together
as being shown in a slide or am i going
to just build the necessary kernels am i
going to leverage gpu accelerations in
this case so all these questions
are questions that we want to think
about that way go and deploy a machine
learning model
and of course that is you know how how
am i going to build another thing from
scratch so mlc process
is this and it's processing try to
automate some of those things
and in order to automation
we want to kind of formalize it signal
in a terminology the machine also
understands right so from machine's
point of view mlc is just a
transformations among tensor functions
that can be represented using different
abstractions in this particular case
we are transforming
this computational graph of two layer
neural network onto
another
android neural network right that
contains a fused linear regulator
and also supplying additional
linear value implementation in this case
so most of mlsa process can be viewed as
discount transformations
and then our question is mainly about
you know how can we go and implement
those transformations and what are the
different kinds of transformation we can
leverage right so that we can
do it for different purposes in in
certain cases it's about how do i go and
get a better implementation of a lower
level operator
sometimes the lower level operating
implementation will naturally imply
uh possible constraints on
uh on the computation example with a
lower level of expects fusion then we
want to be able to perform combinational
graph transformations to also you know
transform the higher level part to
leverage fusion in this case
so the overall mlc process
effectively
can be summarized as development
transform and build right so most of the
cases in the past lectures we have gone
through each of those phases
specifically
we want to be able to summarize
everything as a centralized data
structure called ir module which is
which represents a collection of
programs collection of tensor functions
we are going to do in transformations
and the good part about it is it makes a
lot of things
modulized and it allows us to think
about things in an incremental fashion
we don't necessarily have to think about
hey i'm i'm going to directly take these
models and figure out all the specific
problems like how i'm going to map the
gpus how i'm going to allocate memories
how am i going to
go and handle
um
upgrade diffusion and so on you can do
them in several steps and each of the
steps is a transformation that
after we finish the transformations then
we will be able to take the ir module
and
and build and run it and in if it's a in
temporary case we just just need to go
and execute the specified uh updated
execution form right so
most of the mlc prototypes can be viewed
as this
transformations among ir modules
and one of the difference that we are
doing in this lectures we want to be
able to
in this class is we want to be able to
also let you understand what's happening
under the box right so usually the
transformations
among those ir modules are hidden behind
the scene of the machine learning
framework the machining deployment
the machine influence engine and so on
but really you will find that a lot of
those things can be understandable by
developers and sometimes it's helpful to
understand those things for example if
you want to guide quantization
transformations or in certain cases you
know if you want to choose someone
transformations uh it's not necessarily
a very straightforward or you know maybe
the underlying system that's not smart
enough to figure out what kind of
transmissions you want to have
and
in this case it's really helpful to also
allow developers to come in and also
collaborate with the system
another thing
that this kind of modular transformation
helps you is that usually those
transformations also been build and been
specified by different
different
engineering groups audiences for home we
could imagine that
library builders and power vendors
provide some part of the transformation
that maps the lower level tensor ir
functions and test the perimeters
onto the power acceleration parameters
while
the
machine learning engineer provides a
high level
um transformations right that that does
things like operating fusions and also
specifying the corresponding
computations they were interested in
so having the ability to expose the set
of transformations will give us uh some
more flexibilities and make the overall
mlc process more accessible
when we talk about mlc transformations
there are two things you want to think
about the first thing is the na right so
what is the
input output of each of the
transformation
throughout this lecture we have um
focused on the nouns what we call ir
module
effectively ii module is a contains a
collection of functions or tensor
function in this case
that that can represent
you know machine learning tensor
functions in different forms
from ho throughout the course we have
learned how we can use tensor ir
functions
to represent multi-dimensional loops
as well as
as well as tensor programs
this kind of multi-dimensional loops is
really helpful for us to specify
low level details of implementation so
we'll be able to you know run automatic
tunings on them or trying out different
variants of loop ordering vectorization
and prioritization
and usually you know this type of loops
is very powerful for us to do effective
code generations in this case
another important factor is library
functions like because of the
environment linear or callback onto the
torch function
this is because in most of machine
learning environments libraries
are still being very powerful and we
really want to also collaborate with
machine learning system engineers and
and hpc engineers who have the common
wisdom to be able to come up with those
libraries and so um being able to
present the course onto those library
functions it's really important for us
to be able to you know generate
transformation that contains those
library functions
finally the one of the important thing
is you know we still want to be able to
build a computational graph that
represents a high level computation that
trains everything together
and also
contains high-level primitive operators
like you know relaxed and dollar value
that represents just a computational
graph node of value operator
these high level operators are usually
helpful
for data scientists and domain engineers
to be able to quickly specify the high
level inputs onto onto the system
in the meantime there are usually cases
where we want to be able to say
customize a certain operator they are
not available in high level operators
that's where things like pencil
functions library directly in location
of library comes in handy because we
will be able to you know represent all
those things in a single computational
graph
and one important thing that
we keep coming back in this class is
also about interaction so how can
combinational graph interact with
the tensile functions and how can it
interact with library course right so in
this case at least the ability to be
able to represent a computational graph
and a high level operator and library
function is very helpful
once we have this we'll be able to do
transformations like you know take
a high level value operations and map on
to map it on to a library function
course right that causing the library
and that could be a very interesting
project
if you are interested in doing a
follow-up project on the course
like you know take a high-level model
that contains
all the possible high-level operators
and try to map them on to libraries like
cod and
in the case of mobile devices like
insane and other library functions while
still leveraging the mlc infrastructure
to do a lot of optimizations
or even more more interestingly right
trying to map the causal library
function together with some cause onto
tensorial functions that allows you to
do a bit of code generation together
with the library function
so these are all the interesting
possibilities
that mlc
enables and the first thing first step
to enable that is
have a common noun that also represents
all the possibilities
through our homeless processing that is
ion
and the angular related abstractions we
have on on this
once we have a noun the next thing of
course it's a verb i want to be able to
transform across ion producers because
another module contains all the
the ability to represent both you know
tens and functions
the library functions as well as
computational graph high level operators
and also cos among them we can we can
you know take
the taken diamond around is through
different transformations a lot of the
machine learning compilation process now
becomes just a transformation from an ir
module to another animoji
um
i will give a few examples that we have
learned in the course where
in the first few lectures we're learning
about cancer ir level transformations
right using what we call cancer schedule
and meta schedule that gives us all
ability to do auto tuning and takes
existing functions try out different
possibilities and then go and find the
best one among them
we can also do computational graph
optimizations it takes a combinational
graph and then generate
another combinational graph that for
example fuses to operator together or in
other cases you know trying to allocate
memories among them or being able to you
know
plan the extrusion orders or certain
operators if they are paralyzed informed
and
when during compilation of course in
different stages we can choose to
map product computations onto library
functions very interesting we'll quickly
try things out and also mix it with code
generation approaches so that you know
we'll be able to try out both library
functions and code generation have them
work together
so
transformation is really at the center
of all the mlc process
and
the ability to be able to you know
represent all those code and being able
to build those transformations in an
incremental fashion it's really
important for us to build a robust and
continuously evolving machining
component
if you look at the set of transformation
that existing approaches do but in most
of the machine learning frameworks
the common approach that measurement
framework is doing they will just go and
first import
them the computations onto a high-level
computational graph stored in ir module
well usually different frameworks have
their own terminology but you know
starting our ir module represented
computation
and then machining frameworks will go
and do some computational graph writing
like replace fusions determine the
layout of the computation
and and so on and finally most of the
machine learning frameworks will go and
map
the
go and map some of the operator calls
onto library function call so they will
directly go and invoke the heavily
optimized libraries
that people build
and effectively
when we're building the entry
institutions it will run into like enter
interpretation of library function
throughout this class um we can find
that you know we are doing everything in
jupiter notebook right except the first
and the last lecture
now most of the things we are doing are
handling juvenile notebooks so it's a
bit
not very typical you know says that most
when you think about compiler think
about something like your invoke from
command lines and you want to build
everything as a black box that people go
and and and directly in local
what we believe is that we want to be
able to also in
also enable some interactive
transformation because a lot of cases um
the machine learning engineers and users
also have
a
great amount of knowledge on how this
optimization can be can be used and
there are also different kind of
transformations we can do but maybe you
want to just try things out in a loop so
that you can try different optimizations
compare amount and pick the best one
because mlc process is still a very
emerging domain so there's not really
a silver bullet answer of hey these are
the set of transformations and these are
the set of things you do once you do
that you will get the best performance
and the best solution
so we really want to enable
different kinds of possibilities in here
and
the the way we enable that is trying to
be able to have an ir module that can
represent different possibilities be
able to represent them in tbm script
a python asd dialect that you can
directly go and interact with in jupyter
notebooks and build separate
transformations in python or in club so
that it gets exposed to python so that
you can go and play with all those
impacts and see the effect before and
after
this is a new
way of trying out machine learning
compilations and it's also the first
time we ever teach in the course
so
you know we will see how
how will what other things they can
enable but hopefully throughout the
course you can you can get a few of you
know these kind of interactivities and
it will become a kind of normal python
workflow that you can go and interface
with your normal machine learning build
and the deployment flow so
let us know if you have more ideas on
how this kind of interactive
transformation can be used
and what we believe is that you know
being able to
enable this makes it more accessible
and
helps more people to getting start to
use mlc in a python first fashion
okay
so finally i want to talk a bit about
future directions
and of course the mlc is an emerging
theme and
it's not possible for us to talk about
all the possible
techniques that i've been involved
the goal of this course is really give
us a glimpse and and talk about the
basic principles basic principles
include the tensor program function
abstractions
how can we have different abstractions
to act with each other
and then and then you know being able to
formalize most of the moc process as a
transformation among those ir modules
interactively i bison notebook
there are of course a lot of exciting
future directions that i've still been
working on on on you know a lot of
machine learning compilation researchers
as well as machine learning assistant
researchers well i'm hope one of the
things that
folks are looking at is how can we we
have talked about several layers right
the power designers go and build our
specialized layer that we talked about
in one lecture
the machine learning engineers might
might be interested in building the
engineering the the communication graph
optimization part
and then you know in certain cases maybe
you want to try out auto tuning so we
are going to leverage tens ir and so on
and previously
um traditionally most of the frameworks
try to structure the computations that's
what we call multi-stage lowering so you
start with the communication graph you
go and do certain transformations and
you map everything onto the onto the
tensile functions you do something
further and then you'll map them on to
lower level libraries and so on
um
really we want to be able to enable
feedback and
optimization across those later so not
only we try to have this clear boundary
we want to be able to break the
boundaries we want to be able to have
an
ir model that contains both tensile
function computational graphs so that
say if i want to do
optimizations also anti-functions like
layout decisions you will be able to
flow it back onto the communication
graph and it's very important for
specialized power
and of course one of the
important themes how can we build a
smarter and more automated approach to
support specialized powers like dsps
machine learning accelerators or even
gpus that come with like tested call
obstructions
tensorization is one first step and
there are a lot more work we can do to
automate this process
and more importantly a lot of cases we
want to start to think about how can the
engineers and users collaborate with the
compilation system
this is because machine learning
optimization is becoming so interesting
that we can really benefit from
knowledges from you know hpc engineers
and others the rice libraries
have you know ideas of how we want to do
approximate optimizations like
quantization and other things
while compilation solution can offer
certain level automation to support well
be able to you know handle our entire
layout deployment solutions recipe with
a few hints
leverage micro kernels to build by hpc
engineers but still making use of
the but still make use of an automated
solution to figure out you know tilings
and
gpu strap mappings and so on
so the collaboration between engineering
and compilation system will be a common
theme that we will see more and more in
the future that's why i believe that
interaction is so important that you
know help us to build the entire mlc
flow in jupiter notebook
many ideas can be a and one important
part that i think comeback and why makes
so exciting just like machine learning
frameworks offers you the ability to
build options with residual module
detectors
and and you know build a separate demand
connection together in organic way many
of ideas in mlc process can be achieved
through incremental transformations
among ir modules and by having a common
set of abstraction that connects
everything together it allows us to be
able to you know collaborate more easily
so that in certain cases i will be able
to build a fuser that that might fuse
this two operator together and then
bring that together with a very generic
version of user that fuels the rest of
the sense
or i can work with positive optimization
that feed on to the hardware engineer to
work on the rest of the part
so the ability to achieve most of the
things in this transformation paradigm
and being able to expose an into jupiter
notebook so that you can observe what's
going on
will allow us to really make it a
multi-process more accessible so
hopefully this will become part of our
beta machine learning workflow in the
future
moving forward um we have we will
continue to improve this course so do
follow us on mlc.ai and you are more
than welcome to also check out the
related course materials give us
feedback and use the course content to
build something that might be useful to
you let us know we'll definitely love to
know
you know what the things you build
and you know take a look at apache tvm
which will continually bring in some
more learnings of course onto the
project as well
in the meantime if you're also
interested in building machine learning
system in general there are also other
courses you can check out and in coming
uh in incoming four i'm going to offer a
course at cmu called deep learning
assistance that gives you that teaches
you how to build uh end-to-end pythons
like different systems from scratch
that's also going to be quite fun a lot
of principles we learn in this course
will also help us to
goes into that course as well
okay
thanks thanks everybody for uh awesome
joining the summer i really enjoyed
building all the cost materials
and and really start defining the
machine learning compilation together
and i'm looking forward to continuing
with we work with everybody as a part of
mlc
and
you know
hopefully we also see each other in both
physically virtually and see more use
cases of machine learning compilation in
the machine learning ecosystem thank you