hello everyone welcome back to mlc this
is lecture h
today we're going to talk more about
um what are the common properties and
techniques we're going to use
in mlc machine learning compilation for
specialized accelerators
in the last lecture we talked about how
to build mlc flow for gpu environment
and in the past lectures we talked about
how to do so for cpu environment
and one of the things that
we we haven't touched a point so far is
you know
when we started look at recent howard
trent we can find that there are a lot
more specialization going on
so traditionally if we look at the
hardware programs that we normally write
we we typically write program in a way
which will call scalar computing where
we just need to specify for loops and
compute how do we
get each element of the corresponding
data
and then as the modern hour evolves we
start to introduce what we call vector
computing unit
in this case is there an instruction
that allows us to take a vector
of certain lengths and we will be able
to you know perform say uh four full
importance additions and multiplication
together and that is the foundation of a
lot of the modern cpu architectures and
gives us a lot of accelerations in some
of the applications
and more more immediately we start to
see
a specialization trend among
the hardware backends especially for
machine learning this is because the
machine learning computing brings such a
high demand
and the traditional howard themselves
it's really hard for them to keep up
with all those demands
so we start to see
a trend of specialized accelerators in
particular there are you know
accelerated design especially for
machine learning like google's tpu
or in other cases uh gpus and
even cpu themselves start to also start
to introduce some of the specialized
acceleration unit like nvidia introduces
tensor core and amd more recently brings
what we call matrix core that allows us
to do uh matrix multiplication in a
single instruction
so all those common hardware trends
brings a common pattern on the howard
specialization
especially most of the instructions that
those howard provides
involves the element called tensor
computing so traditionally when we load
a map
element from a memory usually you know
you just need to load one element
now you know in this regime tensor
computer usually there is direction that
loads data in a very bulk fashion so you
can load the region of data onto your
memory and there will be instructions
that takes regions of specialized data
and run
um accurate computations like there will
be you know matrix mission
multiplication instruction or sometimes
even efficient convolution
so extraction
more question we want to ask you know
how can we build a machine learning
compilation process for
these kind of specialized hub and one
interesting thing about those
specialization tower is that each kind
of power is different so if you look at
one
one uh
one one power backhand it may contain a
six by six
sixteen by sixteen matrix communication
instruction and the dma unit allows you
to shuffle in say data know in the unit
of 1024 if you look at another hardware
uh the specific instruction can be
different from how in certain cases like
um cpu more recently there is a form
there's a dot product instruction that
allows you to take two vectors and make
dot product and
the ability that we would build to
support
these different kind of power backhands
also different and that makes the moc
process quite challenging
in general
okay
so
so today we are not going to work on a
specific kind of specialized power
because most of them are not openly
available
instead what we'll do we're going to do
is we're going to study some of the
common properties of those specialized
power programming and those properties
are going to be applicable if you are
going to build a mlc backhand for a
particular hardware and they are being
applied to
uh they will apply to to build some of
the backhand for mho4 tbm themselves to
support some of the specialized power
backup of course the things that we're
talking about today are not going to be
comprehensive so it's only going to but
it's going to touch a lot of the key
element that's going to be useful to a
lot of power back
so to begin with we're going to come
back to a low level numpy code to help
us understand what are the
key elements of a specialized code that
we write to target
a specialized tower
in this particular case
we are making a simple assumption of the
specialized power model so
the in the this particular hardware
contains
um several key components i'm going to
walk you through the code
themselves this particular of course is
implement python can be run in python or
structure in a way such that you know we
can easily also map it to a possible uh
code that runs on our accelerator
so first thing that you might notice is
that
um you know in this case we are working
on computing a transposed matrix
complication which means that my outcome
c i j
equals sum of i
summer over k
a i k
times b i k so effectively c equals
a times
b transpose in here
so
uh if you look at the code here
we can find that uh it's slightly
different from the original low-level
numpy code that that we write so first
of all we are allocating three temporal
memories of course in those cases this
temporal memory sits on
it's a normal number
but well well let's assume that this
three piece of memory sits on a
specialized part of the system
the c accumulator is a specialized
memory that accumulates the result of
matrix replication and a rag and b rag
represents the two input registers or
two input special memory that these
matrix multiplication unit takes
and
do the matrix multiplication and then do
the accumulation
so in this case this this
hypothetical
illustration unit contains a specific
instruction called
excel tmm add
which does uh
accelerated matrix computation right so
effectively what it'll do is it will
take
us
a slice of
accumulator matrix c and
run matrix multiplication of a and b
transpose and add it back
onto the size of accelerated matrix c
and
this means that in order for us to
leverage this to do
a bigger matrix simplification in this
case let's assume that we are doing a
thousand twenty four times a thousand
twenty four major communication so a
input is uh a
thousand twenty four times a thousand
what we need to do is we need to divide
the computations onto sub matrix
computation right so effectively if this
is my big matrix i'm going to divide it
into
a sub matrix computation in 16 by 16
fashion
and each of the time we are going to
copy
a sub matrix from
16 by 16 sub matrix from a
and another
16 by 16
sub matrix
from
b in this case this is actually be
transposing here
and and we're going to run this matrix
on location here so let's look at each
of the lines in here first of all
there's this line called sldl dma copy
so this is this resembles the typical
memory copy operations the actuator will
do that moves the memory from the left
hand side to the right hand side so
effectively in this case we're moving a
60 by 16 matrix onto a register here
similarly the dma copy here moves a
16 by 16 matrix from b
to b register in here
and finally after we move those data
onto registers the next thing we're
going to do is we're going to do a tmm
address in this case we are you know
taking the data from a registrant b
register and accumulating that uh raw
measurement multiplications and
accumulating that onto c accumulators
we're going to do that for 64 runs
because each of them computes a
submatrix computation of 16 by 16. so
after we do that for 64 runs
the c accumulator already contains the
result of the 16 by 16 sub matrix that
we are interested in and then we are
going to copy the data back
on to the global memory that we have in
cube
and this
picture uh help us to summarize or
uh
overall flowing pattern of the data
right so effectively we are taking the a
and b from
from normal memory that you have we are
going to do dma copy that copy the data
onto those special registers
and
this is where
this matrix multiplication addition
operation happens right so in this case
we have we're doing tmm adding here and
finally we are doing in dma
back onto the global memory
so if you look at this code and
you know
try to digest a bit of what are the
common elements here you can find that
usually
if you start to write code that involves
special accelerators it involves several
elements first of all it will involve
special memory scopes um in this case c
accumulator a register be registered of
course we are writing the numpy because
numpy don't have special memory scopes
but they correspond to
effectively the
they correspond to special regions in a
hardware for example you know they could
directly respond to a fast register file
in however
and that allows us to copy data in and
and store intermediate data during
computation
the second element that we're going to
have is
is the specialized instructions right
tmm ads so this is the instruction that
allows us to accelerate
in this case measures multiplication
transformations multiplication
operations
by um but there's also special
requirement of such instruction normally
you cannot arbitrarily take a piece of
say data from a global memory accelerate
that you have to place data onto a
special region of the power so that
these things exactly feed on to the
acceleration unit that's why we need to
copy the data explicitly to a rack and
b-rack before we
run rather tmn and finally there are
memory copy operations that allows us to
copy the data
in a bulk fashion from the
from a global region to some of the
local
registers and local specialized memory
these specialized instructions also
interleaves with the additional loops
so in this case actually we still have
some flexibility
to
how to to order the the computations
right example we will be able to in this
case you know reorder i and j and that's
you a valid computation
for
building out a thousand point eight four
and so on twenty four measures location
so even even in the regions of
specialized accelerators they are still
especially in those that are
programmable there are still a lot of
flexibility as we can do on optimizing
some of the outer loops to coordinate
the computation and that's also you know
making a general purpose uh enough so
that we can not only build accelerator
for matrix multiplication but also make
the work for things like convolutions
and dilated convolutions and other
operations okay
so this is one example of low-level
numpy code or
for a hypothetical specialized
specialized actuator model and actually
this kind of model usually reflects
accurately a lot of the challenges that
we're going to face in programming some
of the domain-specific accelerators
okay and of course we can go and run the
code to confirm that actually the code
that we build
for the
low-level numpy
specialized
low-level numpy version of this
transverse major implication matches
this overall computation
so now we've introduced a number and
code
next we're going to think about you know
how we can bring in some of the insights
to design
mlc obstructions to design compiler
abstraction that allows us to be able to
represent some of the structures that we
have in the specialized acceleration
computation
in particular one of the things we find
out is that
you know
in most of the computations we see
in the low-level numpy code they happen
in a
bulk fashion right so so we have
instructions to copy
original data onto another region we
have an instruction to take
data from specialized memory and do
matrix multiplication
and all those instructions and all those
all those operations are called are
carried out
by taking a sub-region of cancers
and you know
do we combining that with another
subregion cancer running by running some
computations and store that back onto
some piece of specialized memory so the
key thing here is what we call
tensorized computation
that
allows us to be able to present
a
a tensor computation that takes a
original tensor work with original
tensor as a basic unit of computation
right and we want to combine that with
loops
in a case of tensile r originally when
we talked about has ions we usually talk
about a block that contains a piece of
code that tells you how do you compute
each element
of the target instances
and and actually you know in order to
look at special accelerators it's no
longer true that each of this basic
operation step is one element at time so
you want to be able to have an operation
that allows us to represent not only an
element of time but also a bulk regions
of elements at a time
so let's do in order to do that
uh
we're going to introduce
um another tensile code here which most
of the elements of this sensor actually
you have already seen them
the main difference here is that you can
find
um there's already a for loop of 60 by
64 by 64 by 64.
and we have a 10 tensor block
in here
and in this block what you'll find is
that this floor contains
three block iterators
still the relations are ssr spatial
spatial reduction
but each of a step
in this particular block computes a
subregion of the target result so if
this is my
final matrix
and each of a block here tmm16-16
computes a 16x16
uh
matrix multiplication
sub step right that says that zero
reduction so we want to take 16 by 16 by
16 matrix location and add that back
onto the c sub regions
and and you can find that you know
this block still kind of closely follows
the original blocks that we did for
scalar computations
and within the block there are also you
know intermediate sub blocks right so if
you look at these blocks you can find
that they have an initialization region
that specifies for the first time of
reduction how do we initialize the
corresponding data point
and effectively this is the
implementation that iterates over
60 by 16 regions and set that to zero
similarly this part represents you know
during reduction steps at each step how
do you
perform the updates to a sub-region of
the result in this case this sub-region
is c
right
so why do we need to have this block
abstraction at a tensorized computation
level the reason is that a lot of those
computations will be
mapped onto the specialized power
varmint now this particular computation
we're not going to compile that into a
forum but
in the case of you know if we already
have an instruction that directly
performs a 16 by 16 by 16 major
communications we can directly replace
this piece of code
with an instruction that performs that
operation right so effectively it allows
us to group those tensorized
computations together
for easy targeting of specialized power
and of course we can use tbmscript.show
that allows us to see the corresponding
ir module one thing that you might
notice is that
on the block signatures it contains the
analysis of the
read and write regions
uh of the that list block does but in
this case the tmm 16 by 16 reads from am
a 16 by 16 region from a and b and it
writes on to a 16 16 region of c
this information is helpful for us to
perform analysis when we're transforming
the blocks especially loops outside so
while the key property of the block is
try to perform provide some kind of
isolation
so that from outside broad point of view
uh what all it does is you know it will
read from that 16 original lights onto a
16 16 region by by c
and all those contents are
implementation of that but when we are
transforming the loops outside actually
we can completely rely on information of
read and write
information to to perform some of the
writing so it helps us to isolate
from the
outside and inside
why this kind of isolation is important
the reason is that you know if we have
this solution i can feel free to replace
this
with
excel
tmm
adding here and still perform a lot of
the transformations that we have right
because from outside point of view it
doesn't matter within the block body
whether it's an accelerated instruction
or it is uh
or it is a normal follow-up as long as
the interface actually matches each
other
okay
so we'll be able to run the code and
confirm that actually this block code
can give you the correct result
uh another thing that we can do is you
know um we can also run transformations
around those blocks just like the
transformations we did for block the
computer scala computation
so in this case what we can do is we can
you know create a schedule
and get
the block get the surrounding loops
along that block and we can say do the
split and run our reordering here
and you'll find that effectively the
resulting code
will have something that
contains exactly the original blocks
implementation so the block body does
not have to change when you change the
loops in the outside
but we'll create additional loops in our
site reorder them right and then there
will be a
clear mapping of the iterators that help
us to maintain
the invariance that allows it to
effectively carry out internal
computation
so this gives a lot of advantages you
know says that you know we can still
specify example how do we want to
compute x-ray internal blocks while
still gives our ml3 system the auto
system ability to be able to iterate and
search over possible loop ordering and
other optimization patterns in the
outside
of course in most of the cases we do not
start with a
tens ir that contains a tensorized block
because if you take a high level
computation say a computational graph
from python tensorflow the first step
usually will generate
a for loop like this and that is a
really plain vanilla that loops over
each of iterators and you just do
you just use it to do you know uh
to do reduction and to the major
multiplication operations
one of the things we can do though is
that we can also transform
this piece of code to bring up a block
during
uh during scheduling or during
optimization
so the following code tries to
effectively split out the 16 by 16
uh iterators
from the original mathematical
reorder them so that we have outer loop
in the loop where the inner loop
contains 16 16 by 16 right so if we do
that we can find out what reorganizes
this data
uh contains you know 16 16 loops in the
inside and what we can do is we can try
to cut these loops uh
i'm trying to bring this 16 by 16 by 16
iterations together so effectively we
want to be able to
bring in a new block
that contains this region
now we can do the actual control called
block rise
and if you go and call block rise
you will find that it creates a 16 by 16
by
it
creates a
internal blocks that reads from a 16 16
by 16 regions from
uh
from the a a's important b
and writes from the c right so this is
exactly the code that we manually wrote
in the last part so there is a way for
us to be able to transform the original
code and try to bring that onto some of
our blocking structure that we have and
this blocking structure also should
create effective mappings onto the
x-rated power
and you know these are common mechanisms
right so in a lot of cases when we have
existing
programs that sitting
high level that do not have those block
structures and we have a power that
requires this kind of blocking structure
so that we can match some of the tensor
combinations onto low level power then
the system will mlc system will either
take a program and perform automatic or
semi-automatic transformations that help
us to bring the state to our final
spinal part
of course you know after we bring the
data onto this part
we have talked about you know about low
level numpy code there are other
elements besides the tensorized
computation we still need to be able to
introduce specialized memory scopes that
represents that we can map through onto
the special registers or memory regions
you know our specialized data
specialized actually
so here
we are creating um two additional stages
called
a register b
in the global action later
and then put them on to the original
computation
so in this case you can find that we
created
additional
data computing
memory right so we have you know a-rack
drag and accumulator and we have copy
stages in here that copies the data from
a to a global register b to b global
register
and then copy the data back on from
accumulator onto the global memory and
this is our computing block in here that
carries out the computation
so this code roughly
can be represents the overall computing
structure that we we wrote in a
low-level numpy right and in this case
uh when we look at this um
scope in here so these are what we call
memory scopes there is a special tag in
the in the compiler that allows us to be
able to recognize um that you know you
know follow up backhand creation phase
map this piece of memory through that
special attack and we are following a
convention here where global uh try to
mark you know what is the relation of
the memory with respect to threat
hierarchy in this case because we don't
have any threats in here a b and c are
most visible to all the stress
effectively and the second part a
register b register and accumulator are
called text so this text
marks you know what kind of special
memory they do of course right now they
don't resemble any meanings
uh but
the the compiler background will be able
to match those things and say you know
this allocation should be translated on
to
a
register
in the a register or be registered
so so they closely resemble
what
real world special accelerator
special accelerators behavior okay
so now that we have those uh specialized
memory scopes
that's the second element what the last
element we need to do is we need to be
able to map some of those
test rights computations right now the
body of the of those computations during
uh for loops want to be able to map them
onto
a lower level implementation
that
you know can map to say assembly code of
my
of my accelerated accelerators or other
implementations of this accelerated
instruction
so you want to do that this is a process
by the way called tensorization
so um if you
if you worked on vector processor before
you might heard about the process of
vectorization so vectorization is a
process that try to take
code written for between four scalar
form we try to transform them to
leverage the vector processes that
that we have so so you will be able to
perform say like a vector add
and vector multiplications and so on
so the transformation step allows you to
take the original code that works on
scalars and move them on to work on
tensorized computations
similarly the cancellation step
effectively is a way for us to move a
sub-original code that was originally
described in a scalar form and i want to
remember them onto another code that
effectively runs tensorized computation
in order to do that uh one of the
challenges that we will face is that
each of a power is different so so
there's one hour that might perform you
know 16 by 16 matrix multiplication and
you might find another hardware that
performs you know a 16 by 16 matrix
vector product
so
in some sense it's really um duplicate
this really duplicate the effort if you
want to go and build
a specialized mlc backhand for each type
of hub
so instead in the temporation process
what we do is we will try to register
a pairs of
of functions which we call
tensor intrinsic
so in this case
we want to register two functions the
first function is a description function
so this is a tensile function that
describes
for existing uh
accelerated sub-regions
what do we do so in this case this test
output is describes for existing region
we are going to
we are going to read from a 16 by 16
regions right and the right one to
uh
sigma 16 originally in c and this is
working
effectively this piece of code describes
somatics of that accelerated instruction
which is you know mixture of application
and adsense back onto that piece of
memory
we also have another function
that tries to describe the
implementation so what it tries to do it
says that you know for a given buffer
here
we want to be able to describe um what
is the actual coding implementation that
implements that piece of code so in this
case
we are trying to call onto a call action
function called tmm16 so it is a
microkernel that we write to accelerate
the 16 by 16 machine publication we can
also change it to other form of probe
like you know emit cause of inline
assembly and other cases so this is the
final code that we want to place
as a target
and
we want to register it as a tester
intrinsic both contain a description and
implementation
so our test relational process will try
to you know take a separation right try
to look it up from a description part to
match to say hey this does this part of
the computation matches up my
description if they do we're going to go
and replace that with the implementation
part
if you look at the description
implementation you can find that they
also contain several interesting
elements so in this case uh the the
scopes uh tries to show the special
memory scopes that
that we are going to
we are going to you know we are looking
for so effectively this implementation
only works
and both the description implemented
actually all microscopes right the
scopes marks that okay okay
this particular tensor intrinsic only
works for mac input memory from a global
registers b global register and rise
onto accumulators it also gives you a
few low level constraints in here from
ho you know there's of that factor
that
says that you know
my underlying memory have to align to
multiple of 16 in here
and they are also uh in this case in the
implementation side there's a try it
tries to do what we call strike matrix
so the strikes matrim effectively
allows us to be able to have a striated
buffer in this case so that that means
that this particular piece of a
can be a sub-matrix
in here
and the strides in fact represents
the regions in here so that you know
while we're accessing the piece of
memory it can be non-continuous in here
so so
um
if it's a 16 by 16 membrane here and our
result is also 24 by 1024
then the strikes here equals 7.84 so
that you know for us to visit the first
element the second row of elements we
know that we can you know add it by
uh
we can add it by the length of our 724
and in this case match buffer directly
constructs you know effectively it says
that i'm expecting a a input buffer
of of size 60 my 16
and i'm going to store the resolved
strides onto this variable sc in here
okay
so in this implementation what it
effectively does is to call on to
uh
call onto
a accent function by passing in oracle
access pointer so these pointers
are
the
are the starting point of a b and c
uh in the in the void in a void or pick
form we're also going to pass the
strikes onto the
onto the onto the resulting function so
that it can form computation on sub
slices of memory
in other cases you know we might expect
memories that are compact that do not
come with strikes
in those cases we also need to create
special requirements of a low level
validation to validate whether or not
some of the compacting requirement is
fulfilled
okay so as a property step uh you know
we still do decompose reduction in this
case you want to decompose our reduction
step that contains
uh an insulation that fuels on fuse all
the elements uh to zero
and then an update step that come that
runs the matrix communication
and addition step which we aim to
replace with our target
instruction
then what we can do is contents arise
with the tension change name and after
we do that we can run
sure again
and what you can find is effectively
this piece of tensorized computation
body gets replaced
by a call excellent step
that
that calls on to an external function
and these intrinsic are slightly longer
so they effectively this these access
pointers correspond to excess pointers
of a and b and c
and then there are additional parameters
that are passing through to a lower
level
okay
in this case um we are using call
external to call into external function
in designing environment
and the downstream compilation can
easily map this onto an instruction that
implements operation but i'm going to
give you a specialized specific
implementation in this case
what we're going to do is we're going to
simply view this tmm 16 by 16 by writing
this following c code
that implements that that piece of uh
what we call microkernel it's a
microkernel
implements um that 16 16 matrix
multiplication
in reality of course we can write
embedded assembly code and other forms
that directly perform the acceleration
code
uh so
it effectively demonstrates a mechanism
that enables us to try out different
kind of things and we're going to you
know combine that with the original
piece of code through what we call
import lvm so in fact we will import
a
temporal lvm module onto my final kernel
and we can try go and build
and run it and you'll find it actually
gives you the corrector in this case
we have run all the transformations of
course this particular experiment still
runs on cpu so the the global.a react
robot.b rack and the and serial
accumulators in this case translate on
onto cpu memory because we do not run
any of the specialized
mapping paths and map them onto
specialized memories
and the particular
acceleration function also still runs on
cpu
but you know the same mechanism allows
us to use use those transformations to
map those tensorized computation bodies
and other pla and other computations
onto specialized acceleration
instructions
we also release optional
material that for you to go and try out
or how do we leverage similar mechanisms
onto mapping
the set of computations onto a videos
tensor core that's a real specialized
well there's a real gpu that comes with
a special acceleration unit
there are also other additional topics
that we do not handle so far
that
um that you know you are more than
welcome to check out in the future
including things like layout constraints
interaction with threat hierarchies
but this lecture have already covered
some of the key ideas and key elements
specifically how we can group the test
rights computation onto sub-regions and
leverage those key constructs called
blocks allows us to you know
run transformations of the test rise
programs and map some of our regions
onto the
uh on to the specialized implementation
that power can take
okay with that i would like to conclude
today's lecture thanks everybody for
coming and i will see you
next week