okay hello everyone welcome back to mlc
this is episode five today we are going
to introduce
um an interesting topic so up until now
we talk about
how can we represent machine learning
programs in both primitive function and
end-to-end fashion
in today's lecture we're going to talk
about
how can we
automate some of the transformation
process
another logistical announcement so
it has already been updated on course
website
uh after this lecture the next uh next
week uh i'm going to travel a bit so we
are going to skip one week session i
will be back with more interesting
contents
and there are a lot of exciting things
to see today as well so let's get
started
so to get us prepared again we are going
to um this is a more like an interactive
session so we're going to use collab
notebook here for
explaining some of those concepts we're
going to import the relevant components
in here
and to begin with one of the things we
want to do is we want to recap a bit of
what we learned in i think two lectures
ago
about how we can take a permitted tensor
function and then go and transform it a
bit
remember that our general principle of
machine learning compilation is going to
be able to represent
tensor functions in different form and
transform around them and in two
lectures ago we talked about how we can
take a primitive function and use a
transform api onto a schedule api to
allow us to go and transform a loop a
bit to get a more efficient program
and then last lecture we talked about
how we compose those permitted tensor
functions together to form an end to a
neural network
of course one of the things we might ask
you know how those two things fit
together right so one way that we can
fit them together
is that we can take already a permitted
function that's already existing end to
a neural network run some transformation
to get a better variant and use that to
replace original primitive function
anti-execution and that's what what we
are going to do today okay
so this is a recap so some of the
contents we already covered in in two
lectures ago we are just going to walk
through them again
so first of all we can use tvm script to
define a set of cancer programs that
contains loops and in this particular
case we're just using a
128 by 128 matrix multiplication as an
example
and hopefully this is a program that you
have already been familiar with
some of the key concepts include
the multi-dimensional loops the
computation body the block constructs
and the multiple dimensional buffers
okay
once we have it uh we will define a set
of input and output for evaluation and
here we are using numpy as uh
as a reference point well
it should be
here
and then
now we are going to create uh
we're going to create a
reference and the arrays we can use for
running this function and in here what
i'm going to do is i'm going to
build the mymodule function and bring a
tummy evaluator that help us to evaluate
overall runtime here
and i'm going to
invoke the time evaluator and gives me
the average runtime speed of this
particular function on this collab
environment
so fast look good
you know that's the first step right
remember that the or step we are doing
is struggling to construct or develop
a ir module that contains the function
of interest in this particular case
we're interested in our permanent cancer
function
we're going to
well in this case we're going to
directly build
gets the result in some other cases we
might be interested in transforming a
little bit
so let's let's review some of the things
we learned in the last two lectures
we can go and transform the particular
uh module a bit in this case i'm going
to define a function called schedule mm
and what we're doing is we're going to
get the blocks out
get the loops
do a loop splitting and reordering and
change the
reduction here
so
to see what the effect it will bring us
around this code block
and we in fact we are creating a
schedule
feed into
the schedule admin function here
then we're going to
use this uh display utility to show
what's the transformer code
so
in this transform code we can find that
there's a new loop in here called j1
and
and in this case you can find that
this new loop here j1 contains
you know
is reordered with the k right so in this
iterations we are we start with
iteration k then j1
and this is the uh tensor ir program
after this transformation
okay so
this basically overview of what we
learned two lectures ago
and uh it gives us uh
you know then we have a reorganized
program so this is a program that
hopefully as we explained in two
lectures ago
um you will be able to allow to
reorganize the program and get a bit
more cash locality
and we can go and go ahead and build it
um
and we'll point that actually compared
to
the runtime that we're having here
three point four eight seven minute
micro second
in this particular case this transform
code did give us a bit of a
bit of improvement over the original
program okay
so that's a
quick overview a quick quick review of
what we learned before
and now let's start to
learn something new that comes with the
schedule transformation up until now
when we are examining this code right
what we do is we call the schedule
function and we just display the script
result in here and this shows the tens
ir that we have after the schedule
transformation
now besides this way to show it another
thing that actually the ti askgaryvee
providers is this uh functionality
called trace
so i'm going to go ahead and print it
out
and what you can find is actually this
trace kind of exactly corresponds to the
set of transformations we run in order
to get this schedule so forever in this
particular case you'll find that the
first call
get blocked
and then get loops
except the you know loop the variables
that naming are different but other the
n effect the same right it's going to go
split reorder and decompose reduction
okay
it's a bit hard to see it but it might
be easier to say side by side so i'm
going to
also
insert a code block here
let's try it's already
run so that we already have a schedule
variable so i can run
schedule.js here
and we can compare right so we can find
this line corresponding to this line
this line corresponds to this line
split function in here
factor equals four
reorder
and decompose reduction
so this trace actually records a set of
transformations
that
that was being performed on this
schedule and we can use that to as a way
to to see you know what are the history
transformation that we need to get to
this point
and
so why is it useful right now you know
for the disadminist schedule it's only a
way for us to remember what we have done
before uh so
but we're going to use it throughout the
the rest of the chapter and be always
else you know it's going to be useful
for us to start to make use of this
tracing
okay
so upon you now we've talked about uh
what transformation will make on the
original test hour program in this case
the original
uh the original program is um you know
two dimensional matrix communication i'm
gonna try it by 108
however
we are trying to specify in this case
all the possible details that we want
the final program so so in this case
while our transforming loop we already
have what the programs that we want in
mind we want to be able to write the
loop in this way the factor should
exactly be four
and then that's our final problem in
many cases however even though i'm a you
know i have worked on parallel computing
and
sometimes you know optimizing computers
for quite a bit even i don't know how
exactly that we want to optimize a
particular code of course there are
principles like cash localities making
use of power and so on
so so the question is you know what if
we don't exactly know what we want but
we kind of have a rough idea of you know
the overall direction what can give us a
possible
possibly optimized so what can we do
so one question we want to ask you know
instead of specifying everything very
accurately
can we try to specify what are the
possible ways we can transform it while
leaving out some of the details
hopefully you know to the to the system
to figure it out
and that's what we're going to talk
about now so this is what we call
stochastic schedule
transformation uh it's being achieved by
this particular function called
stochastic schedule mm okay so let's
walk through the code
you will find that actually this code is
looks very very similar to
to the schedule mm that we had in before
so it might be useful to see it side by
side so on the left hand side it's a
stochastic version of schedule mm
and on the right hand schedule okay
so let's compare line by line so first
of all the first line is the same right
the second line is the same
the difference is that on a stochastic
version
now this call called sample perfect tile
so instead of directly specifying hey my
j factor equals four
what stochastic schedule means so
stochastic or usually it means random
processes so it says there's some
randomness in here
so where does the randomness come from
the remnants come from this sampling in
this case the sample perfect tile
tries to draw
these j factors for distribution we'll
talk about what the distribution is
but effectively try to you know select
something right that that
sometimes you know if you run once it
will mine gives you one kind of
factor of hardware one split loop and
then somewhere around and i give you
another another one so you factor in the
sample chord after we get a j factor
it's the same split chord right on the
left-hand side you get splitting here
that path of j vectors same split chord
similarly order
and same decomposed reduction okay
so you can find that the only difference
from what we call a schedule mm to store
cassie mmm is actually this additional
sampling step
and in here some perfect tile
so this particular function actually
just draws from the number that that's
going to gives you two random numbers
usually
and the perfect tile means that we want
to sample
integers
that
perfectly factorize
the original loop so because our
original loop size is 128 so there are
different possible ways
we can get
2 8
8 by 16 32 by 4 2 by 64 and all of this
you know if you multiply all those pairs
together
64 in here and it should be 128. okay
and you know um
now we have talked about what are the
uh
now we have talked about you know what
are the possible ways we can use to
to run a stochastic schedule let's try
to write in action and see you know what
what what the code can generate
uh so if you go and run it
you'll find that it's going to get give
you one version of a code in this
particular version if you look at
these
j1 grid this value equals 1. so actually
in this case the j factor
in this particular case the j factor
equals 128 and one okay
and if i'm going to run again
and
again
well you can find that
this internal factor changes right it
becomes 2
by 64. so in this particular case it's
64 by 2.
so you can find effective what's
happening is that every time i'm going
to run the stochastic schedule it's
going to give me a random program
well a program
from a space of programs and each every
time the selection can be different so
farmer in this case is 8 by
16 as my
stochastic fraction right so the idea is
that you know
because we are introducing some
randomness what we are going to get is
no longer a problem we are going to get
different programs every time we call
this function
and
and you know effectively uh this gives
us a distribution of programs a
collection of programs that
that specify a possible space or program
that we're interested in
and now
this is where trace can come in handy
right because every time
now we
we have the transformer program
we can also print out a trace you can
find that the trace now contains the
sample perfect tile and there's a
decision field which was not specified
in the original course but it's being
recorded in a trace and this means that
actually in this particular case
the sample value
factors equals 8 by
16 in here and if you double check
you'll find that hey this is you know 16
and
the
the outer loop j1 is 8 right so so
effectively this recall the particular
decision of this this sample parts that
gives you
and this is a very interesting way for
us to take a look at the transforming
decisions right so effectively this
particular if you have an initial
program and you have a
linearized trace the particular trace
also represents what's the final program
that we might get okay
and so so because three is another
alternative way so we can you know go
and try and run this and train our trees
and you can find that every time you
look at the decision field the decision
field in here kind of changes every time
we change the
every time well sometimes because well
we're drawing example with without
replacement right so every time uh we
will sometimes we will see the same
thing but sometimes we will see
different values as decisions
okay so that's the first taste of
stochastic transformation let's start to
dive a bit deeper on what's exactly you
know what are the additional details
that we're going on
so if we review this stochastic
transformations you'll find that it's a
simple generalization of the original
schedule with two additional elements
first of all we have sample perfect tile
it's going to return
two variables in here which will call
random variables that that uh and and
you know sometimes
you can use sample perfect tile to get
around the numbers that perfectly
factorize a loop we also have other
sampling operations like we can somehow
form a selection of deterministic values
like you know 4 2 or 8 and so on
we did not cover in this example but
there are other assumption operations
that are available
the second thing is that you know we
will have schedule transformation
before those squadron transformations
can take in
you know concrete integer numbers like
factor equals four to specify the size
of the loop down there on the factorized
in this particular case these actions
can depend on
those random variables in here so
depending on what
result what decisions were made at
random
variable sampling
the subsequent operations
and result of subsequent operations can
change okay
so let's try to run those stochastic
transformations step by step right so
the first thing we can do is we can go
and run some more perfect tile if you
look at this uh result of sample perfect
actually they are not real integer
numbers they are what we call symbolic
variables
so these variables
just
record that hey here's a random variable
that we're interested in and when we
pass those variables through
transformation api
it will they will allow us to specify
the choice of
of the vector values and those choices
again are being recorded
in a trace in here so so effectively the
schedule itself knows like now in this
particular evaluation of a trace
um this j factor zero cross one two
hundred twenty eight and j factor one
will correspond to one in this
particular case
and if you go ahead and look at the the
code that we have so far we can find
that the code does not change because
effectively at this point
we have only sampled the random
variables but we have not yet taken any
actions that depends on those random
variables so if you look at a trees we
do have those number perfect tile action
but it does not impact the current code
that are being
produced okay
so after we sample the random variables
we can go and take some actions right so
we'll be able to run a split
that depends on j vector
and reorder
and after we run it if you look at the
trace again
you'll find that we kind of append those
operations onto the trace
and if you look at these code that being
transformed in here you can find that in
this particular case you know it is
indeed different right so the order of k
and j one different there's additional
uh loop of last one because in this
particular case we are drawing a sample
of you know 128 by one
as part of this decision so this kind of
loop reflects
the programs that this trace gives us
and finally we can call re reload the
decompose reduction
and that gives us the final transform
location
okay
so one interesting thing that you
observed is that
it is a simple ingredient which is
sampling
that we add to this particular
set of transformations and it gives us a
very powerful way to go from
a single program you know take a single
programming transformation you get a
single program that's the original
uh original way of you know expressing
possible program transformations
in that particular case in the original
way kind of specify all the details
during the transformations
and it requires a lot of expertise and
also hand tuning if we really want to go
and optimize programming that way
and if we just just add a tiny bit of
you know randomness in here
and it will keep the space of possible
programs as opposed to a single program
and this kind of programming model is
usually called a problems programming
because you know when we are when we are
working on these uh transformations and
actions some of them involves rather
than something it's a very powerful way
for us to express a space of possible
choices in here as a result you know
when we are very certain example in
certain cases we are very certain that
we want to reorganize it from the
program this way we don't have to draw
random samples we can just directly
specify that hey i'm going to do the
same things this way but in certain
cases when we are not very certain about
hey what is the length of the loop i
want to split two what are the other
possible choices we can try to leave
that to the system so it gives us a way
to specify things that we are really
certain about while leaving out the
choices that are not very certain
persistent
okay
now what we are getting is the space of
possible programs right so one more
question we have is still you know yes
the space is good what we want is you
know we want to be able to take the
space and still narrow it down to find a
good
choices or a good set of random decision
that leads to
optimize probe
so one thing we can do is we can try to
do search on that space
and let's try to do that and the first
attempt we can do is we can actually go
ahead and write a python code that works
in this way the idea is that
because every time i will call
stochastic uh schedule mm it gives give
me a you know random program
a program randomly selected from that
space
so what i'm going to do is i'm going to
every time pick a random program go
ahead and build and benchmark it to see
how fast it is
and then repeat it again so that you
know
for a few times so that will pick and
then we pick the best one
across all the rounds right effectively
here's a simple program that tries to do
that so you take ir module every time
you cross stochastic sampling function
you'll build a program
and then you try to evaluate the result
which is the common cause in here
and then we're going to print our trade
so you can see every time what is the
exactly the proposal is and let me try
to book it and try to you know
bookkeep the best results so far and
finally i want to return the batches up
in here
okay
so this is a quick dirty way of doing
you know random search right which is
good in all cases at least you know
long enough gives you a quite decent
result
if the search space is fit okay so if we
run it you can find that you know i
tried five attempts i'm not going to try
a lot five or ten each overtime gives
you different decisions like
64 by two 16 by eight sixteen by eight
sixty four by twenty six four oh in this
case
rather than just like two choices that's
fine uh if you're going to write one
again it's going to
try different choices renaissance very
dumb in this case it's a very very dark
variation that just draws samples from
that
and you'll find if you read all the
runtimes you'll find that you know some
of them
most of them are actually quite similar
in this case maybe this one is a fast
right so
uh in this particular case 64 by 2 is
not that good
i'm just going to try one time again
to see if it gives us a better answer
yeah so in this particular case you can
find this one gives you know quite a
good answer in this case
and if you if you go ahead and print out
a chase you'll find that it picks you
know a by 16 in this case
and and usually you know this program
and and then you know we can use this
as our final program interest within
that space
okay
so so that's our you know poor man's
version of doing stochastic random
search over the states but general ideas
you can you can give your idea of how we
can take uh stochastic transformations
and compose that with a search right so
so you'll be able to go and pick sends
from a space and do search
in practice we want to do a lot more
things
for example in certain cases what if we
want to try and do stochastic search or
if what you want to deploy on to say my
browser or my mobile devices then we can
no longer do benchmarking or jubilee
notebook so we kind of need a way for us
to do benchmarking
sometimes you know we also don't want to
do this down to effect stochastic search
sometimes you draw the same samples
and the other times you know you don't
always need to go and run the code in a
lot of cases we can try to build
uh
some
you know intelligent estimations of of
how fast it is without having to go and
run the code
so
so there are better ways to do it that's
a highly high level just
and tvm provided utility to do that
search for a given search space we don't
have to go and understand all the
details i've already talked about some
of the magic behind but the key idea
remain the same so key ideas we can use
stochastic transformations to specify a
search space of possible possibly good
programs
and then we are going to call api called
tune tier
that's going to help us to search and
find our optimal optimized solution
within that search space okay
so here's what my schedule api looks
like
it's going to take a module
a task that's uh in this particular case
the task's main function
um the target that specifies where we
want to run it and this particular is
we're also going to specify a number of
cpu cores because this is uh
this is all the collapse so likely they
don't have a lot of costs i'm going to
use one core
the tuning config specifies how many
trials you want to run i'm not going to
run a lot so these are some of the
possible configurations and then the
search space comes from
the generator that generated by
this stochastic function okay
so i'm going to go ahead and run this it
will take a while that the effectively
under the hood it tries to
go through um possible program within
that third space
and trying to do bench markings and
actually this particular exit the meta
schedule function does not use random
search so it uses a advanced version
called evolutionary search and what it
works is that remember that we have
traces in here so we have traces that
have decisions
and
the the evolutionary search would not
try to rerun the sample schedule mm but
it will simply try to change the
decisions
that we have on the on each of the
stochastic
sampling and then try to generate a
program based on these updated decisions
and then the evolutionary search will
try to evolve it so that you know the
the decisions that these two better
programs
in the middle are being favored and we
try to reject us these traces that does
not contain better programs and
eventually it gives us uh
find a reasonable program fast okay so
that's kind of a high-level rundown of
what so what the evolutionary search
might look like but today we're not
going to in new details there are
different ways but however ideas give
you a third space you will be able to
use the meta scheduler tune to give to
you a transform schedule so after we do
that you can find you can look at you
know what they will find
actually in this particular case it also
finds 8 by 16 factor
this is a set of
program transformations that the tuner
suggests
we can go ahead and
you know display the code
that uh
do the split reorder and if we do things
after tuning you can find that
1.392
comparing to the original program it's
indeed faster
but look at unispeculates i guess it's
quite close to original manual schedule
so so far we have shown that for a given
search space that is specified by a
stochastic transformation we'll be able
to record metaschedule.2
or to be able to
get
get a
fine optimized program within that
search space
no actually messenger also comes with a
way to automatically generate a set of
search base so we actually don't have to
specify that space okay the only reason
that we specified in beginning is we
want to show
everybody what's the underlying
mechanism so the underlying mechanism
of this tomb is always you know trying
to use together transformations
to graph the possible states of
transformations that's going to join
so in this particular case the default
set of rules that mathematically is
called auto scheduling rules
and what they are trying to do is
exactly
slightly more complicated version of
stochastic transformation so what what
they are doing is that those
transformations will go ahead and look
at the program blocks
and try to reason about you know what
kind of possible transformation we might
be able to do
and then apply those
so although they are slightly more
complicated actually they are
the general principle is the same we are
trying to
build a set of stochastic
transformations and trying to use those
stochastic generation to guide our guide
the construction of our search space
okay
so in order to use that actually we just
need to remove the original space
specified so that it will it's going to
use a default automatic schedule
and if we'll go ahead and run it
it's going to
you know
use the set of internal generic
schedules and one of the interesting
thing is that those internal set of
general schedules
don't so originally we were trying to
write the schedule function stochastic
schedule formation location
log that is tied onto matrix
multiplication itself like you know we
want to get the particular block we want
to be able to do those
factors and so on the set of generic
schedules is made
so that they are relatively generic so
you can apply then on to you know matrix
multiplication convolutions and other
settings so you know
and this is kind of like
another advantage in terms of you don't
have to exactly specify the set of
transmission for a particular
prime function on the other hand there
will be cases where we want to come back
and extend
this
automatic scheduling or want to be able
to effectively you know specify proper
domain input onto what the search search
space might look like
that is a point where the stochastic
transformation api is going to
again come in handy because we are going
to use the same transformation language
to specify the set of possible rules
that help us to generate an optimized
program okay so now that we transform it
we can take a look at the term actually
if you compare it this one is much
faster than you know the original one
this is because the under the hood or
mass schedule actually have a much
larger search space than what we had
before so originally what we had is we
just do one level loop splitting and
reordering and we're just tuning that
particular one level
of the loop size
and if you look at the trace again
you don't have to go and read all this
because it contains some of these
transformations that we
have not yet
learned about
but the horrible summary is that it
involves some of the elements like you
know more level of loop tilings
uh if you look like here listen some of
the italian factors at least four level
in here or sometimes more than four
level
and sometimes it also involves a
vectorization of intermediate results so
in this case it's vectorized
uh is uh
give us you know calpers leverage
underlying
low-level
cpu vector instructions
and also involves parallelization so
although i say you know maybe we only
want to have one call but perhaps on
this machine there are parallel calls
and
that gives us better speed up and here's
the
final code that being transformed
that that's slightly more complicated
right then than the original one and
that and this particular tensor code at
least from the benchmarking suggests you
know it runs much faster
okay
so let's do a checkpoint so so far what
we learned
and this most important takeaway message
for developing on this lecture is for
automation i want to be able to automate
not only but also be able to go ahead
and build the program want to try to be
able to
automate the search
of this program
and
there are a few elements right so first
of all we introduced stochastic
transformations allows us to express
what are the possible
set of optimization we can do instead of
thinking hey here's exactly what we want
to do
to the program the second thing is
there's a tune function that you know
for a given space the tune function will
help us to find a good solution
um within that space
and finally uh nasty become a set of
default set of building transformation
that covers a broad range of search base
so if you call math guys on two
you will search over that default set of
transformations and try to give you a
reasonably good
search space and hopefully you know
within that services find a reasonably
good performing model uh for the target
device of interest
okay
and uh you know
if you are curious if we take a look at
the final program again that contains a
few more elements i'm going to quickly
walk through them so
there are annotations like you know
pragma maxima or road steps it will
hinge online compiler to try to
unload a loop in certain cases and that
will be vectorized make use of vector
instructions
and
here the block annotation itself is just
you know trying to inform that you know
what are the
what we call loop typing structure it's
not it's not does not contain uh does
not affect any of the underlying code
generation they just said hey
so if you look at this particular
program they are also parallelization so
so this particular program
um overhang
it's a dust contains a few more elements
on our hand it's not that complicated
but you know within that third space
it's very interesting to see that
this particular program i think runs at
least 10 pounds faster than at least a
very original product that shows that
you know the importance of trying to
explore
the set of possible transformations
really get a good performing code from
them
okay so so far we've learned automation
tricks and one thing that you might see
that hey this automation tricks only
works for a single parameter function
how can i use that for my end-to-end
neural network extrusion
so let's try to do that and
the kind of idea is that you know now we
have a tool
that allows you to take a parameter
function construct a search space
with industrial space find a good
solution
one thing we can do is know for android
neural net executions
and try to take the specific permitted
function of interest
to search and find a good solution and
tries to use that better solution to
replace the original primitive function
as a result the end-to-end solution
becomes faster right so let's try to do
that and we'll use
an example of two-layer multi-layer
perception from the last chapter so
we're going to do the same thing again
and
that's
the same set of preparations and
executions we're going to do
and this particular case is the trousers
we're going to download the weight and i
want to remind everybody so here's the
two layer model that we're going to use
and i'm going to load in the weights
in here
and we are going to use the mixture
module just to make the display simpler
so in this mixture module
the first layer
calls into tanzania function that we are
interested in here
the second two layers will just call
into external library function in this
case we are still going to use pi torch
so our pi touch library as our fallback
okay so the only thing that we can go
and optimize for is this first layer and
here it uses the default implementation
in here
again
if we're registering the corresponding
torch function
we'll be able to
we'll be able to you know and then we're
going to use a binded version in here
that binds the parameter into it and we
should be able to go ahead and do our
prediction and gives us a chance here
and then if we look at a term
here's original time cost oh one thing i
want to notice that actually you know
and because this is a very small model
so every time you run it does come with
a bit of fluctuation so take the time
cost with the grain of salt but
oh the overall magnitude is kind of
reasonable so so you know
if you are going to go and do our
optimization you will find that actually
you will get a speed up from this number
and let's try to recap what we want to
do right so effectively originally we
kept
the things in here so here's our
original ir module right that comes with
the linear function
in here
and in order to go ahead and do mlc
process on this what we want to do is
we're going to transform this collection
of tensor functions right in particular
we want to be able to take this linear
function
go
and run a set of stochastic
transformations that give us a search
space here
and then what i'm going to do is i'm
going to call a tune function that gives
us a hopefully optimized linear function
and then what we're going to do is we're
going to remove this
and then replace the linear function
here
that will give us a final
end-to-end module
that uh that is you know more optimized
because this particular primitive
function is being replaced by another
equivalent version but uh more effective
okay
so that is kind of an overall idea what
we are going to do here
now with this roadmap what we're going
to do is first of all we want to run
this a stochastic transformation and
tune step so
currently the
queue api only takes the ir module with
one main function so i'm going to do
some simple transformation
to take out linear function changes
global symbol domain and then trying to
convert it to another ion module so
effectively this is just
another implementation of linear
function
this module only contains linear
function in this case
it's more linear
and we can pass it to tune
here
that's going to run
the tuning
that gives us a
possibly optimized scheduling here
i'm going to wait about one minute
and then after we get the result what
we're going to do is we're going to
place the back effectively
we're going to first get another binded
version remember that this is from
original program
and then i'm going to construct a new
function
from the tuned result
and i'm going to get
so here global variable in here means
it's just like a pointer so because we
don't want only your stream to indicate
functions so global variable is just a
pointer name that we use to specify
global functions we can call then called
the update
function
in here
to try to update the original linear
zero with the new function
and then finally we're going to print
out the code in here okay
so hopefully it finishes tuning
then
while we run it
you'll find that actually in this
particular case
this linear zero
and here is different from the original
one so and this is the near zero that's
being defined by the
uh by the minus schedule okay
and then we'll go ahead and build it
again uh first of all you can find that
it still gives you the right prediction
trousers
and then if you're gonna run it
um
does it become faster
in this case actually it may not become
that faster because different rounds
come with slightly faster 0.39
and this particular case
3.0.37
but the main purpose of this is trying
to demonstrate you know the overall flow
of how we can go
and
take the original model take a linear
function and go ahead and replace that
so for this particular small model the
end impact is not as significant
but we're going to see
more bigger real large models then this
replacement
usually is going to give you much bigger
impact in terms of the end-to-end
running performance
okay
so let's come back and summarize what we
what we learned so far so
you can find that in the previous two
chapters we have focused a lot on what
are the possible abstractions what are
the possible
ways we can use represent or tensor
programs
and this chapter this absolutely focus a
lot more on
how we can go and transform
a tensor function this particular case
the primitive transfer function all
right and the second thing is we want to
focus on what are the possible ways we
can use to automate this and in
particular what we are doing is we are
trying to specify a set of stochastic
transformations
but what can be possibly optimized
without actually specifying all the
details
and then
the stochastic transformation will help
us to you know search over that
the tuning action will happen to search
over the space and find a good solution
and once we have this automated result
what we can do is we can piggyback that
onto antenna flow by just replacing
the original function with a new one
that is informed by
the overall training process
so again we can find that we're
following this generic moc process
except that we are focusing more on what
a set of transformation we have
in this particular lecture
we are mainly focusing on this automated
search of
permitted functions so we're taking one
primitive function
do a stochastic search tuning and then
come back and replace
and practice we uh enter a neural
network can have many many improvement
functions and want to do straight hair
search and tuning for
all of them and come back from place
and of course in a lot of cases maybe
you know
doing tuning or all those parameters
takes time so we can also do other
transformations like replace some of
them using library functions
or we can pretune a lot of these things
so we'll be able to go ahead and
generate search base try to know then
already recall those results on my
database
so next time i come in i will just need
to look up uh you know for this
particular case what is the setup
optimized program that we can have and
use that to do the replacing
and we'll cover some of those apis as
well in the following up lecture
so you'll find that you know this
overall process is centering really
around ir modules that help us to
present the collection of mixture
programs both permit tensor functions
as well as the end-to-end extrusions
using the combination graph and then
we're going to do different kind of
transformations so this lecture focuses
on
automating the stochastic transformation
of a single permitted function and we'll
talk about other ways of transformations
or follow-up lectures so also how can we
really compose them together to form an
end-to-end deployment form
okay so that's the end of this lecture
hopefully you enjoy it
and i will see you in two weeks thank
you everyone