Okay. So before this lecture we spent
four lectures to talk about GPU
architecture, right? So this is a rather
unconventional decision to make GPU
architecture before the CPU
architecture. We think at least I think
GPU architecture is simpler in many
aspect then CPU architecture is simpler
on some other aspect. So we use a GPU to
give you lots of preview [snorts] that
we touch a little bit on cache
coherence. We touch a little bit on the
uh instruction pipeline so that we can
give a preview for the rest of the
semester. So we use CPU to dive deeper
into this into the same topics again. So
uh like as when we first talk about GPU
architecture, we start with the software
the how to program a GPU, how to write a
GPU program and how the GPU assembly
looks like. And with CPU part, I think
all of you know how to write a CPU
program like a C program or Python
program. This type of program eventually
compile or into ISA.
ISAs can be different from one to one.
But the the main idea are close to each
other. So we use risk 5 is which is uh
like the most popular in academia today
to as an example to talk about the CPU
ISA the CPU um code. Then starting from
there in the next lecture we talk about
how the CPU core is designed with this
type of with specific to risk 5 is
although the general idea works for all
type of uh architectures. all type of
ISAS. Okay.
So starting from instruction set
architecture then we consider the
earlier programming. How earlier
programming is done is done by this type
of puncturing card programming. This is
really early. Then later on even with
storing techniques we write the program.
But when we write when people write a
program they write the program in a
machine specific way. So if you have one
machine write one program then there's
another machine if your company decided
to buy another machine then you need to
write all your code again but pretty
much at that time there's no big concept
of software reuse at anyway. [snorts] So
how does it work is typically in the
morning or in one day you prepare all
the punch cards that you really need to
uh execute. Then you give the punch card
to some like computer operator. Then
they will take your card and feed into
the computer. Then in the evening you
get a result. If the result is wrong
then you just have nothing to do. You
just figure out what's the problem and
the next day you send another card to
the operator. then they will execute it
for you. So consider how hard it is to
debug this type of code. Then although
the code are not likely to be very
complex at that time and the first
system that uh brings the idea of ISA is
the IBM uh 360 system in the year of
1964 and by that time [snorts] the goal
is to deliver a family of machines. So
they are they think oh we want to have
just high-end machines for some big
companies lowerend machines for some
smaller companies or who is not very
sensitive to performance. Then by that
time um how you can have one series or
one family of machines covers different
type of market but you want the software
to work on all of all of them. Then
computer scientists or computer
engineers the best thing that they are
good at is to think one way of
indirection right they think they just
introduce an abstraction layer so that
they can make the whole idea works for
different type of machines. So there are
two level two layer of abstractions
starting to get separated from this
point. One [snorts] is the architecture
level or sometimes it's called
instruction set architecture level. Then
this is a abstraction between the
software and the hardware. It's the
proto code between the software and
hardware that if we encode the program
in this way then our software hardware
will be responsible for you to get a
result. Uh but we cannot ensure you the
performance because the performance is
done at the second layer is to get a
lower layer that's called micro
architecture level. [snorts]
So the micro architecture level is
responsible for the implementation. So
for example you may have a lower end
with um some lower end cores may not
even have division module right. So they
can use some multiplication or add u
subtraction to mimic the division
operation. They definitely will take
longer time but it allows the device to
be cheaper smaller dice size. So there
are different type of micro
architecture. Another example is today
you might hear that on our phone or on
our computer there's a performance core
and the um the low energy core right. So
there they have different cores. So for
most of time the low energy core is good
enough for to respond for your uh
request. But when you really need high
performance when you are doing some
computing computation heavy workload you
really need a performance core. Then
this type of abstraction allow you to
have different hardware to support the
same program at a different performance.
So by that time we start to have the
separation between instruction side
architecture and micro architecture.
Okay. So uh today we're going to mainly
talk about one example of instruction
set architecture. On the other side then
for the rest of this lecture we're
mainly talking about micro architecture
side. Okay. So one particular example is
the journey of Apple computers.
Then starting from in 2004 they start to
use IBM power PC right then after that
they started transit to Intel core and
that was a very painful transition by
that time. Then later on they start to
transit to ARM to transit to the
machines that they are really designed
the chip really designed by Apple then
that's another very painful transition
by that time but Apple did it very well
by that time when Apple M1 is really
used immediately like we can feel like
experience improvement because the
energy consumption is much lower and the
design is much better than the Intel um
course now I don't know if you have used
the Intel machines Mac machines it
always make a noise then the battery
probably lasts two or three hours that
we always need to carry a power um the
power cable but with uh today's MacBook
Pro then almost I just use it I don't
need to bring it bring a power cable
with me for most of the time during
daytime this is good enough then So if
you consider this, this is already a
very painful process. Now for Windows,
if you if you know the journey of
Windows, Windows have been starting the
transition from x86 machines to ARM
earlier than Apple. But even today, you
probably won't really buy ARM based
Windows machine because of the
performance and before because of the
efficiency.
So on another side now if you look at
the GPU
if you look at the GPU assembly GPU ISA
then for Nvidia you have like when when
you hear about the architectures the
architecture Nvidia may have fermy um
these days we have hopper blackwell then
those are generations so generations
different generations of GPUs they all
run at a different ISA then AMD also
have this GFX X8, JFX 9, JFX 10, like
CDN, RDNA, RDN 1, RDN 2, RDN 3, these
are all slightly different ISA. So why
GPU is so easy to change on ISA and why
Apple is rather easy to change ISA, but
Windows is so hard, Linux is also so
hard to deal with the ISA transition.
It's mainly because of the ecosystem is
closed or open. for Windows or Linux is
there they really have a open um
ecosystem that means the compiler is
controlled by one group of people
software controlled by another group of
people then the hardware is controlled
by another group of people operating
system another group of people right
then they need to work together so one
side they change something the other
three parts also need to adapt to
support new thing just consider if you
one day change ISA then all the software
doesn't really compile Then there some
software may just no longer have a
maintainer. So nobody maintains the
software then nobody can simply
recompile the software for your new ISA
and if they cannot recompile then you
cannot use the software and
compatibility is a big issue. Applebook
definitely controls the ecosystem more
but for GPU vendors like AMD they
control the compiler they control the
intermediate representation they control
the hardware and the assembly they
control everything. So that's why they
can switch the programming uh they can
switch the ISA so quick that they do not
really have to fixed with one ISA
design. Okay, it's just different um
type of ecosystems.
Then you probably have heard of this
term called CISK and risk. One is a for
complex instruction set and uh risk is
reduced instruction set. Um
so the CISK design is large and complex
and the risk design is small and simple
right. So why CISK is so large and
complex is because in early stage the
your computer is not so complex. There
are some simple some uh some style of
instructions. For example, if you write
add instruction, if you write add a
right in write add instruction, add two
numbers together, you don't really have
to
uh deal with registers directly. If one
day one piece of data is in the memory,
no problem. You can just directly get
from the memory.
So in early days we in x86 we can have
some instructions like this R1 R2 then
this one is R3. I'm just making up.
Okay. So what does this mean is R1 and
R2 are registers. R3 is a address. It's
a memory. So we can load this piece of
data from the memory that represented by
this this address. The address is stored
in the register. Then we load this this
piece of data then perform add
instructions and store it there. Okay.
So this is a typical simple of symbol of
CISK um
instruction set. Then there are probably
more op codes more type of instructions
that they can support. You can combine
multiple in multiple operations
together. The risk is designed in the
other way because they want to be really
simple. Um why Cisco is designed in this
way? Because in early time the memory is
not that slow or actually the core is
not that fast. So the speed difference
between the core and memory is not that
large. So loading from a memory is not a
big problem. So we can just load it
while we're doing this calculation. Not
really slow. Today our core is getting
really really fast.
then we cannot really use this type of
representation here. So what we do is we
add dedicated load instructions. We have
load instructions. We load into R4 from
the data that is represented in R3. Then
we put R4 here. Okay. So we have more
program. We have more instructions in
our program to do the same thing. and
each pro each instruction is doing fewer
things then typically this type of
implementation is more um
friendly to today's faster course now
because load is super slow right last
time we talked about latency hiding load
is super slow now we need to put into
special instructions so that we can put
special consideration
u to this type of load and store
instructions Then and also today the
boundary between CISK and risk are not
that like distinct that it's really hard
to tell if it's a risk machine or a
Cisco machine. We all know that x86 is a
CISK machine, right? as x86
um Intel CPUs or AMD CPUs that we run is
x86
ISO
then but
it's um it's actually a risk under the
shell of a CISK ISA what it does is even
sometimes you see this type of
instruction
instruction they use something called
microode
What is a microode? It's basically an
ISA that you don't see. Uh they just use
this
x86 as a intermediate representation.
Then they actually do what they do is
they translate this type of instruction
down to load and add instruction. Okay,
they convert it into multiple
instructions. So they do smaller
operations
um so that they can achieve the same
level of performance as what risk is
doing. So this is what h what hap what's
happening internally at the Intel
machine. Okay.
So they still need to support x86 ISA
because of compatibility issue. That's
their burden from the history.
Okay. So we talk about machine let's
talk about machine languages. Then uh
what machine sees then machine sees
machines can see this type of binary
format or files when you run an
executable program what they see is
basically a file. Then the file is
encoded in binary. Right? Then this part
is the binary representation of this uh
instruction.
It's the binary representation of these
instructions. These are these are what
you what your computer sees like 001293.
These are representing hex numbers.
Okay, those are something that your
machine sees. Then um typically we say
there are two different format. One is
the binary format and one is the
assembly format.
Binary format is the machine language.
The assembly language is basically a
human readable binary format. Then
there's a onetoone combination. And also
if you look at here this is a
disassembled file. Now disassembled file
means we get this binary then we convert
into the assembled language and we can
see okay this bite this four byte it
represents addi instruction integer add
instruction. Okay. Then another thing
here that you can see this one 058 is
typically called program counter. It's a
pointer that points to these
instructions that if we want to execute
this instruction, these are the
[snorts] um are the address that is
stores in these instructions.
Okay. Then another very important thing
that if you see in Linux um environment
we see this format called ELF format is
executable and linkable files. These are
the file format used by lin by Linux for
both shared libraries and executable
files.
they have e format then there are
something very some something really
interesting that is recorded in this ef
format then for example e format always
starts with ef plus 07f
it's just a magic
string that represents this is a e
format then there are lot of information
that is stored there um as a header as a
header of this file just store the
required information. So this format is
predefined. So every program every
operating system at least the Linux and
Unix system should follow this format
definition. Even today this this format
have been designed there for many many
years but today they everyone is still
following in general following this type
of format. Now even for TPO programs
they still execute this type of uh
program. Um I just want to introduce one
form one concept. When we talk talk
about the GPU programs we always talk
about a concept called fat binary.
Bite binary means this is a binary
program that contains both the host
program and the uh device program the
GPU program. Then how it's done is
basically by compiling the GPU program
into a bite into a EL file on its own.
Then embed this part of EL file the GPU
file as part of the host EL file. Then
when we call that program, we just use
some pointers to redirect to that point.
Then we can start to execute that GPU
program.
Okay. Another concept here is called
application binder interface. Then um
then now you may heard of API
application programming interface.
That's how a how one program communicate
with another program. Now API is the
binary interface that how a program
communicates with the hardware. Then
these are predefined interfaces
predefined format so that your machine
can read.
There are several tools that can help us
deal with the e format. For example,
there's a read ef
have many um arguments that we can dump
different parts of the um e format.
Hex dump is another uh used tool useful
tool. It's not related to ef but it can
help you understand the binary format in
the hex style. Okay. So let's see you
can introduce something uh what's
we can use the read ef
output to understand a little bit more
about what's inside format. There's
definitely something that you can learn
on your own but I want to just point out
a few highle things. For example this is
the header of the e file right as we see
in the previous slide. Then it requires
it requires what's the type of the
program. Then what's the uh machine? Now
what's the ISA that this program is
recorded? Then start of the program
headers, section headers. So those are
other parts of the EL file that it's
pointing to and there size of the
headers and the section headers. Later
on we're going to talk about sections.
Okay. So section header table. What are
sections? So the program the EL file is
represented with different sections and
the sections are represent different
things.
For example, text um text are actually
execu uh stores the most important part
the program itself of the instructions.
Then you can see the flag here it's uh
um at least you can see the X this is
the executable part right this X
represent only this one is executable
then risk five attributes are standalone
for risk five now we don't talk about it
simple table string table are special
things for example string table records
all the strings that your program
requires for example when you print
something that uh like um this m this
this request is failed. Now we cannot
process our program crash. This type of
strings that are hardcoded into the
program that if you write a string that
prints something, everything is stored
in this string table. Okay, what is
symbol table? Symbol table rep re uh
records all the symbols in this program.
Now what are symbols? Then typically at
this stage you can consider two
different type of symbols.
Uh from here from here you can see the
symbols are although it's really small
there
uh say there are two symbols here one
start this you can consider start is a
special
function. Okay it's a function that you
don't write and another function is
main. So the function name all the
function names are represented in
symbols in your program. And another
type of symbol is labels in your
program. I'll just try to see I think
there should be one example. Yeah, this
is a symbol table. You can see start and
start and may are symbols, right? And
there are other parts of the other type
of symbols.
Um there's no label here.
Okay. So sometimes if you want to jump
to a certain location then those jump
locations are also represent by symbols.
Okay.
Then um now we talk about labels. We
have talk oh we have talk about labels.
Okay. Is there a label here? Oh there's
still no label. Then this main when it's
program is actually stored as a label
rather than a function name. So your
program your assembly doesn't really
know what is a function. So you it's
stored as labels. There are comments and
there the most parts are instructions.
So for example here we can see these
instructions as addi addi are for
integers. Um [snorts]
then there's special e call. E call is a
instruction that is calling operating
system features. Then
for example if you want to print
something if you want to allocate some
memory then those are all operating that
you want operating system to provide
some services for you. Okay. So for
example, we define one as
if we define one as the print integer
operation and we store it into a zero.
Now x0 is actually zero. It's always
hardware to zero. We'll talk about that
later. And this is actually a move
operation that moves one to a7. Okay,
just store it in a17. Then we store t2
whatever data is in a z. So this is a
move instruction.
They are there are actually both move
instruction. I don't know why this one
um this is disassembled in this way but
there are similar instructions.
Um we're moving from T2 to A0. So e call
is a instruction without oprint without
anything that we're processing on but it
follows some convention that we execute
the
system call number recorded in A7 and
the argument is stored in zero and in
this way we're printing
in this way we're printing the integer
in a z
okay so for example here system call 10
if We define system call 10 is exit.
Then we store it in 10 in A7. Then we
don't really need an argument. Then we
do e call then the program will exit.
Okay. These are some how something that
our program can communicate with the
how we or our program a user space
program can communicate with the
operating system.
Then for every instruction now we have
mimmonic that is the operation or
sometimes we call this part the op code.
Now for example this is an addi
instruction. Then we have oprint is the
element that we're processing on. They
can have sources and destinations.
Then the com is the first register. The
first element is the destination and the
rest are the the sources and we take we
take this as input and we store it
there.
And here we see t0 and x0 are registers.
There are registers that are store
storing the information for this
program. Have t 0 and x0. You have one
that's a immediate number that is
hardcoded into the program. So for most
of the
uh for many numbers that we can directly
encode these numbers
into this instruction. The instruction
will allow will allocate some bits so
that you can store some numbers. Um but
sometimes these numbers is a weird
number that is not some number that we
we can directly encode because the whole
instruction is encoded in four byte
size. Okay, then a one integer number
can be four by size on its own. So
sometimes there's no enough bit to store
here. Then these type of things should
be stored in some other sections of your
e file so that we have the pointer to
that point. Then we can load it the time
we need to use it.
Okay. So here are the instruction the
instruction format. Now we're not
specific for risk 5 uh
any type of instructions when any type
of assemblies follow this type of
format. Then we're going with risk 5 is
and see how risk five ISA is organized.
Risk five is defined by UC Berkeley then
as a the fifth edition of their risk
risk instruction set. Okay. Then it
highlights for extensibilities for the
base ISA. They only have RV RV is risk
5. RV 32I integer and RV 64i integer
instructions. So those are the basic
sets and they're really simple. They're
designed to work even for the simplest
machine. The minimum the minimum core
can support these type of instructions.
So there are some cores that are just
there to say in industry control like
control a robotic arm or something. They
really does not need to be high
performance but really need low power
and
um perform simple operations or
something a core that excludes in a
remote sensor that operates on battery.
Okay. So they want a risk five core a
simple risk five core executed on that
type of machines. So they are
intentionally designed to be minimum.
Uh but if you want to build with really
high power
cores with risk five
ISA yes you can do that then you can use
this type of extensions. Then you can
there are many standard extensions for
example the M instru extensions support
multiplication and division atomic
instruction single single precision
floating point double precision floating
point that means for a basic machine you
don't really need to support floating
point operation right for compressed
instructions the are special
instructions that have shorter
instruction u shorter sizes for vector
expansion then these are simply
instructions
that we can perform. We can calculate
new instruction. We can calculate
multiple numbers in one instruction.
Then this type of extension set require
extra registers. So these are really
flexible there. The bit manipulation
extension um
like bit level masking these type of
operations is really efficient at this
level. Okay. So there are many many
extensions that you can add. Then you
can also define your own extensions for
example that people are using risk 5 to
build CG devices that some devices will
talk about later. Then there is also um
like a trend of using risk 5 to define
GPU architectures. Then the GPU
architecture definitely have a different
programming model as CPUs. So their
instruction set is not good enough. So
they just add extensions to support this
type of GPU operations and so far at
academia level is successful. They can
demonstrate using something like FPJ to
simulate a GPU implementation a rift
fire based GPU extension and they
demonstrated it was possible.
Okay. So when instructions that are
encoded in a four byte long um sequence
then
a instruction set need to define what
registers are available. So how many
register are there in the default um
instruction set then you can see from x0
to x31 there are
32 registers.
So if you really have a simple
core, simple rectify core the each core
has 32 user programmable registers.
There definitely need other type of
registers that storing other
informations. Um for example,
is PC even here?
Yeah, PC is even here. There are some
other registers that are
like structural registers that just
required by the core. Next time when we
talk about the CPU architecture micro
architecture design, we'll talk about
those ar registers. Those register are
required to implement a cPU core but
user cannot program those things. So
only these 32 registers are something
that user is programmable and we
actually need to reduce this one because
x0 is always zero. Then even if we write
something into x0 it will stay zero.
Okay. Um so they have different API
names or assembly names. In assembly you
can either write something like zero
rabb or you can write x1 or x2. Okay.
They have different purposes.
um they are defined to be used in
different ways but these are more like
conventions. So you better follow this
type of convention if you want to work
with other programmers and other
programs. But if you really don't want
to follow these conventions uh in theory
yes you can do that you can just use s32
different uh registers
as just registers.
Okay, then descriptions. Now we can see
RA is return address, SP is stack
pointer, there's global pointer, thread
pointer. We're not going to touch that.
Those are temporaries. Save the
registers. It's a frame point frame
pointer uh function arguments. When you
call a function, then you use a z a1
and a2 to a7 to store the function
arguments. Right? Then a z and a1 are
also used for return values. So that
here you can use registers to return two
values and S2 and S11 are saved
registers. We'll talk about what save
the registers later and T3 to T6 are
temporaries. That means T so T02 and T36
are something that you can just use to
store some information there you know
without worrying that you are
overwriting someone else result.
Um so one thing you can see here each
core has 32 registers right that's a
really really small number coming from
the GPU word so how many register are
there in a GPU core let's just consider
vector registers for a vector register
for for a GPU core a vector register
so first of for each warp how many
registers that we can have. We can have
V registers
each warp.
Okay. Then each warp has 64
where we from
has 30 64 threads.
Okay, that means for each verb we need
this number
registers.
What's what's the number here? What's
the result here?
Uh
for then this 16 kilo 16 16k registers,
right? So five times 500 times larger
than that one.
This is this number of registers is also
the number of registers that is
associated with a wavefront pool and
also a SIMD unit.
So if you really fully use 256 registers
in one warp then that means this
wavefront pool can only include one warp
right because these registers are
allocated there.
you are using all the registers vector
register vector registers are one
limiting factor about how many wave
fronts that a wavefront pool can handle
[snorts]
the key point is I just want to tell you
that GPU really allocate a lot of
resources for registers while CPUs only
have a very few thing that's why if you
consider all this data is stored in
registers and if you want to store this
data into the memory it would take a
very long time and a lot energy. If you
want to store 32 byt of data, 32
register data and each register is four
byt. Okay,
if you want to store 32
integers into the memory, it will take
no time. No big problems. If you want to
store all this data in for GPU to the
memory, it will take a lot of time. So
that's why context switching for GPU for
CPU is very easy. For GPU, it's almost
impossible. That's why GPU can only
support something like you just execute
your whole warp until everything is
done. Then you just kill it then start
another round, start another warp. For
CPU, you can just execute a little bit
then store it back to a memory then
bring another context in another thread
in excluded and store back to memory.
That's possible.
Okay.
Okay, what instructions are there? So
for risk five, we can have a logic
instructions and or X or
uh
and there's a
I and I or I and X or I what's the I
there? I stands for immediate. There's a
one out print that is immediate number.
Okay. So those are bit level operations.
Then there's shift instructions. For
example, there's a shift left, shift
shift left, shift right and shift the
right. But why there are two shift right
is because one is called the just read
the third letter. L stands for logic. A
stands for arithmetic.
Okay. What is logic for left shift? No
problem. Left shift always fill with
zeros. The right shift has two different
possibilities. You can shift either
always shift zeros
always fill with zeros or you can fill
whatever data result is whatever bit
that is represent in the first bit.
Remember in two's complimentary
represent two's complement
representation if the first bit is one
that means it's a negative number if
it's a first first number first digit is
zero that's a zero or positive number
right so if we do shift to right then
filling with ones filling with the value
of whatever that is in the first bit
will maintain the value okay even if
negative num value will maintain the
sign. So that's why we need two version
of shift right operations. Then we can
have arithmetic instructions add I add
with an immediate number and sub
instructions.
So there's no sub i because you can just
add i with a negative immediate number.
Multiplication numbers are not risk are
not in the RV32 but they have a similar
format. I just want to mention to
perform one multiplication operation
four byte multiply by 4 by will result
in what?
Just consider 9 multiply by 9 will
result in 81. Right? So one digit one
digit will result in two digit. If you
consider 99 multiply by 99, I don't know
what's the value, but it's a fourdigit
thing, right? So in for
decimal numbers,
if we start with two digits, we end up
with four digit. And same thing here, if
we have four byte by four byte, we end
up with eight byt number, [snorts]
right? But remember each register is
four byte.
That means we cannot really complete a
multiplication operation in one
instruction. We have to use two
instructions to perform a multiplication
operation. That's why here we have M
which calculates lower for bite. Okay.
Here we have these two
and you we typically first calculate all
T2 S3
S5. Then at T2 here stores lower for
bite. Then more
h T3 this T3
stores the high
for by
okay two instructions to calculate
multiplication operations.
Then we need to talk about branching.
Then how CPU handles branching. Now it's
much easier than CPU here, but there's
some ideas that are similar. We don't
have the execution mask. We don't need
the predicated execution. Now we simply
because there's one instruction and we
just either execute it or skip it. So
here we have we add a conditional branch
instruction BEQ. There are some uh
conditional branch instructions. BQ that
means branch if equal, branch if not
equal, branch greater equal, branch less
than, branch greater equal Einstein
integer, branch less than Einstein
integer. Okay, some instructions. Let's
just look at BEQ.
BEQ means branch if it equals. If S0 and
S1 equals, we go to the target
point. Okay.
So target this you may look like this is
a string right in assembly this is
string
how it's encoded in u binary is
basically either by offset of the
address. So here there are two
instructions in between. So this may
probably be two or it can be a absolute
address just directly say oh the address
of this instruction then you can jump to
that point. Okay the target although it
takes a line in
takes a line in assembly it doesn't
really take any addresses because this
is stored in a separate symbol table. So
in the text section these are just
encoded one instruction by one
instruction. These are exactly four byte
away from the previous instruction.
Okay. So here if consider s0 equals s1
they both they're both four. If they
equal what do we do is we call this
branch is taken.
The branch by the way branch can either
go back or go down. Okay. So in this
case branch is taken.
Taken means we will take the branch that
will jump to the target. That means
these two instruction are skipped. Then
we don't even consider this
instructions. When brancher is taken
then we directly jump here. We execute
this line. Now when branch is not taken
we just go down. We just execute one
instruction by instruction. Then just
remember you see this code we do
something then after that we also do
something else. Right? If we do
something else this is add instruction
is the something else that we're
executing.
Something else we're executing. So in
assembly it's executed in the fall
through style. So there's no if else and
there's no branching it just if you well
but I cannot say there's no branching
there's no if else statement we just
directly go through instruction by
instruction okay if you really want go
somewhere else just add a branch there
okay this is on the flip the condition
the only thing is we ch the only
difference is there is BEQ on this side
we have B B and E then B means branch is
not taken. So we just go and we execute
this line of code. This line of code and
add finally add this add instruction are
executed anyway. Always excluded.
Okay. This one you can see the pointer
on the other side.
Okay.
Uh this branch is not taken. So there's
another type of uh instructions here.
We're talking about conditional branch.
So when the condition holds, we jump. We
go to another location. Another case is
we do we do jump no matter what. This is
called jump instructions or
unconditional branch instructions. And
here we can either just directly jump to
a label or jump to some thing that is um
some address that is represented in a
register. For example, if you want this
is represented by a
um either a redirection table or a
function pointer. So sometimes you in C
program you may do something like a
function pointer but sometimes you may
do like a switch case. In switch case
you may just say there's a table right?
If this is the case, this is the address
that you want to jump to. This another
condition, this is the address you
eventually want to jump to. Then this
address is stored in a register.
So last time we also talked about this
concept called basic block and which is
a basic block. A basic block is a
sequence of instructions that are always
executed together. So there's only a
single in entry point and a single exit
point. These four instructions, one
basic block. this uh two instruction is
another basic block and this instruction
is another basic block. Okay. So because
these instructions are always executed
together. So we sometimes just consider
those as a unit of scheduling.
Okay. Then we when we consider either
compiling or sometimes performance
modeling then we just model at basic
block level.
Skip this examples. Those are if
statement if if else examples. Then
switch is done in this way. So case one,
right? Case one is a is a label and we
do something. Now eventually when we're
done with this case one, we jump to a
certain location, certain location,
right? There's al also a default.
So there's always a J a jump to the done
operation. That's why we have need to
have a break in C program. So C is
designed to be really close to assembly.
That's why it just if there's some
instruction then we need a break
operation otherwise it's falling
through. Then some newer languages like
go they just re remove this feature.
They never fall through. So fall through
is really not intuitive to human.
sometimes is very likely to be the
source of bugs
right
now and while loop let's just spend a
little bit time talking about loops and
we never talk about assembly for GPU
loops right but in CPU so we can see how
loops are implemented and this while we
just write this label um in the same
line as this instruction okay but if you
write in a separate instruction is
exactly the same so what we do here is
at At the beginning of while this loop
we consider if s0 is equal to tier zero
or not right when they equal there's a
implicit
flip of this condition then we write the
program we say while it doesn't equal
right here we check if it's equal then
we just directly go out we flip the
condition now then when this two numbers
equals to each other we jump to done
Then we exit the program. Otherwise, we
stay in it. We just go down, do the real
calculation, then we jump, right? We
jump jump back to uh BQ so that it will
stay in that loop and keeps executing
uh array access. Now, I think last time
we talked about array access in GPU,
then we will skip this part.
Okay.
to binary format. By the way, uh so last
year I when I talk about the risk file
architecture, I spent two lectures to
talk about this whole session than this
this lecture, two lectures for what we
covered today. Then this year I really
want to squeeze it to one lecture so
that we can cover something more useful.
So, but we really need to talk about
this part because next time when we
design the core architecture, we need to
understand what type of instructions are
there, why we need this type of
instructions. Then
um so we can design the circuit directly
for this type of instructions. So there
are different type of encoding. So we
encode different uh different instru
instructions in different ways because
there are only four byte to encode one
instruction. So the resource is really
tight. So we can only use this limited
bytes to represent instructions. There
are lots of instructions for us to
encode. So let's look at what
instructions are there and what formats
are there.
There are basically six type of
instructions. We'll go one by one and
they also looks very weird. Will explain
why they are designed in this way.
The first type is the R type.
Rents for register because all the all
the operants are register in this in
this case. So
typically we consider in this way we
consider op funk 7 and funk 3 as one
unit. These are the op code. These are
bit that represents what instructions
what operations that we want to process.
So the op plus funk 7 and funk three
combine to encode add instruction.
Okay. Do you think how many bits are
there to represent this instruction?
There are seven bit, seven bit and three
bit. There are
uh 17
bits. That's actually a lot. But not
actually not all the 17 bits are can be
used because these ops are limited. We
need to reserve some ops to for other
type of instructions.
Okay. So but 17 bit for this type of
things and if you consider 2 to the^ of
17 or 2 to the^ 16 that's actually a lot
of instructions two to the^ 16 is
uh 64k
right now don't expect hardware can
support this number of instructions the
largest uh number of instructions is
what I see in AMD GPUs can support
something like 2,000 type of instruction
there are many instructions are there's
slight different variations. So for risk
five, we can execute say 100 200
instructions. That's already quite a big
set for CPUs.
But anyway,
so those bits encodes what operations
that we want to perform and we even the
RV 32i and RV 64i are not really using
all the bits there. They reserve some
bits. and they reserve some codes for
the multiplication division uh
instructions. But here there these are
the examples for example add S2 S3 S4
right. So here we use number 51 to
encode ops for add
if you consider 32 is actually only one
bit is changed right from zero. So only
one bit is changed from add instruction
then so we from this funk seven and funk
three and up we know it's add and sub
instruction then rs2 rs1 are the
different values here now you can see
those are encoded in this way now for
example source this is source one source
two right 19 then we directly write
number 19 here 20 we directly write
number 20 there although eventually we
need to convert to binary
But these are number 20 in decimal
format. Now here destination RD is for
the register destination. We simply
write number five here. Sorry number 18
here. This is why we have a second
representation
rather than S2, S3, S4. S2, S3, S4 are
more human friendly. There are four
different series of registers. But
eventually we just write X 18, X9, X20.
those are more machine friendly that is
easier to encode.
Okay, so this part and this part have no
difference but on the right side on the
machine code we have the binary
representation.
Okay, so our registers are the most the
most easy to understand. Okay, let's go
with the next group. So, by the way,
this is a table for all the instructions
in the RV32i
table. This is like a cheat sheet. If
you want to write something like um
super simple core in um Verlog or if you
want to write emulator then you can just
look at this cheat sheet. Then it's
rather easy for you to write the
disassembled instructions.
Okay. So this group are the RV
um the R type instructions. There are
only 10 instructions in the RV32 set.
Add sub shift left um X or shift right
or end. These type of instructions
support this format. And you can see
uh the ops are all the same. Okay. Then
this part are slightly different. On
this part there are only two only one
bit can change.
Okay. Only 10 instructions here.
So let's talk about I type. I type are
very close to R type. It just replace
one.
It just replace one opt with the
immediate representation.
Okay. So op is still up. It can be
slight it can be different from R type
then it only have a fun three. So it
doesn't really support that that many
instructions because it needs to res uh
reserve space for immediate values. So
what's the immediate value here? It's
from zero to 11 bit. So there are there
are 12 bit that can be used to encode
the binary.
um the immediate value. So you cannot
really encode a very large immediate
value is the range is limited. Okay. So
here we have some examples. For example,
addi we have number 12 that number 12 is
stored here. Then RS1 is nine that means
X9. RD is 8 that's X8 register and funk
is zero up is 19. Okay, remember two's
complimentary representation. If we need
to represent numberative -14, then we
use this special way to represent 14
negative 14.
Okay. So not many instruction here now
uh but in general it's very similar to
our type.
So from here I want to want you to
reflect why this is why risk 5 encoding
is designed in this way. It's designed
to be really machine friendly. So it
doesn't really want a very complex
decoder.
It want to be consistent across types.
So if you look at here,
look at here the low seven bit are
always ops right
from this way seven bit
are ops then five bit
are RD
three bit
are fun
are the function there
five bit
are RS S1
then only this part is different. The
whole thing at this part is the same for
R type and I type right. So for R type
here this three bit is R S2. This is R
type.
Then for I type then we don't have RS2.
Everything is immediate number. And for
this seven bit we have
seven. Okay, you just want to keep
consistent across different
type of encodings so that decoders can
be decoded rather easy way. So this
makes sense because you're not going to
read the binary code anyway. [snorts]
It's machine who will read the binary
code. So the binary code need to be
machine friendly not human friend.
question
uh when they're decoded. Now we will
we'll talk about that next lecture this
core design but
uh
so but I I can give you a quick preview
about how how this part decoding is done
right decoding decide two things or even
three things. So if you look at say this
is a register file right. So there's
some control logic needs to go to into
the register file. Say which register we
need to read. Okay. If you consider
register file in this way
then this is one register this x0 x1 and
so on. Right? Then eventually we need
this
this thing called alou.
Then how we can define which one fit
into this ALOU multiplexer right? So all
of them are connected to a multiplexer
that fits into one ALOU another
multiplexer here all of them are
connecting to both of the multiplexers.
We need to we need selector bit to
decide who can go through this uh
multiplexer.
Then AOU also can perform add
instruction, sub instruction,
multiplication instruction, many many
instructions. So what instruction need
to be performed there is also controlled
by a control bits to decide for which
operation that we need to take. And
actually
if you don't want to cons if you don't
consider power gating the annoying thing
about ALOU is
it actually works in this way.
So these two are connected to say add
unit. Okay, it can if you also have a
multiplication unit. So add unit and sub
unit are the same thing. Okay, they're
share some unit but they still needs
extra bit to decide if it's add or sub
operation to to that which type of
operation that we're considering. They
just need extra bit to go into this
combination logic. Then there's a
multiplication operation. There can be
shift the left,
shift the right
by shifting operations. Then the
annoying thing is they go to all of
them.
Then eventually there's a multiplexer
that select which result that we want to
use. Then this multiplexer also need
control logic decide which one which uh
which result is eventually selected.
then go back to the register and
eventually when to go back to the
register for writing right. So this is a
the other way of the multiplexer to
select which register that we can write
into.
This also requires decoding process. The
decoding process need to parse this
format to select to decide this control
bits that controls the rest of this the
back end of this pipeline.
this something that we're going to talk
in next lecture.
Okay, let's just quickly go through
other formats there.
uh S and B type for example S
this S type
um S stands for store so we store the
data to the destination I think we can
quickly skip this part because you can
uh read the document there's something
more important there this is B type
um something that when you read the
technical documentation that you can
understand how it works.
I want to talk focus slightly more on
how functions are handled. [snorts]
Now why the registers are temporary
registers and uh [snorts]
um stored registers different type of
registers. So we have an example of
function then a function has a function
header we have return values and input
arguments and the operation that we're
doing here and the return
I don't know where I find this
screenshot I don't know why this return
has a parenthesis there and this is not
good C syntax it's not wrong syntax it's
just not good
return is not a function call return is
a statement right so but anyway It
returns the sum operation then it
returns something. This is C definition
some other language we can return
multiple values.
Uh but is so this is a function and how
this function is encoded into a uh into
a CPU program in assembly. Then we need
to understand the concept called stack
frames. Right? So when we call this
function we grow a stack frame. Then if
we call another function we go another
stack frame. when we return we decrease
the stack frame.
So how these stack frames maps to uh
assemblies. Now we can look at how
assembly works and how assembly deals
with registers. How assembly can handle
this arguments and also the return
value.
Uh
so I just want to quickly give you some
arguments how we handle arguments. We
can use registers to handle arguments.
Okay. So this is something that is
defined by a calling convention. A
calling convention is defined com
jointly by the ISA the operating system
and the
compiler the program language and the
compiler. So all of them can decide
like which type of calling convention
that we can use. And if you say C
language working on Linux may have a
calling convention. But if your compiler
really want to develop some new calling
convention, it should also works in
general.
So this is a risk five calling
convention. Then they start with a
simple function that doesn't do
anything. What we do here is when we
call we use a jump a jump and link
operation. The jump and link is doing
two things. It jumps to simple this
label, right? Simple is here. It jump to
this point and start to execute from
there. But also we need to know where
we're jumping from.
Right? So that return we can return to
that location. It's not randomly
returned to any location. So we can
return to the location. So JL is
performing the other operation. The
second operation is to store the current
PC actually the PC + 4 the next
instruction otherwise we're going to
execute this function call again it will
jump to another location say PC plus4
into array. So when whenever it's doing
PC plus4 it involves some adder some AO
operations there. Okay. So it stores
PC+4 then we jump there. Okay. Then this
simple if it's a return then we don't
need to do anything. We simply jump
back. Jump and return. Then we return
back to the original location.
U so JR here is jump by register. So the
RA is the register storing the address
that we're we're jumping to.
Then when we have arguments, how we deal
with arguments? So look at this example.
We have FG J FJ FG hi and F plus G minus
H plus I. Okay, we need to parse four
arguments and there's one return
argument. What we do here is we store
them in a z a1 a2 a3 right those are the
arguments that we pass.
Then here
we
what we do here is we do the add
instruction another add instruction r
type instructions and we do the sub
instruction then eventually we do this
add at three z into a zero.
So for most of the time if we hand write
a assembly
we would typically write MV instruction
move instruction and we typically write
move A Z S3
okay
move whatever in S3 to A Z
then but if you consider the effect a
move instruction has nothing no
difference with adding zero and store it
into another address. Right? So to save
one instruction, there's no need to have
a encoding for move operation.
They simply use add to replace. Okay.
But if you handwrite this instruction,
the compiler or the assembler can also
recognize this instruction and can
compile into and can assemble into that
add instruction. If it's a disassembled
it will disassemble into add
instruction. Okay. So this type of
instruction is called p sudo
instruction. So instruction does not
exist but also exist somehow exist in by
convention. [snorts]
But anyway here this is a move
instruction just move to a z. Then we
jump back to this location. Then we
continue to execute this add
instruction.
However there's a problem. The problem
here is this S3 is a special
instruction. So if the main program use
S3 here then use S3 after this point the
S3 because S3 is modified then the
context in this main function is not
maintained.
Right? So the problem is this S3 is
being modified. Remember S is a stored
instruction and is a CI
is a caller maintained instruction. See
here as instruction or save the
instructions saver who should save it is
colle
who is using it is the caller right the
main function is the caller the diff the
the diff of sum is the colleague. So the
caller is actually using it. So color
will assumes that this fun this value is
not changed.
Okay. So that's why we cannot modify it.
We cannot modify here. If we're
following the risk five convention, we
cannot mod we cannot modify this value.
So what we can do here is we can
what we can do here is if we really need
this register we can store it in memory
and recover it from memory before we
return. Okay so that the context of the
main is maintained is not changed.
So, by the way, T are temporary zeros,
temporary
registers. They're temporary registers.
That means the colleague can change it
however they want. The caller should not
expect they are consistent.
Okay. [snorts]
Right. So, they can modify it any way
they want. then the caller cannot really
expect that they are they have the same
value after this function is called
F3 is a problem here.
So what we do here is a more
conservative method. We form a stack
frame. How we form a stack frame?
So consider
there are several values that are useful
right for example we have i3 t1 t0 and
t1 those are the values that we're going
to use
in our main program this we need to use
t0 t1 t s3 right we need to use these
three registers what we do is we first
store whatever in s3 to
sp the stack pointer
by eight, right? Offset eight.
What we do here is we grow the stack,
make the space on stack to store three
registers.
So we
change the stack pointer value. We we
decrease by 12. That means we're growing
the stack. We're allocating some space.
Okay, stack are a piece of memory that
always consider being allocated but
there's a fixed size. You cannot
allocate too much element in stack and
we we add this number. So we grow the
stack we allocate some um
space. So that's why this part of
allocation is really fast that is much
faster than maloc.
If we can save something on a stack, we
should save something on the stack. We
should avoid a heap. If we use heap, use
melo is stored on a heap. Question.
These are nothing special. It's just
part of the memory, main memory. It can
be cached, but if it's cached or not, we
don't control.
Uh so these are not hardware specific
memory. It's just regular memory that
say this is CPU then we have a on the
motherboard we have those um third party
dim memories then we just inert there.
Okay.
So stack memory then we store this data
to we store this to S3 store this to T
store T0 to this part at the stack store
T1 to the stack. Then we perform the
regular operation, right? The regular
operation is performed here. Then before
we return, what we do is we recover the
context for the main program for the
color. So we just basically we load data
from whatever that is stored on the
stack. Then we save it back to i3.
Okay. We save this to T0. We save this
to T1.
Okay, this is a context recovery
process. So I have to say this is in
general this is not how risk 5 should
handle things because
we have T0 and T1 right T0 and T1 are
assumed to be maintained by the
colleague. So colleague can modify it
whatever however they want right that
actually save some operation some some
save some load and store operation load
and store operations can be expensive.
So we want to reduce this thing. So in
fact we can simply remove this and
remove t0 and t1 and keep the stack
frame to be only one register that
works.
There is a more risk five style stack
management.
Okay. Some commonly used data can stay
on the stack.
Then as you may notice this this is too
conservative and u we can simply use the
stack to hold S3 right this is the risk
five style then it can reduce some if if
it's a small function then we can reduce
the load and store operations there now
we can even do something more aggressive
basically we have a z there then a z is
the a z and a1 can be used for return
value right in this case we can directly
write the result into a zero and just
eliminate A3, no problem. Then it just
really depends on if the compiler is not
smart enough to use this type of code or
not. And this is a really small example.
When there's a really complex example,
probably just do not have the chance to
do this type of operation, right?
Sometimes your stack frame is really
large. If you write something like
int
a
then all these
six 16k data are actually in the stack.
Okay, it's a statically allocated part
of data. Then you article this number
there. Then this this data on the stack.
This definitely cannot be handled by
register. The whole thing is handled by
the uh stack.
Okay.
Okay. So when we call talk about
non-leaf functions then there are some
registers the caller need to save. Now
when we call these functions if we the
caller have been using t0 to t7 and a z
to a7 they have to save it into the
memory then recover it when they need to
restore the value again continue to use
the value again. Some registers are ci
to save for example s register ra the
colleague need to save this type of
registers.
Okay, the another thing is the stack
grows and shrink when we call function
and we grow the stack to store this type
of information temporarily so that we
can recover later.
Another thing is called register
spilling. So sometimes the register is
not enough to handle the data that
handle the variables required for
whatever that we need to store in the
register. For example, if you have a lot
of things like this, ideally you want to
store all the variables that your
function need in the register. So that
is really fast, right? Um
however on CPU on rich 5 CPU a simple
core you only have 32 registers and many
register like RA SP there something that
you cannot use. There are only a few
register you can use. So when the
register is not is not enough you have
to use stack memory.
to manage those variables and whenever
you need to use it load it back to the
register and start to do the
calculation. Okay, it's kind called reg
spilling. Then for CPU's register
spilling are kind of expected because
the reg space are so small. You don't
have so many registers that you always
spill. But on GPU, this is something
that we should try to avoid as much as
possible because we already have so much
register