now 7 so starting from this episode
we're going to do a two episode series
about
gpu and howard acceleration
and
so one note is that
this particular
notebook and next one is going to
require cuda dependency so you will need
to run the relevant part on a kuda 11
environment
if you don't have such an environment
it's also fine as you can go and follow
along
and
actually the particular uh sum of code
generation called also generalized to
non-cooldown content that we will also
mention later so this is part one of gpu
acceleration
so i'm still using this collab
environment except that you know i'm i'm
using the gpu enabled so right now if we
take a look there's a tesla 300 gpu ring
here that i'm going to use today
to demonstrate some of the today's
process uh to begin with um we're still
going to import some of the necessary
dependencies
so
gpu is kind of an exciting topic you
know says that i still remember when i
started working on
deep learning and building machine
learning systems uh the first thing i
did was you know pack a a very old gpu
card and bringing in deep learning
models onto those devices
one main difference between a gpu and a
typical uh central cpu processor that
you might see in your mobile phones or
on your
laptop is that gpu themselves are
massively parallel
so and this is kind of like an
illustrative diagram of what a gpu
architecture looks like so normally uh
you will have a global memory so on your
bio gpu it says you know you have 24
gigabytes of dram or hbm this is a
global memory part
and then within global memory
within the gpu there are multiple
overpower stream multiple processors so
so if this is a gpu
actually we'll have multiple of those
stream multiple processors that stream
multiprocessors that sits on a cpu card
each of the stream microprocessor
contains a group of compute cores in
cuda they call it cuda cost that's that
can be viewed as an independent
extrusion unit that allows us to execute
some related computations on the on the
respective course
and effectively each of the stream
microprocessor kind of corresponds to
this kind of this kind of global unit
and another interesting thing about gpu
is that um you know within each of the
stream mining processors that have
explicitly managed what we call shared
memory
um that can be accessed by all those
calls so this is not
uh this is the typical you know nvidia
gpu or amdgp architecture uh if you look
at some of the gp architecture some of
them may not have shared memory or have
other special things but normally you
know you can view it as a this kind of
two level
uh two level structure where you have
global memory you have streamlined
processors and you have uh each of a
call that can execute the code in a
reasonably independent fashion
so normally on a gpu you have multiple
of those three microprocessors
and
as a one of the key interesting thing
about gpu is it's massively parallel if
you look at a
typical video gpu it can contain more
than thousands or sometimes tens of
thousands
that means that effectively you can exit
so many things together right comparing
to a typical cpu gap you can get
normally you can get up to 64
cores at most if it's a you know server
class cpu
so so that's a huge amount of difference
on the other hand
the type of operation that gpu cost can
perform is also somewhat limited also
um you know
it can actually serves most of our
machine learning workloads
so now we've introduced this a generic
overall architectural view of the
streaming mining processes let's come
back and
talk about you know how we normally
program a gpu
so conceptually
when we have a gpu and hand what we do
is we try to map the computations onto a
group of threads so so so in this case
now we have one thread a program that
describes one thread that get maxed on
to a lot of the other uh chords in here
and then
multiple threads can be grouped together
and each of the these multiple tracks
can form what we call thread block
and during extrusion time this ram block
get mapped on to you know a stream
multiprocessor effectively onto here
and then finally we can launch multiple
blocks that can get mapped to either the
same stream other processor or different
microprocessors so
effectively uh in here
each of the block in here kind of can
expand onto a list of threads and
another blocking here can also expand to
another uh another list of strategy okay
and this is conceptually you know how we
can program this
and
now let's try to
start to see a concrete example how we
can use tens ir and some of the things
we learned in the past lectures to also
perform some of the gpu optimization on
on the gpu that we have on this notebook
so first of all we do is we can define
a
vector add operation program so in this
case this uh
tensile program recall that we have
buffers
uh these
loops and the particular operation so in
this case we are simply taking two
vectors and try to add them together
in order to map the auto gpus remember
that we have the
gpu contains many threads right so ideas
that we want to try to map them on to
the strap blocks and threads
so so you want to do that let's first go
and split the loop
eyes right now we have only one loop and
in the next case i'm going to split it
onto
two components like the internet outer
loop in here
and then what i'm going to do is i'm
going to map it on to the thread in the
indices of a gpu
so
normally a gpu program
for each of a thread it can be
identified by two indices i'm using cuda
terminology here but you know if you are
familiar with other gpu terminology like
openmp opencl
or you know sycl or
or metal you know that can be a slightly
different terminologies but usually you
know they translate to each other
the threat indices refers to the offset
of the threat from home in this
particular case within a swear block the
first threat is 0 1 2
and so on so so these are like thread
indices and then the blocking this is
refers to the offset
of each of the strap so one so
effectively uh threading the thread
index and the block next help us
uniquely identify
a threat within that
within the kernel that we launched
all can do here is we're going to try to
bind the iterators onto block index and
strategies here so if we do that and
you'll find that in this particular case
the for loops contains what we call
thread mining construct that indicates
that hey this particular loop is going
to be binded to
a gpu
strap and so so effectively when we
launch this we are not executing these
two followers so these two follow-ups is
going to be uh it simply maps on to the
environment gpu indices that's available
on that particular strip
and one interesting thing is that you
can find that all the thread actually is
running the same program with the only
difference come from
the the the
indices that that that you you have on
that on that particular thread for the
block index and thread threading next
offset
that
uh on that particular
on on that particular strap that that
all
so now that we have this um
now that we have this you know
program that bonded those iterators onto
gpu threads
moving next what we can do is we can and
go and build and test out the resulting
function on gpu so so in this case we
are running a similar procedure with
only differences that we are trying to
set the targeting here as cuda so that
we will be able to build the particular
um the particular module on the cuda
environment
and
um
we are also creating you know uh the
input
uh
ran ring random vector in here and where
we are copying onto in this case through
two and the arrays on the cooldown
environment and we're also allocating
our output and the array here okay
and running next the the way we invoke
this uh generated gpu kernel is the same
it's the same way we invoke the original
uh previous tensor functions that we had
in the past lectures so all you need to
do is to passing three and the arrays
with the only difference that we are we
are going to pass in the uh cuda device
context in here instead of the normal um
instead of instead of a normal cpu
context we had in the past lectures
we can print out to say that actually
you'll find that the corresponding
elements did add up together and we can
also go and use the numpy answer or
close to to to confirm that actually all
these all the results match up
okay so far so good so that's a
gpu example 101 that help us to you know
go and try out one running example of
adding two vectors together
okay moving next let's move towards
another example that's slightly more
complicated so in this case what we're
interested in is we are interested in
taking this input array
and trying to do a windows sum so the
idea is that for each of the elements
i'm going to look at a window of size
three and add those three elements
together for example if it's one two
four and the result is going to be seven
or on this particular element
so so it's kind of like a tiny version
of convolution with uh with the weight
of with with all the weights equals one
okay
so um here is our
window sum program that we can write out
in terms ir with a simple loop that that
looks over the output space and we are
going to try to add three consecutive
elements together
um to run this we know some on gpus
again we can try to do the thread
splitting and try to go and bind
the corresponding elements onto
the the threading next and block
indexing here
one of the things we noticed uh is that
actually you know in order to
optimize this program one thing that we
want to notice that you know
if you look at the gpu overall gpu
memory hierarchy here you can find that
each of us threads have a shared memory
that we can leverage
when we are trying to go and run this
particular program naively right you
have each of us thread go and read three
elements in here and this neighboring
strat is going to read the other three
elements the neighboring stride is going
to read another three element
and you'll find that actually there are
quite a lot of overlaps right
of on of each other element that
that i've been reading here so for
example if i'm going to read
this because this is going to read these
three elements this thread is going to
read these three elements and this this
shadow area are the areas that are that
are overlapped
between the reading region between
uh these two elements
okay
so so
how can we go and further optimize it so
one more thing that we can do is we can
try to leverage the shared memory here
that's being ensured across multiple
threads
and the idea is that instead of trying
to
have each of us rather go and directly
read from an input
let's try to try to
collectively get all the threads to read
the input together assuming that i have
four thread in my group in here
and you'll find that actually i only
need to read this
amount of elements and if i'm going to
go and read it individually i will have
to read 4 times 3 terms
from the from a global memory but if i
try to directly read this region in this
this region that by considering the
possible overlaps i only have to read
four plus
i guess is four plus two elements right
so this equals 12 that equals six so i
almost get a half reduction in terms of
reading the data from google
and another thing that i forgot to note
is that
the cost of data loading just like when
we introduce the cpu optimizations
there's always the memory latency and
throughput cost of from the
the lower layer of memory hierarchy
similarly
the cost of loading from global memory
to shirt and should memory through the
to the registers are very different
the cost of loading from global memory
to shoot is much larger usually than the
cost of loading from shield memory to
the to each of the threads
so as a result usually we do want to be
able to fetch the data first onto the
shared memory then try to
run computation there of course one of
the trade-off here is that each of the
gpus have limited amount of shared
memory so we kind of need to plan to use
that a bit wisely
okay so in order to do that in our
tensile program what we can do is we can
try to create a scope called shared
in this case um we are using this cache
read construct effectively what i try to
do is create try to create another stage
so if you look at the original program
the producer consumer graph looks like
if you are reading from a and you are
trying to run computations on the b and
effectively
in here i'm trying to
create what we call
a shirt program
and then going to read that onto onto b
okay
and
and another thing that that we do here
is we are also trying to put the shield
memory loading at a particular region in
this case i'm putting that
on the the under the block index
here so that
um
in other cases you know we might want to
put them on the on the thread index
actually actually in this particular
case you know putting it on this redness
is also fine
uh
let's try to see if that's the case
so i'm putting it on the threading next
it's also okay
okay one thing that we want to
um
[Music]
one thing that we do want to note though
is that
you know because it's a shield memory
right and
as a result we still need to re-specify
how we are going to how each of thread
is going to read which element of the
shared memory if you if you look at this
program you can find that now we do have
whoa
this is the sugar shape so
we might need to because it's imperative
we need to write over again
try
yeah so so in this case
because this is a shared memory although
it's already in the thread index regions
we still need to re-specify how we're
going to read each element
of the shared memory because you know
this memory is being shared
and the threat binding patterns can be
different
okay
so the way to and another thing you'll
notice is that as of now
i1
is in australia index
it appears on the normal computation
block but i1 does not appear in here
right so so effectively
if we now if around this particular
program
each of the thread is going to go and
trying to attempt
reading and it's going to go and try to
attempt read most of the
uh
most of the 100 elements all together so
in that case in that sense it's not it's
not
a very efficient way effectively threat
0 is going to go and read all of them
thread one is also going to read off
so so what would distributor work a bit
to mount the amount of threads in the
computation
we can do is we can try to get the loops
here
split it and then rebind the strand so
in this new program
what's happening is that you can find
this is the reading region
and that one thing you notice that you
know this thread index finally appears
multiple times
but within our computations you know
because all x is directly maps to this
value index right so we are only going
to count for one term
and effectively what it says is that i'm
going to distribute the loading task of
the
of the a shirt across multiple straps in
particular this program will try to
distribute a loading task
of a shirt on from
uh you know if i were i i could assign
stride zero to read this one to read
this to to read this for to release and
zero one again
so at most you know one thread have to
read two elements from that
from the shared memory as opposed to
reading all the elements or you know
reading the corresponding elements that
are interesting
this is a technique called cooperative
fetching
because each of threads are kind of
cooperating with each other to fetch the
data that we're collectively needed and
this is a very commonly used technique
in gpu programming to fetch the
necessary data from the external global
memory onto the on to the local field
memory that we're interested in
okay
finally we can actually go and inspect a
bit what does final code look like so
right now we have this uh tensor ion
code in here
and
what i'm going to do is i'm going to try
to build it to a put up program and try
to print out the source code so in this
case when we view the kuda code under
under the hood we try to generate two
components in here the one component is
what we call host driver that
calls on to the gpu driver and it
launches the kernel and then the other
component is the cuda kernel that runs
the corresponding computations
the phone code prints out the
corresponding cuda kernel
and
in order to run this crack now it still
needs to be driven by the host program
but the cooldown kernel itself kind of
is a good way for us to tell you know
what is the final code looks like if you
look like this code you can find that
hey we have a short memory component in
here
there's a shared memory loading
and you can realize that you know
there's no sugar memory loop thing here
right the shared memory loops directly
translate onto the australian accent
here
once we load things on the shared memory
we will run this windowed computation
which uh if you scroll over you will
find that you know hey this is a window
computation over three elements thank
you
another thing that we can we need we i
want to note in here is that if you look
at the size of shield memory it's
actually smaller than the original
original size which is 127.
and this is the reason this is because
you know during the build process the
overar
program or try to compact the memory
buffers during the build so that only
try to use the shared memory size in
corresponding to the size of memory that
we touches in intermediate stage so
normally that's more efficient than you
know directly allocating the bigger
achievement which actually sometimes
runs out of memory of the gpu capacity
okay so far i'm going to now we've
talked about two concepts how we can go
and bind things to gpu threads and how
we can leverage shared memory and do
co-operative fashion to bring data from
global parts onto
this uh onto this um stream
multi-processor shared memory and then
run computation there
and so far we've talked about you know
how to build this entire process in a
cuda platform
a typical machine compiler allows us to
support multiple kinds of hardware
platforms but we can also join the
opencl code
by taking a different target string so
in this case i'm passing opencl here and
if you have
run opencl kernel before you can find
that these are the syntax that
writes out the same kernel in opencl
now the syntax is you know roughly have
a one-to-one translation actually you if
you read the kuda kernel you will be
able to tell that hey there's a roughly
one one-to-one mapping that allows you
to map the original cuda column to the
corresponding uh to the corresponding
opencl kernel here
and
we also support other targets like metal
other cases let's say
if metal is enabled i'm not too sure but
okay yeah so this is the metal kernel
that allows you to run the same program
on
apple gpus
okay
so that's the first part now we talk
about some of the gpu basics
moving next let's start to try out um
running
uh
running um our tensile transformations
and try to optimize a slightly more
complicated program which is matrix
multiplication that we have
studied
in some of the past few lectures
so this is our original pencil program
that chris won through
matrices
a and b and multiplied together and we
are going to
load that onto c
so we have a few transformations to
optimize this then try to map that on
the gpu
the first technique that we're going to
use is what we call our local blocking
or register blocking
the idea is that for each of us thread
by trying to load um we're trying to do
instead of computing each of the
elements we're trying to compute one sub
matrices at a time
so for example i could choose to compute
uh four by four sub matrices here
and you know it together so the ideas
you know formula um
each of the iterations what i'm going to
do is i'm going to read in one stripe
of this
input from a
another stripe from b
recall that my our matrix multiplication
operations formula is c i j
equals
sum
k
a i k times
b k j
so in here i'm trying to compute this
for
a sub region of i from i can compute it
for i equals 0 to 4
and j equals
j inside 0 to 4 so so it's effectively a
loop that that allows us to loop into a
sub region
so what is the advantage here
the advantage is that because i'm going
to compute this sub region
each of the time i'm going to
read in this drive
and this strike right
and
and in order to compute this first
element actually i'm going to need the
first element of a
first element of b
let's say that this is a to simplify
like this let's say v equals 2 okay in
this case
you know in order to compute this
element i need to read this element
and
this element of b
then in order to compute the second
element i still need to read the same
element of a and the second element of b
now i'll compute this element i'm going
to need to read this element and this
element
in order to compute this element i'm
going to read
this element at this side
you can find that interesting case is
that when we're reading these stripes
a and b
in order to compute four elements right
each of the
uh inputs a and b stripes
is is being re-twice because you know
uh because for each of these elements in
here it's going to be needed for
computing the output of all these
results in here
so this helps in in a sense that it
helps to reduce the amount of read that
we need to read the data from a global
memory and this is also called register
reuse because we are
normally reading data onto a and b and
you know we can reuse those data
multiple times as we compute this sub
matrix
and and this helps us to reduce the
amount of load that we need to load the
data from outside things so usually this
is a very helpful technique in both
most of our actually you know in both
cpus and gpus
so we're going to do that then this
program is slightly more complicated
than we our previous one i'm going to
walk you through that
this is our original
this is our original loops we're going
to do is we're going to try to split
i j and k
into two components and and or actually
in the case of i j we're going to split
the three components
and then try to try to reorder that a
bit and then try to map it outside on
the gpu thread the innermost remember
that i want to keep this register
blocking here okay
so so let's walk you through this so the
first thing we're going to do is we're
going to get the block c
another thing that we're going to
because we're going to try to um you
know first
compute run computations and store that
onto local memory i'm going to create a
different stage called c local that
that we use to cache the computations on
and then
um what what we are doing here is we are
going to split
loop i and j onto three components and
loop k on to two components
we're going to reorder
the the looper bit
so that uh
they form a more interleaved pattern
these are called tiling patterns that
allows you know that forms the outermost
loop in here
and then then then i won
the iterators and j1 and i2 i2 and j2
once you notice that we are ordering j2
and i2 inside the reduction rule and
this is exactly to do what we call this
uh
register blocking that allows us to
compute
all the elements
and that's in the domain of i2 and j2 in
here that correspond to effectively and
this direction can be viewed as i2
and this direction can be filled at j2
and finally we are bringing in this c
local computations back onto
this in j1 loop
and then we're going to bind the outside
loop onto the block indices
and finally the decomposed reduction had
to you know decompose original
reductions on
onto a a certain level okay so i'm going
to run this all together
and
this is a resulting program
actually one thing that we you can also
try to do is you can try to run
interactively so you will be able to
perform a few transformations and use
the ir module.show to see what is going
on in each of the steps
but let's first take a look at this
final program you can find that the
camera structure first of all
if you if you go and look at the final
output matrix you'll find that logically
we're trying to divide it into small
tiles that's why we're calling it
dividing tiles
where the outermost iterators correspond
to the block into this and then threat
indexes right and and finally the
innermost it is really corresponding to
the the register tile block in this case
v equals eight
um
and then
this final program you know first we
initialize the corresponding say local
regions
and then we are going to do a reduction
that go and you know runs the local
computation the aspect to say local
and finally uh this c local region gets
written back onto the global memory
uh through another loop
so when we compile this program
uh this local memory actually will turn
into
registers in a low level com no lab
computation because after we compact
them it's going to become an 8x8 region
that can be transformed onto registers
okay so one of the things we can go and
try out is we can go and try
build this particular program
and and here i'm trying to allocate the
input
data
and output placeholders and i'm going to
run what we call tummy evaluation to
evaluate
the runtimes on this
on this uh device
one of the common metrics that we use to
measure you know how fast
a program runs actually we can pro we
can print now you know the milliseconds
another way to to evaluate it is through
about what we call a flops matrix
and this flops matrix
matrix uh measures
uh how many floating point operations
we perform per second so the evaluator
will return the
the time
that's um
that
will return the term
that we take to run this particular
computations
and
this is a number of protein point
operations to perform this major
simplification there's a
scaling factor of two because you know
the multiplier add actually counts as
two floating point operations for most
of a convention so if we go and run this
you can find that you can get around two
teraflops of computation which is pretty
decent actually for our first attempt
uh when i started to try to write gpu
programs it will go and naively directly
go and map the stress without reduced
time like you are going to get a lower
number okay so now we have talked about
the basic technique let's come back to
another technique called shoot memory
blocking
so one of the things that we want to
notice is that originally if we look at
this
program
we only take um notice of these
multi-level threading techniques right
we're only trying to do optimizing
within a single thread on the other hand
there's another thing that would really
benefit uh in terms of gpu memory is we
want to be able to reuse
the common parts that we read from
different
um gpu threads within the same spread
block
so in here let's assume that each of the
tiny blocks here corresponds to
a gpu strap block uh gpu
threads
that within a sram block
and we have a l by l actually this 2l
can be different
threads within that gpu threadblock
so in this case in order to compute all
the results in this l by l output
we won't need to read in a bigger region
and you can find it as a commonly used
kind of example in this case in order to
read um
data for this block we can
go and get
the
input data from here and here and then
in order to read second block you can
find this you still need to read the
same region all right so we can try to
do is we can try to go and fetch this
true stripe of data
onto the gpu shared memory and then load
from there to be able to help us reduce
the memory pressure
and this is a technical cooperative
function
and the following transformation help us
to do that so it's slightly longer but
it looks quite similar to the original
key cell program the main difference
contains two parts the first part is
that we go and try to
fuse um these two threading decks
together and only bind to to one strand
this is just to simplify things so that
you know
you can either do two dimensional square
and that's one dimension it's index they
are usually equivalent if you feel soon
together effectively you are trying to
in the in the runtime and you will
decompose the
ones right index using module and
division onto the corresponding
two is
the second thing we're trying to do is
what we call cash reading cooperative
fashion so in this case the cash flow
incorporated fashion will try to go and
take a block like one point in this case
originally is a v2c and
b
if i'm going to do cash read on a i'm
going to introduce a stage called a
shirt
and insert in a bit trim
and
and remember that you know we still need
to specify for a shirt how we're going
to read that
so what we're going to do is we're going
to go and try to first of all find out
the loop
loops in the reading cache actually and
then we're going to fuse the two loops
together
and then we're going to split it by the
number of number of threads so that you
can spread it out over the thread in
this case the second iterator is being
bind as red x
and finally actually in this case also
vectorizing it so that
you know
this is another optimization that we can
do so when we are reading from
the output memory the global memory onto
gpu memories we can leverage possible
you know
loading several floating points together
if possible
um if this code is a bit more
complicated for you you know don't worry
too much try and play it with a bit you
know remember that every bit of
transformation you can will be able to
use ir module.show to see what are the
intermediate results and that might help
us to incrementally look at you know
what's going on but let's look at the
final results of this assured memory
blocking
and you can find that the main
difference in here is that we have
two additional stages
that
that help us to go and
bring in
data from uh a to a sure then b to b
sure
another thing they want to notice is
that you can find you know
this loading happens inside the
reduction right so so that as we do the
reduce we are going to go and read the
corresponding data onto those shared
memories
and
finally because we are fusing all the
threading this together so we can find
there are some modular individual
operations that try to redivide and
and get all get indices out okay
so for this particular program if we go
and view that
you'll find that actually will get much
better performance right this this
number is uh at least larger than our
previous level it may not be the best on
this particular gpu but now
as a manual attempt these two techniques
kind of covers a lot of the common
techniques that people use to optimize
optimize the tensile lining algebra
program more in gpu
so i've talked about how we can manually
write in the transformations on gpu
in the last few lectures we also talked
about how we can do automatic program
program transformation and in this case
we can go and do that
using the meta schedule api so
in this case we have specified our
original workload
and
and it will run a tuning on a background
it can take a while so i'm not going to
show the final result but you're more
than welcome to go and try out this
notebook and see you know what the final
results look like
usually because we are not selling a
setting a smaller number of trials so it
may just be as good as the original menu
version but it's a but you know
the takeaway is that it helps you to go
and find out um a possible optimized
kernel using the techniques that we
introduced uh just in the in the past
few steps
okay
okay so to summarize
today we started another axis of ml
series up until now we talk about you
know how do we take models on to from
machine learning frameworks onto an ir
module how do we go and transform them
and
but most of example so far only focuses
on the local cpus that we have on the
notebook
in this particular case
uh we we switched here to look at the
new hardware acceleration in this case
you know a gpu
and modern gpus are becoming more and
more complicated so you know be beside
the normal threat and shield memories
there are additional concepts like
cancer cause and specialized computing
unit that we're going to touch in the in
the incoming lectures
and uh
they are and you know depending on which
gpu environment where i use a machining
compilation processor can help us to
bridge that gap by bringing input input
models and try to target different gpu
program models and environments
we'll visit more highway specialization
topics in the future
and you know you're more than welcome to
check out this notebook and play with it
and thanks folks this is the
end of the part one and today's lecture
and i will see you folks next week for
the part two of gpu and power
acceleration