Okay. Um, we can get started. So, our
plan is we have I have the quiz here.
So, that's please remind me when is
about 250 or 3 then I can give it to
you. Then you can work on it. Then
whenever you're done, you can submit it.
Then you can leave. Okay, we'll do the
quiz at the end of this lecture. But uh
using the main part of this lecture,
let's keep talking about uh GPU
architecture and following the part that
we uh didn't complete the GPU
architecture too. I don't know if I can
finish in three lectures then if three
lectures is not enough to do the fourth
lecture. Okay. Uh let's give a review.
Last time we're talking about GPU
program, right? Starting from the
intrinsic conflict conflict.
So human consider everything um in zero
then but the hardware works in parallel
because there are so many combination
logic and those combination logic are
independent from each other. So they can
work on their own um and can get their
result without waiting for another
combination logic to complete.
So uh then talking about this we
consider different type of parallelisms.
Then we try to use the intrinsic
characters of our program to find the
methods that can paralyze the execution.
Then the easiest type of execution is
data level par data level parallelism is
the paralism that resides in data. So we
talk about embarrassing parallel that
are parallel patterns that each each
output each piece of output can be
calculated independently without waiting
for another piece of output.
This type of program is the most
suitable for GPUs and GPU can really
calculate this type of program really
quick because GPUs are originally
designed for renderings and in pixel in
rendering uh workload pixels and
vertices there are a lot of them then we
follow the same type of operations on
all on all those vertices and pixels.
So then uh we talk about we give this
example of a pthread program then we
also convert it to a kuda program. The
most important part are these two parts.
The first part is a simple example of u
first part is a simple example of u a a
a kernel and then and this program this
function is describing what is uh doing
in a thread. Then when we launch a
kernel in this way there are many many
threads being launched and we call it
when it's launched we call it a it forms
a grid because it can be two-dimensional
or threedimensional but here let's just
focus on one dimensional okay now we use
one-dimensional
we we launch a one-dimensional kernel we
need to tell two key factors one is a
block size one is number of blocks block
sizes are typically 32 64
128 8 all the way until 1024. The number
of blocks multiply by the block size is
the total number of threads that were
launching. Okay, with these two extra
parameters, sometimes you can have even
more extra extra parameters, but the
basic requirement is two uh the basic
requirement is is the two
parameters. Okay. So
um then each thread knows its indices by
calculating this from this expression
and the T is the global ID so that the
threads knows which piece of data it
needs to process.
So today in today's lecture we're going
down to hardware and see how this type
of program is executed in GPU hardware
and see why some key programming model
decisions like
uh threads within a kernel but from
different blocks cannot communicate with
each other. So like this type of
decision how can those type of decisions
how those type of decisions are made
because of the hardware limitation.
Let's first into look at into how a
program is compiled into assembly and we
start with a super simple program called
shifted hop copy. It's even simpler than
vector add. We only have a input
input array and the output array and we
shift everything by four element. Okay,
we shift everything by four element and
write it to the output element assuming
both input and output are large enough
and the number of uh the number of
threads are suitable. So we don't do the
condition check there. We'll see how we
can do condition check but let's start
from the simple example. Okay.
So this is the assembly. Then it's a
simplified assembly version. I don't
want to get you the tell you the key
point of how this assembly is for. Let's
explain a little by little.
So the first thing you see is
the opra right? So this part is called
the op code which is the instruction.
These part are called the oprints that
we're applying operant on this. We're
applying an action to this opt and we
have immediate numbers right zero two
that's okay those immediate numbers but
for registers we immediately see there
are two sub set of registers one starts
with s scalar
okay then the other set is a vector
scalar registers and vector registers so
what are scalar registers remember in
one work. So here everything every
instruction is executed in one work. So
when we execute say add operation there
are 64 threads actually performing this
add operation. Okay but this is a scalar
register and this is a scalar
instruction. For scalar register there's
only one s0. So all of them share the
same s0 value. The hardware physically
just a one piece of register and re
uh one register storing 32 bit of
information. So 32 def flip-flops
okay 32 bit of data. Now when we say s1
= 1 all the threads will see s1 equals
to one and when we perform a scalar
operation it's actually only one
instruction one operation is performed
and it's only adding 16 to s0 and
storing back to s0.
Okay. So all 64 threads are executing
the same operation. not not executing
the same operation but there's only one
operation is being executed if it's a
scalar instruction
and on the other side we see vector
instructions right so v let's see this
v2 here v2 can have different values
from thread to thread so when we do this
v add co is considering the carry uh is
is carry out is performing the carry out
operation the ADDC is carry is
considering the carry in. Okay. So add
carry out ADDC carry carry out. But just
ignore CO part. Just consider this add
operation. Then V V2 there are 16 V2
operations
right
not 16 there are 64 V2 values. Then this
instruction is repeated by 64 times and
64 different values are being added
together. So single issue single
instruction multi data. So for V
instructions they are vectorzed
instruction and the multiple
instructions multiple operation are
performed in this work.
Then another thing these are rather
straightforward to understand right
these are s0 s1 s2 s3 are combined
together it just require much wider data
type so these registers can be combined
together
so this is scalar registers vector
register for v1 we have different values
from thread to thread and there's no
easy way or at least in standard ways
there's no easy way that one thread can
add a value from another thread.
Okay. Now for scalar instruction we for
the whole word 64 thread there's
actually only one instruction and one
operation is performed. For vector
instruction 64 instructions is being
performed.
Okay then let's read this code a little
bit. The first thing we do is as load.
So if you're not familiar with
instruction load means we're loading
from memory from the memory to the
registers so that we can use it. So what
we're loading so this instruction is
we're loading from s45 with an offset of
zero and the result is stored in s0 and
s0 s1 s3 s2 s3. Okay. So what is
loading? So since we start with S45,
this S45 must be pre filled and it has
value at the beginning. So what value is
prefilled? It filled with the kernel
arguments.
Okay. So where the then the first thing
is the pointer is the address of this in
pointer and the second thing is the
address of this outpinter. So how wide
is a pointer?
How how many bits is a pointer?
Eight by right? 8 by 64 bit. So remember
S1 S0 is 32bit four byt and we need two
registers to store one address. That's
here we're loading these addresses both
in and out. Then S0 and one has in. S2
and three has out. Okay. Then we have
the pointers initial pointers.
Okay. Then
uh let's ignore this shift by a little
bit. Then let's look at this one.
As weight count. What is doing with as
weight count? as weight count is a
special instruction that is doing an
explicit
synchronization.
So, LGKM count local global constant
memory count. Okay. Um you don't need to
remember I just tell you this weight
count is to wait for the memory to
complete. So how AMD GPU execute this
instruction is it will execute this s
load instruction
immediately right or load the data then
it will take a very long time for the
data to come back what it will do is it
will just do some calculation because
there's no dependency we need v23 and
here we fill in as 03
right so there's no dependency between
these two instructions so why We're
waiting for the result for this to come.
We can just do this calculation.
But here S1 S0 were used in instructions
four and five. In this case, we have to
wait. We have to do a synchronization.
Then the design principle of GPU is to
design the hardware as simple as
possible. So in CPU you will see this
type of controlling or this type of
dependency resolution is done by
hardware. In GPU we want hardware to be
really simple just all the unit to be
used all the circuit to be used in
calculation.
Then we use software we used the
compiler to do this resolution. So we
inert one instruction. So this
instruction can only finish
when this data is there. So we wait
until this counter when this one is
issued is incremented by one. Then when
this result comes back it will decrease
by one right will decrease by one. Then
it will fall back to zero we will wait
until this counter becomes zero. Then
once is become zero we know we have the
data ready. Then we can start to do the
calculation.
Okay. So what here we're doing?
So add and add their scalar
instructions.
What we're doing is remember S0 and S1
is the
S0 and S1 is the input
pointer. Right? Now we add 16 to it. Why
add six? Why add 16
on this side is four, right?
Yeah, it's a offset. Then
remember this is floating point numbers.
Each floating point number is four byte.
So
here we have this pointer semantics that
is defined in C or C++ or CUDA.
By the way, I'm using a CUDA program and
but this is compiled with for from open
sale. So not very different.
Uh so we add 16 right
16 here and let's see what's in V2 and
V3.
So v_sub_2 and v_ub3 at this moment
v_sub_2 and v_sub3 should include the t
the
t that is shift the left by two that
means it's multiply by four now we add
v2 and v3 by s0 and v5 to v 0 and v1
it's more likely there's some
performance optimization here so that
move the s1 to v5 otherwise if we write
v s1 here is basically the same thing
okay so Don't don't worry too much about
this. But I can tell you at this stage
we w0 and wi 1 and w 0 and wi 1 contains
this address this exact address that we
want to fetch.
Okay. At this point at this point we
have the address that we want to read
from the memory that is pointed in this
in pointer.
Okay. Then we do a load global load. We
load from this address V 0 and one. We
already calculated it right now and we
store it into V4.
So V4 is our data. It's our input data.
Then see here we're doing something
similar. We copy three to V5 then
perform an add operation.
Okay. Now what does this part do?
It's calculating the address that where
we need to store the data.
Okay, this part the left the address of
the left part of the equation of the
expression.
Then see here the interesting thing the
most important thing that I want to
introduce is this address calculation
can happen in parallel while we're
loading the data.
Right? While the memory system is busy,
we want to keep the AOU to be also busy.
Then we have this weight count, VM
count. This is vector memory. So it's
another counter. So vector memory count
and because this is a global is reading
from the vector memory and it becomes
zero. Now our data is back. Now we
store. Store means we're writing from
the register space to the hot writing to
from the hot from the register registers
to the memory space from where from v4
right this contains the data then we
zero and one new v 0 and one contains
the address that we want to write to
okay then eventually we have a end
program
um it's just a special instruction
telling that's the handle this work. No,
it can exit. It can return.
Okay.
Question.
>> Okay. read.
>> Yeah, that's a good question. So that's
related to how weight count works. Then
uh one type of instruction,
one type of program we can do global
load
load into V1. Now another global
load into V2. Okay. Now we can then this
load can happen in parallel. So this one
can issue can just send to the memory
system. Then this one sent to memory
system without waiting for each other.
Now what we can do is we can wait
count that is I'm just writing there. I
don't want to write a counter. Okay. We
can wait for count then use
we one and we two.
Okay. Another way actually it's
you can have a finer granularity
control. It's type two say type two you
can do something then you can wait
for this counter to become one. When
this counter becomes one that means vi1
is ready but w2 is not necessarily
ready. Okay. Then we can use wi1
then we can wait
to z to zero. then we can use which okay
this is AMD assembly and media assembly
is probably simpler
then this is
something that is very in my opinion
very controversial why
it looks like this is a good
optimization right because we can use V1
without waiting for result so we can
improve the utilization of the ALUS to
do some real work.
But the problem is
it forces the V1 and W2 to return in
order.
We one and W2 to return in order. Since
we haven't talked about cache, it's
actually not that easy to guarantee it's
in order, right? Let's just say this is
a L1 cache and this is a memory.
just
think at least you should know basically
what is a cache, right? It's a faster
memory but it doesn't contains all the
data. What if W2 is here but W1 is here.
We want in the L1 cache. This is a heat.
It can almost immediate return. This one
takes a very long time to return. Right?
That means W2 is ready. We cannot use
V2. V2 is ready earlier and we have to
use V1 and out of order return is very
very common.
Auto order return is very common because
of this situation. So we have to reverse
the order. Then to guarantee that the
order is the same as we send the request
down. So what we need to do is to add a
reorder buffer. I call it Rob or RO O
reorder buffer. What does that mean?
It's basically a buffer to record say oh
we first requested v_sub_1 then we
requested v_sub_2 right so when vi1
return when v2 returns the data needs to
be stored here but cannot be responded
to the core and it has to wait that we
one returns then sent to the core and
think about how complex the hardware is
this because of this optimization right
so
achieving this is not easy.
There's a hardware cost. So does it say
worth effort? I don't know. And I don't
see
lots of program is actually using this
method from like um about
15 programs that I evaluated deeply only
see one or two uses this optimization
method.
Okay. Most of them will just do load a
bunch of data and start use it just
without doing this ordering.
Thanks for the question
and you you don't know how how much time
how many hours I spent just to implement
this feature in the simulator to recover
order that even some AMD official
simulators that in AMD research they do
not support this feature.
question
uh on a GPU. What is this input?
Um okay, so this is assembly code,
right? But your computer cannot really
consume this assembly code. So there's a
a matching binary zero and ones. So some
way to encode this instruction. This
instruction is probably 8 byt to encode
this instruction. Then your your the
core will load this instruction will
load a bite of data and to decode it and
to see oh this is a a load instruction
then we'll execute this instruction.
Yes.
Yeah.
We'll talk about that later. Okay. How
this maps to hardware.
Okay.
Okay. Let's talk about thread
divergence. Thread divergence is how we
consider how we execute loops and if
conditions. Remember last time we talked
about the verbs execute in lock step.
That means if we long is if we issue one
instruction we need to execute 64
threads. Repeat the operation by 64
threads. What if there's a if condition
there
right? If there's a if condition just
assuming say there are only 16 threads
needs to be excluded or we can manage
that.
Then let's look at this new assembly.
Okay, it's basically the same as before,
but there are some extra things.
So here,
let's first look at this one.
Okay,
V45
V4 is storing
in GD
the value of in G. Okay, also we change
it to double. Previously it was float.
This time it's double. So we need v45 to
store. We need v45 to store uh the the
in the input value in g. Now we need to
check if it's greater than zero or not.
Here what is actually comparing is less
than. I don't know if this uh
exact match of this program or this uh
or this assembly I say probably less eco
is a better one but it's okay. So here
we do the comparison right what do we
now we do this comparison the next we
run this save execute instruction and
this is a little bit complex but
basically we're saving this thing called
VCC so this is a comparison result
comparison so VCC is a 64bit register
and if this condition holds that that
thread then that bit will set to one if
it doesn't hold that will set zero.
Okay. So here now then now we do a
execution mask check. Then this is exec
that means check if the execution mask
is zero or not. So what is execution
mask? Execution mask works in this way.
So it's a execution mask is also a 64bit
um register 8 byt register. If the
corresponding bit is one then we say oh
this thread will take effect.
If the thread execution mask is zero
then this thread will not execute this
instruction and the result will not be
stored back to a register and the result
will not take effect.
Okay. So just be careful if it's zero we
still need a time to execute this
instruction.
It's just that the result is not writing
back and it's not taking effect.
Okay.
So, so we say execution mask is a
predicate. Predicate is a term in
computer architecture that is using a
bit to determine if this instruction to
be executed or not to execute.
Sometimes also called this is predicated
execution.
Then it's a one bit determin takes
effect or not. So when so let's let's
just look at this part
these are few instructions are
controlled by the execution mask right
if they are
um if that thread has a one then this
few instruction will take effect and the
result will store back otherwise the
result will not store back right it's
controlled by that uh if condition
here there's a comparison there's a
comparison to check if excusion
mask is all zero if it's all zero that
means we don't need to execute this part
at all
right we can just directly jump to the
outside we can jump back to the BP2
basic block zero basic block two
okay what is a basic block since we talk
about the BB basic block is a group of
instructions that if one instruction is
executed all other instructions are all
executed.
Okay. So let's see what's the first BB
basic block. Basic block starting from
here from the first instruction.
Basic block starting from the first
instruction same basic block. Same basic
block same basic block same same until
here. Okay, because if you consider
the first few lines
that's BB0 basic block zero from 1 2 3 4
5 6 7 8 9 10 10 or 11 right from 1 to 11
is BB0 then we have that branch so any
one of the instruction executed in this
basic block this whole basic block must
execute and there's no branch There's no
branching out. So your program always
execute in order. Then it can have two
choices. It can either go to BB1
or BB2,
right? BB02. Just see just read as BB2.
Okay. Then BB BB1 has
12 13 14 15. Right?
These four instructions. Now BB2 has
16 17
this instructions and BB1 can go to BB2
and can fall through and it always go to
BB2.
Okay. So this is how these type of
branching programs are executed.
So we call this this effect the exec
using execution mod to handle either a
loop loop is handled in similar way
which is more complex then or handle
this if conditions we call it thread
divergence what's thread divergence is
the threads within a warp maybe need to
execute different basic blocks or
different branches of if condition
that's called thread divergence.
Whenever there's a thread divergence
that means the number of effective
threads is not full. So your whole warp
is not being fully utilized
then that reduces the effective
computing capability. So what's going on
here is let's do some calculation.
Consider
okay in Nvidia each warp is 32 thread.
So if there are 16 thread are active
then the maximum utilization is 50%.
Right? The other 50% are wasted
question.
Yeah they are still executing in log
stop.
They say come here this this part is not
there right or this still here they say
if all these 32 thread are executing
this instruction they're still all
executing this instruction but maybe
only the first 16 are being applied the
result are being applied that's how it
works in lock step the other 16 thread
will not take effect then that means as
if there they didn't execute but they
still wasted resources. They still take
time. Okay. Now, if just assume if you
have a if else case,
just assume if you have a if else case
if I'm just writing if n smaller than 16
then else. Okay.
Then what happens is we'll execute this
condition. Then it will execute these a
few instructions.
Then we execute these instructions.
So all the threads will execute all
instructions. But only at the at this
part we have
uh 000000
F FF.
Yeah. Let's start with FF FF. Okay. And
starting from here we have 0000 f F F F
F F F F F F F F F F F F F F F F FFF FF
until this point. Whenever we encounter
an else
just imagine there's a else instruction
there we just flip it.
Okay. Then we use this to keep in
executing.
Then let me allow me to write an end end
of this end if. Okay. Now we just
convert it back to f F F F F F F F F F F
F F F F F F F F F F F F F F F F F F F F
F F F F F F F F F F F.
Okay, now we keep executing with all
these apps.
Is that clear how this exclusion mask
maps with lock step exclusion?
Okay, so just one one more sentence here
is going a little bit deeper. If there's
another nested if just imagine that's a
stack, right? So there's original
execution mask. Then we go there then
it's a not even nested say 0000 f 0 0
ff. Then when that finish when that else
finishes it's like popping the original
state out. Right? When this one finishes
it's just popping the original um
execution master state out.
Okay,
hope this is not
uh too hard to understand.
Okay, the word size consideration.
So AMD uses 64 thread works and Nvidia
uses 32. So which one is better? It's
really hard to say. They have both have
good cases and bad cases. So what larger
warp size when the ex when the case is
very ideal when the program is very
regular when the thread divergence is
low then in theory if we I issue one
instruction we can execute 64 times. So
overhead is lower. So for regular
programs AMD is more efficient in this
sense, right? But for irregular
applications where there are a lot of
thread divergence or a program is uh the
the the weight of work is smaller that
means the wasted threads are fewer then
in this case Nvidia is more flexible and
more efficient in irregular programs.
Okay.
Then starting from here we're done with
the software part. Then let's see how
the soft piece of software maps to
hardware GPU architecture. Starting from
CPU and GPU. Then CPU and GPU are
connected with PCIe networks. Then of
course you can connect with something
like link but it's a network that can
send data. Okay. Then CPU sends commands
to the GPUs. These commands in uh mainly
are memory copy command and kernel
launching command but it can be rather
complex the commands that send from CPU
GPU you can even just modify some
register some global control registers
those are not the key part and let's
look at what's happening in a GPU then
the GPU the front end of a GPU at the
beginning it has something called a
command processor a command processor or
CP P
it's a CPU within the GPU. It has its
own instruction set and can execute some
commands. It has its own caches
memory memory region and just can do
lots of things on its own. But the main
goal is to accept the command from the
CPU communicate with the CPU and
controls or coordinates internal
resources. Okay, this is a controller.
It's not down into the instruction
level. This is more like what type of
command level. Now we'll see there are
many many different many layers that go
down uh this controlling process down to
instructions.
Okay. So let's start from the simpler
side. The memory copy part. The memory
copy part is the direct has the direct
are called the memory direct memory
access engine DMA engine. Okay. A DMA
engine can directly communicate with the
CPU memory and can perform the memory
copy. Now why there are two DMA engines
is because they can say if there are two
memory copy task one is to read the data
one is to write the data they can happen
in parallel. Okay. So for most of GPUs
at least a little older GPUs and there
are always two DMA engines. I don't see
any other any exceptions all of them
have two DMA engines.
Okay. So that's the simple part. Let's
go with the harder part. Uh kernel
execution. Now asynchronous computer
engine. Asynchronous computer engine
orchestrates kernel execution. Okay. So
when it receives a command say oh
execute this kernel then the CPU will
assign uh AC say please execute this
kernel. The AC will start to execution.
Then when it's done the AC will tell CP
oh this is done. you can tell the CPU
this is done. Um actually if I want to
talk a one step deeper the CPU when sent
to the GPU command it doesn't work in a
way that say oh I send one command when
that one is completed I send another one
this round trip is actually taking a lot
of time to avoid this round trip it
actually has a command Q command Q is
just part of GPU memory and CPU send a
command to a GPU to GPU by writing a
piece of memory into the GPU piece of
data into a GPU memory
And then it will write another one piece
one element one command another command
another command that serves as a command
Q then the GPU can execute this command
Q on its own. Okay. So there are a
little bit in asynchronous communication
between the CPU and GPU.
Now let's go with asynchronous computer
engine. Then uh in GPUs there can be
multiple asynchronous comput engines.
High end may have six to eight of them.
That means in theory they can execute
multiple kernels, multiple uh GPU
programs at the same time. And exactly
how they are interled, how they share
resources, it depends on the hardware
and depends on the uh driver.
So we're not talk really talking about
uh concurrent kernel execution. Then we
go down directly down to the CU part,
the compute unit.
Comput unit is the core of the GPU.
Okay. is where instructions are
executed.
Then in a media is called streaming
multiprocessors SM or SMX. But here in
today's lecture I'm just in architecture
part I'm focusing on AMD terminology but
I will tell you which one maps to which
one. Okay. AMD called CU computer unit
called SM streaming multiprocessor.
There are GPU cores. They have registers
and they handle instructor execution. So
CUS are the unit where those instruction
are being consumed and being executed.
Okay. But we'll go into even deeper
level and how what happens within the C.
But that's first
then okay it show blocks.
Okay.
The CU count the number of CUS.
Typically a GPU may have a large number
of CUS com unit. So like a multi-core
CPU but uh a high-end range high-end GPU
may have at least a 64. Earlier days it
was like when when earlier days when AMD
was using 28 nanometer technology
uh 64 CUS are their high-end product.
When they're going down 7 nanometer 5
nanometer like 120 this range are their
main strength. Okay. When they go
multi-chip multi chiplet design or
multi-chip module they go with 220 and
they can significant increase. Okay.
Then the number of computer decides the
performance. Some even some mobile GPUs
like Samsung CPU Samsung uh phones have
AMD GPUs and then some GPUs may only
have two CUS four CUS. That's the mobile
device.
Okay, then we're talking about block
dispatching. We're finish this part and
then we'll go with the quiz.
Then remember the AC is responsible for
dispatching a kernel and orchestrating
the kernel execution. So the CP will
tell AC or you execute this kernel and
tell me when it's done. So the AC has a
kernel and has a bunch of CUS that can
actually execute part of the kernel. So
what ACE what the AC does here is it
will break down this kernel and forms
the grid. Okay to understand what's
inside what's the dimension of this
kernel. So it will break down into block
and work level. They say just a simple
case this block this kernel has five
blocks.
Now what's happening is it will just
dispatch these blocks to cus and to send
tasks. Say you execute this block, you
execute that block. Okay.
So what's the limitation of number
blocks in a kernel?
Sorry this is this is a efficient
question there's no limitation you can
have any number you want okay any number
of threads and any number of block then
there's any number of block right so if
there's any number of blocks
that means
the the thread
can execute a block on the CU and one CU
can execute multiple blocks but even if
can execute multiple blocks there must
be a limitation because it has resources
limitation right so what's happening
here or Y thread from different blocks
cannot communicate and synchronize is
that if we have 120 CUS and let's say
each CU can exclude 10 blocks at a time
that means we can execute 1,200
blocks
at a time, right? So, we execute this
1,200
blocks simultaneously. When they're
done, they're retired. And then we
dispatch another batch of 1200 blocks.
That means these blocks, so thread from
one block and thread from another block
may never exclude at the same time.
Okay?
they never they may never execute at the
same time that means they cannot
communicate and they cannot synchronize.
Okay, let me say again if there we have
a large number of blocks millions
billions of blocks but the number of CUS
are limited and the number of blocks
that can be handled by the CU is also
limited. So because of this reason we
have to execute in batches. Retire a
batch then dispatch another batch. That
means the block may not be even execute
at the same time. If they're not
executed at the same time they cannot
wait because you don't know which one it
will execute earlier, which one will
execute later. The order is all depends
on hardware and the driver. Okay. So
when control is controls it. It's not
part of the program. So the vendor may
optimize it. So suddenly one day the
order the vendor decide we're executing
from the backward to the front to the to
the beginning. That's totally okay.
Okay. Then actually there's a another
implicit condition that decides this.
Remember in CPU we have a contact we
have a term called context switching.
What is context switching? That means
when we're executing one thread, for
some reason there's some triggers that
we say, "Oh, we need to switch to
another thread." What we'll do is we'll
store the register states back to the
GPU side.
We'll store this register state to the
memory. Okay, sorry about my
my wording. Then we store this state
back to the memory. Then we bring some
other contacts from the memory to the
core. Then we execute that thread. But
remember GPU are decided to be really
simple. We don't want to waste the
circuit on this control logic. And on
another thing is because of the
vectorzed register. If we store a warp
or a block to the memory, there are a
lot of data to be written. So way one
right one is actually 64 multiply by 4
256 bytes of data right and the GPU have
many many more register it can have v
128 12 v 127 they can have so many
registers storing the whole context and
bringing another context is actually a
waste of resources
okay it will take a very long time for
context switching so GPU doesn't want to
do it then GPU will take away. So we
never do context switching. We execute
block
until they finish. Okay, this is a
design philosophy. So there's some there
you can see papers and when they do
research papers they always say oh we
need to consider programmer may program
in this way and that programmer may
program in that program in that way.
Then we may design hardware to
accommodate the programmer's
requirement. Then GPU design is say no
we don't want to do that this is the
best way that you can achieve the best
performance then you just don't write
the code in that way never write in that
way if you write that way I refuse to
serve you okay but what I can guarantee
is I have the highest performance okay
it's not flexible there are many things
I can do now do with a CPU without GPU
the only thing GPU only thing only good
thing about GPU is it's fast high
throughput
Okay,
this will be a quiz question. Okay. Why
cannot why blocks cannot
communicate and synchronize
then
block dispatching we can finish this
part block dispatching constraints. So
the capacity of a CU for block handling.
What are the limiting factors for the CU
in term of handling blocks? Why cannot
handle more blocks? What's are the
resources limitation
then starting from from the first thing
we call this thing we call the first
thing or warp
slots
wayfront is AMD terminology warp is
another is a media terminology they're
the same thing okay sometimes AMD
internally they also just simply call it
wave
okay and later on there's another term
called lane it's it's very interesting
Just consider a swimming pool.
There are lanes, right?
And this is a wavefront. The wave front
goes that way. Okay, a lanes are thread
are thread within a wavefront. So they
the wavefront always go this way but
there are multiple threads. Each thread
is a line. Okay, just MD terminology.
Then
what is a wave front slot? It's
basically a group of register and
resources that needs to record the state
of a wavefront execution. For example,
we have a PC program counter. Program
counter is a pointer that pointing to
the next instruction to be executed.
Execution mask, VCC, right? We have seen
those. There are many many other
registers. instruction buffer the
instructions to be executed. There are a
lot of resources need to handle the
state the execution state of a web of a
wave front. They say in AMD GPUs in each
CU there are four
group of wave front slots and each group
is um typically 10 slot now but I have
also seen eight in some lowerend GPUs.
Okay, remember scalar registers. So
different programs may require different
number of scalar registers. They start
from scalar zero then they go four or
five then they keep going right. So
this their scalar register are more like
maloc are dynamically allocated. So what
this war may take this part of scalar
register that word may take another part
of reg scalar register. If there's no
more scalar register space then no the
the warp cannot the block cannot be
executed.
Vector register. Okay we have vector
registers but we have uh thread one has
a group of registers. Thread two has a
group of registers right and they're
allocated in a way that
they're the same. Right? For every
thread they have the same type of
allocation but we need to allocate some
spaces. If there's no space then we
cannot allocate more uh blocks
just for the purpose of completion.
There's another resources called shared
memory. The shared memory is a part of a
memory. It's addressable memory um
within a CU. It's a it's a super fast
but you can the programmer can control
it's actually like very similar to L1
cache. It's as fast as L1 cache but it's
addressable right or you can call it
programmer controllable programmer aware
L1 caches for L1 cache L2 caches
typically they're program transparent or
directly loading from the memory but for
shared memory programmers have control
of what is stored in the memory. We'll
not talk about shared memory in this
course. It's a little bit more advanced.
So four conditions that determines if a
word or if a block can be issued to the
computer unit.
So which one are the most the most
scarce resources? Which one is most more
likely to be for?
Take some guess.
Yeah.
>> Yeah.
Yeah. Shared memory. So when a program
uses a shares shared memory then yes
shared memory can be a limiting factor.
Then definitely AMD hardware engineers
they try to consider balanced cases.
They want to say oh all the programs
have a reasonable performance
but
uh just consider this case for a like
for a program that is written by a
beginner or from a program written by an
expert which one they care more they
probably care more about the program
written by expert right so in that if a
typically if program written by
beginners wro slots are the most scarce
resources because there are many many
threats, right? But if you're
veteran programmer, the vector registers
are the scarcest res uh resource. And
actually uh for very high-end like
something like Kublas u this type of
vendor provided library that they
deliver extreme performance, they have a
big team just to optimize those a few
kernels. They just want to take full
control of the hardware. What they do is
each block only have one word and this
warp even not using all the registers
will just simply claim all the registers
to prevent another another warp another
block being occupied competing for
resources. Then they will use software
to take care of everything. Okay, in
that case vector register is the most
scarce resources.
Okay. Then for dispatching, let's review
the dispatching process. Then from for
the AC, the AC will first find the next
available next block. No guarantee
ordering to find the next block to
dispatch and find the available CU that
has extra resources that can handle this
block. Um actually AC has
resource mapping um that's shared by
these ACEs so that they don't need to
send a re They don't need to send a
request a message to the CU to say can
you handle this block or not. The AC
knows that the resource utilization at
each computer unit. Then find the
available CU send the warps to the CU's
initialized register. Remember we say
register are being initialized prefilled
and this is part of the dispatching
process set to ready state. The warp is
ready to be executed. Now we have
instruction running there.
Okay. Now one thing is dispatching takes
time. If your program is super short,
your warp is super short, retires pretty
quick, then consider if you have
hundreds of hundreds of CUS, then
dispatching can take time. It will take
a few times in this CU to dispatch one
block, a few times to in each CU. Then
each CU may also even take like 10
blocks, right? It may take 10 blocks. So
it may spend
40 50 cycles here. If there are 100
that's 40k
sorry if there are 100 there about 4,000
instruction 4,000 cycles right. So if
your warp some really short warps can
execute really short in a really short
time um a few hundred cycles 100,000
cycles in that case the basic the
dispatcher can be the global bottleneck
it's not dispatching fast enough
okay and another thing just to be
careful here I want to introduce one
terminology that's not in my slide is um
occupation
So let's say each CU can handle 40 wave
fronts.
Okay. Then how many wave fronts you can
fill in.
If your eventually is blocked by vector
register then if you can only send 10
wave fronts there then we say the
occupancy is 25%.
Typically occupancy is the larger the
better because you have many new thread
other threads waiting there to be
executed. But sometimes occupancy can be
a even a bad thing. But occupancy is a
common term
that engineer a performance engineer
will look at to consider.
Let's say if the occupancy is low,
should we increase it to improve the
performance?