Okay, let's get started. So, today we're
going to talk about virtual addressing.
So, this will be the last lecture for
the memory system part, the memory
system module. So, that means if we're
done with this module, we're going to
have a
quiz next Thursday. Okay?
So, 1 week from now. So, it will include
the cache
the first cache lecture, which talks
about
uh
set, ways,
tags, index, this type of things. Then
the second lecture we talked about the
MSHR and the writing policy. Then the
lecture after that uh it was cache
coherency protocol.
Then today we're going to talk about
virtual addressing. So, these four
lectures' content will um go into the
next uh quiz. Okay?
Uh so, let's talk about virtual
addressing. Then I guess most of you
know that
all current systems work with two
different set of address systems. One is
called the virtual addresses, one is
called physical addresses. Then this
didn't start from the very beginning.
Then in earlier times, now we don't
really have uh virtual addressing. We
only have one set of uh address system.
That even
like like the first supercomputer Atlas
that introduced this type of virtual
addressing system in 19 uh '63, but even
something like
uh Windows 19 Windows 195 1995 was still
using some sort of physical addressing
system. So, that's why by that time, if
you have a 4 GB of memory, then by that
time people do not usually have this
large memory. Now, if you really have a
system that is larger than 4 GB of
memory,
the operating system cannot support.
Okay? So, what problem that uh motivate
people to use virtual addressing by that
time? It's mainly start with this
problem that the memory is not enough.
Now, we have a limited size of memory.
But, the whole program that may need a
larger memory than the physical memory
that we have on the computer. So, the
whole program needs to fit in the memory
um if the
program requires more memory than the
physical memory we have, the program
cannot execute. Right? So, the solution
is definitely in this case we
want the program to run in some way with
slower performance, but we still want
the program program to run. So, the
solution is to store part of the memory
to the disk, right? Now, how we can put
part of the memory to disk? Then
you know, in computer science, anything
can be solved by adding one extra layer
of indirection. Then virtual memory is
probably one of the best or one of the
worst the type of uh
indirection added in the whole
computing
system history.
So, it's
so fundamentally change so many things.
It's just one simple design that can
um it's so it's just one simple design
that solved so many problem, but it's
also one design that introduced a lot of
performance overhead that we really need
a lot of future patches to help
addressing this problem to
avoid the performance impact of virtual
addressing uh uh virtual to physical
address translation process. But, let's
see what problem that virtual address
solves.
So, uh
you know,
the virtual addresses are a set of
addresses that can be seen by the
program. Then
is the the address used by the address
used by the hardware is not the address.
Or at least the when the address used by
the memory part, right? The when the
address used by the DRAM, they should
have to have a physical address. That is
the address within the DRAM part. So, we
want to decouple this part of these two
addresses, the address used by the
hardware and the address used by the
program. We want to decouple them, we
introduce these virtual addresses. So,
it solves several problems. For example,
memory isolation. So, let's say both
like multiple programs may want to use
the address
uh
4096,
right? This address. Then if all the
program use want to use this
addresses, then it's actually very
convenient because you can always assume
that they say our program starts with
address 94 4096, right? Then starting
from this point is our programs. Now, or
like the
um the text section within our program
starts at some other addresses. Then or
um then then grows to our heap
stack region. Now, on the top is the
heap region, right? So, the heap region
always start with another address. And
the top of our stack is another address.
So, these addresses can be fixed
throughout
throughout all the programs within your
system.
Uh in that case,
two processes then must use one
the same address.
Then but we don't want them to access
the same part of the memory.
Right? If they want to read part of the
memory, that's a really serious security
problem. Now, we don't want two programs
to communicate with each other without
um
authentication. Now, in this way we
supported memory isolation. So, I don't
know if you have
used um
some early programs that when you play a
game, then when you want to cheat, when
you want to hack the game, there's
another program that is
just can
change the data of the another program.
Then but when when I was like when I was
in elementary school, I play computer
games. So, what I do is
I first produce two like very powerful
soldiers or something. Then I split them
into I I then I use the other the
modifier program to search for number
two, integer number two in the whole
program.
Then I split this into one and one. Then
I search again by filtering what I have
already searched. I search for one. Now,
I immediately identify the memory
location that is
originally two, then one. And I change
to 2000 or something. They change to
another
another number. And that is definitely
one example of the memory is not
properly isolated because you can access
the data
from one process of to another process.
Then by that time, it was not that
important, but today it this is called
uh sup- this is
uh
security problem. So, there's a specific
term that describe this type of problem.
This is called a covert channel.
What is a covert channel? A covert
channel is a
covert channel. A covert channel is
something that is
typically used in the security domain.
Let's say you have one way that you can
pass some information
from one
um from one process to another process.
Okay? So, um there's some covert
covert channel that is really easy to
exploit if you're you do not have
virtual addresses. Now, you can directly
access the address. Now, even like some
modern
programs, they try to do something like
uh they change
if if if one program program A, let's
say your Chrome Chrome browser, while we
are typing password, then your Chrome is
hacked by someone. Then you the hacker
will do something like change the
temperature of your CPU by running some
programs. Now, if you can change the
temperature of the program, and the
temperature can be read by another
program.
Right? Because they share the
temperature, all of them can read the
temperature of the CPU. And that's some
sort of covert channel that you can pass
information from one process to another
process. Okay? That's a type of security
risk. They can change something like
they can
sending a lot of requests to the caches.
Then so, reading the data is getting
slower than using this type of like if
the reading the data is faster or slow
to pass some information from one
process to another process. Those are
all hard to exploit covert channels
today.
Then that's definitely something that we
don't want to just consider. If you have
a Chrome browser, you never want your
password to be read by another program.
So,
uh then
other than memory isolation, the problem
solves other problems. One problem is we
can have unified addresses for all
programs. Now, memory access
uh all the
authorization that we have to explicitly
say this part of a memory can be shared
by these two programs, then these two
programs can both read or write into
these addresses.
Then uh do I have other things? No,
like other problems like virtual memory.
Then virtual addressing and virtual
memory are two different things. Virtual
memory are
kind of Windows terms. That means you
can store part of your memory into your
hard drive when you are using too much
memory. Right? So, you can have a
dedicated file that's several GB size.
Then when your memory overflows, it can
be stored into the hard drive. Now, in
that case, that you
you can try to access this a virtual
address.
Then when you're doing the translation,
you realize your or your system realize,
okay, this page this part of our is not
in the currently in the memory, it's
somewhere in hard drive. Then it swaps
in and swaps something out so that they
perform this type of operation. That's
why when you have Okay, very high memory
pressure that when you using a lot of
more memory than your physical memory
limitation, your computer will still
run.
While your computer is still run
um
you may see performance issues. That
That's because your the pages are keep
swapping in and swapping out from the
hard drive. Accessing hard drive is
definitely much slower accessing the
memory. And those are all the problems
that
um
the
virtual addressing can solve.
So, virtual addressing is typically done
in this process. Then there's a a
virtual address translator. It can s-
stay somewhere in your memory hierarchy.
It can be part of the core, can be part
of the memory, or can be part of every
cache, or can be an independent
component. So, this is only a logical
component.
Then on top of it, we use virtual
addresses. Then at some point, we
translate it into physical addresses.
Then when we access the memory, we
always use want to use physical
addresses.
Okay. So, uh if we talk about virtual
addressing, then we have to talk about
pages. So, because we don't want to have
page
we don't want to have byte by byte level
translation. That's very annoying. So,
we want to have some granularity so that
we translate once, then we actually know
a region of memory. Then there's a
trade-off between the sizes.
Okay. So, let's consider if we use a
smaller size and use this a larger size,
what's the advantage and the
disadvantages?
Let's say
s- larger size
and the larger page sizes
um
the larger page the larger the page
size, then definitely it's easier to
translate, right? The fewer chances we
translate because if we translate once,
we actually automatically translated the
whole every byte within this page.
Right? Then the but the disadvantage of
a large page a large page is
your memory is probably more likely to
get fragmented. Then if you want to
migrate the page from one device to
another device, let's say if you have
two CPUs, then sometimes there's
affinity that this part of memory is
responsible this CPU, this part of
memory is responsible for the other CPU.
Then
sometimes you really need to do this
page migration. Then you move one page
4 kilobyte of data from one CPU to
another CPU. Or sometimes you want to
store it back to the hard drive. Then
that 4 kilobyte is the unit that you
store into the hard drive.
So
if you want to access that part of data,
then while you have say 2 megabytes of
pages, you really have to load the whole
2 megabytes to the memory.
Then you can access a single byte from
there.
Okay. So, the memory movement cost is
much higher, and the latency is much
higher if you have a larger page sizes.
Okay. So, why people choose the 4
kilobytes at the beginning?
Or why 4 kilobyte is the most common
page sizes?
It's determined by the hard drive.
Um
the hard drive structure. Then the unit
of reading and writing a hard drive unit
is 4 kilobyte.
Okay. So, every time we read or write a
hard drive, we read 4 kilobyte of data,
then we load into memory.
So, that's why it's
a 4 kilobyte
unit used as page sizes. But then later
on, as we access more data or CPU and
GPUs get more faster and faster
this 4 kilobyte cannot really fulfill
the requirement.
Now, because translation is becoming a
more and more performance bottleneck
of the current system. So, we want to
reduce the times that we translate
addresses. So, today
uh
CPUs and GPUs are more likely to support
a larger page sizes. Now, I know for
Nvidia GPUs, the maximum page size that
we can support is
2 megabytes. Okay, I'm saying 2
megabytes is not a random number. Then 2
megabytes is the other extreme.
Then
but it definitely will cause some
problems. So, people typically use
somewhere in between like 16 kilobytes
or 32 kilobytes or 128 kilobytes as a
midground for the page sizes that we
want to use today.
Okay. Then uh
another thing that to I didn't show here
is
process.
What is a process?
So, there's a few terms
that you may heard.
Process
thread
and context.
What are the relationship between these
three
terms?
I'm checking here. I'm trying to see
what they use. They use thread.
The process name and thread.
Right? You see both terms here.
What are them?
What's the difference between these two?
Hm?
Yeah, process contains threads, right?
So, put it down.
Now, what is context?
So, context is more used in the term of
context swapping. That means that CPU is
executing which thread.
Um so, for most of the time, you can
consider context equals thread
for most of the operating systems,
although they may have in some operating
system, they can be different.
Um
so, it they just more likely to be used
in different
um environment, in different context.
Okay, the different
language context.
So, then we can get rid of context.
Now, what's the difference between a
process and thread?
So
should you when you write a program,
should you start a process or should you
start a thread?
Let's say for Chrome browser, if you
start a tab
right? You should start a tab. Should
the tab reside in new process or the
should it be reside in a new
thread?
All right, you can see here there are
some say
there's a Chrome helper, right? There's
probably Chrome Google Chrome Google
Chrome helper Google Chrome helper.
So, Chrome
uses multiple
process.
Right?
Yeah.
Yeah, you should use process. Then why
they use different processes?
If even if you don't have multiple
processes, you can have a lot of
threads. Then you can always group say,
"Oh, this group of threads belongs to
this type. This group of threads belongs
to this type." Right?
So
Okay. So, here remember one thing.
Process is a term related to virtual
address spacing spaces.
Okay.
So, that means
thread within a process
shares the same group of virtual
addressing to physical addressing
translation.
Okay.
So
Uh need a breaker.
Let's say
if I have two threads
P1
T1 and P1 T2
Okay, process one T thread one, process
one thread two.
Then it's address 01000
and
here 1000.
Okay, virtual address.
Then another case is
P1
T1 and P2 T1
virtual address
0x1000
0x1000.
In this case, are these mapping to the
same physical address?
In this case, are they mapping to the
Okay, the quick answer is this is not
and this is.
Okay.
So, probably have written a
multi-threaded program and using
something like Pthread or something,
right?
Then if you use something like Go, it's
probably easier to
create a thread.
In this case
the this address is the same as this
address.
That means communication can be easily
achieved by shared memory. So, they can
read and write one part of memory. Then
you need to consider race conditions,
data races. You need to consider like
you should avoid say one side is writing
and one side is reading, then you may
read some garbage data.
In this case,
unless you use some really advanced some
like IPC method inter-process
communication method.
For most of time,
this and this are mapping to different
addresses.
So, their their memory regions are
naturally
separated.
So, there's no easy way that you can
access data from this thread
to this thread because they belongs to
two different processes. Now, even if
you access the same address, they're
mapping to different hard
hardware address physical addresses. So,
you're accessing different part of the
data.
Okay? So, let's say
if I say again,
processes different process have natural
memory isolation.
Threads have natural memory sharing.
Okay.
So, come back to the question, should
Chrome use different processes?
Then the quick answer is yes. Now,
because if you want to type password in
one tab, you don't want
the other
tab running some random program or even
high high key programs.
There's there should be no way to access
the memory address that you're the
about the
password that you're typing.
Okay? So, let's talk about how memory
allocation works. Then, if you start
from Python world, then you don't need
to allocate addresses. But if you comes
from a C or C++ world, then you need to
consider how memories are allocated.
Okay? So, then typically we call malloc,
right? In C where you use the new
keyword in C++ but eventually it goes to
the same process.
Then you use a new keyword or malloc,
you're actually doing a function call
into the STD lib, the standard library
provided by the C program or the
operating system.
Then, so
then this is a runtime. This is a user
space runtime. It's not the operating
system yet.
So, it maintains a memory pool that
contains some data. Then, even this
memory pool, because it works in the
user space,
right? When user space is maps is
on the other side of
privileged space.
The the operating system runs in the
privileged space. Your program runs in
the user space.
Then, your user space will always have
virtual address. There's no way that a
user program at the user space can know
anything about a physical address. So,
then the STD library runs at the user
space, then it
maintains virtual addresses.
Okay? So, it can maintain a memory pool,
a few pages, for example.
When this
user space
when this STD lib runs out of its own
memory pool, it will do a mmap, memory
map
system call.
Now, in this system call,
and we go it's like calling a function
to the operating system. The operating
system maintains the virtual address and
physical address. Operating system have
access to the page tables. We'll talk
about page table later.
So,
then the memory allocation is basically
allocating two different addresses.
For the virtual address, we consider
it's basically it's unlimited, right?
It's only bounded by the number of bits
that you have in your address. So, we
allocate a 4K range. So, it either go
from this side to this side. Now, if you
know like stack stack go from one
direction, then heap goes from the other
direction, right? So, when we allocate
one page, then on the other side on the
physical space, we should also allocate
a space.
And
you need to know this space, the
physical address space is shared by
multiple processes. So, this page may
belongs to another process. This page
may belongs to another process. They all
belongs to different processes.
So, here, now we allocate a physical
page.
It's also 4 kilobyte size. Now, we need
to
connect them together. Now, how we can
connect them together? Now, basically,
we insert one entry into the page table.
Now, what's inside a page table?
The page table includes a PID, which is
a process ID. Now, just record which
process it is.
Right? It's typically 2 byte long or
sometimes 4 byte long as a integer.
It will have some flags. Flags is
responsible for
uh say what this page is about. Then, is
it a about instructions?
Then, if it's instructions, we should
have the flag for execution. Then we
should allow execution. It's just a flag
that allows us to do some basic memory
protection. You should never easily
execute something in the data region,
right? Just because you don't want
someone to enter some program, then
execute the other user's program.
So, flags contains some in- information
metadata about this page. Then, we have
a virtual address and a physical
address.
Now, for most of time,
we use PID
and the virtual address as the index.
So, that's the input for querying this
page table. Then the page
the flags and the the physical address,
PADDR,
are
the data that we want to query.
Okay?
So,
so whenever we want to access some data,
we know which process that we're running
for. Now, we know which virtual address
that we want to
uh
access because that part of data is
recorded in the register to represent a
pointer.
Now, we translate for the flags and the
physical addresses.
Now, sometimes in some system, we also
allow physical address to PID and
virtual address translation. That's the
inverse translation, but that's not
something that we're talking about
today.
Okay?
So, what physical address we need? Now,
physical address is uh
64-bit long,
right?
Uh
because we're running 64-bit systems.
Then, we the actually useful physical
address, because we're
our memory is not that large, so we
don't need that many bits. To save some
energy, we reduce the
uh physical address size. We just
consider it's 48-bit.
Right? Then,
48-bit. Then consider a page. How large
is a page?
4K, right?
>> [clears throat]
>> is 2 to the power of how many?
It's 2 to the power of 12, right? 2 to
the power of 12. Now, if it's 2 to the
power of 12, that means
the lower 12 bit within this address
only describes the offset within this
page.
Right? So, we don't really need to
record the offset 12 bit.
We only need to record 36 bit
as the index, as the identifier for this
physical page.
Okay? We call this thing PFN, which
stands for page frame number.
Which is a 6- 36-bit number that stores
in the physical in the
page table. Now, we won't really want to
reduce every bit to be stored in the
page table. The whole page table thing,
the whole address translation things are
considered overhead. It's not useful,
but it's only for achieving some other
features
that we have to have we have to use
physical addresses.
Okay? So, how we execute a program? Now,
at the core side, we're executing the
program, right? We're executing a
program. We're you executing a user
space program. Then this user space
program contains virtual addresses that
is stored in the register. Then this to
use this virtual addresses, then we have
to go through the address translator.
Logical. It can be
part of the core, can be part of the L1
cache. Okay?
It's a logical component. Now, it sends
a virtual address to the MMU. MMU here
stands for memory management unit. And
the most important thing is is
responsible for allocation process that
we're talking about, and it also
responsible for the
uh
address translation process that
translates from virtual address and the
physical address.
Okay? [clears throat]
So, we send a virtual address to the
MMU, then the MMU sends back the
physical address. Then starting from
this point, we can use the
physical address, access the rest of the
memory.
It should be memory here, not the
address translator.
Okay?
So, now we're talking about we have
already talked about process and thread.
Now, let's talk about MMU, how MMU
works.
Then MMU maintains the page table,
right? So, this
So, MMU sometimes can be a hard hardware
component. Now, in some system, it can
be fully implemented in the operating as
part of the operating system, as part of
the software.
Um but and no matter is hardware or
software, is maintaining a page table.
Then given the page given the PID and
the VPN, we should find the PFN.
Then actually for some type for uh um
Yep.
So you you can consider for PID, right?
How we can handle PID? Then your
computer actually can have multiple page
tables. For every PID, there's a one set
of page There's a page table that maps
to that PID. So I'm I'm just drawing a
logical representation of the whole
operating system. So the PID serves as a
column there.
Okay?
So say this whole process
of translating the virtual address to
physical address is page table walking.
What is page table walking? Now you can
just imagine this is a
bad example of page table walking.
We just go through
from I equals zero, I smaller than page
count, I plus plus, then we find
the page. Right? If the PID If If we
find the page, then we return the page.
Okay?
So the simplest the type of page
walking, which is very very inefficient.
Now what if we find we cannot find this
thing?
If we cannot find the page page table
page within the page table,
we do we throw a page fault.
A page fault is
thrown by either part of the operating
system or thrown by the MMU hardware.
Now
this is a exception.
Right? And when the when hardware throws
an exception, your operating system need
to tell how we can handle this
exception.
In this case, this page this exception
is a page fault.
Now what happens in page fault?
Now all your operating system will tell
what's going on with this page fault. We
want to try to find this address, but we
cannot find it.
The most two common things that can
happen.
So
how many of you have seen your program
print segmentation fault?
Right? So that's the most common result
of page fault. So it will print that
segmentation fault
then crash your program.
The second thing second second common
thing that can happen is it will
realize, "Okay, this page is actually
swapped to the hard drive.
Now we really really need to use this
address at this time.
Let's swap it in."
Then
when we swap in, we actually
re-add that row in the page table.
Now we can send back to MMU. Look at it
again. Now you have it.
Okay?
So the then your program will continue
to run as if nothing happened. So it
will only run slower, but
nothing other than No No other things
can happen.
Just will continue to execute.
Um since the page Whenever we have a
page fault, it's no longer in the page
table, right? So when is If it's in the
hard drive, that means it's not in the
this page table. It must make the
operating system must maintain another
table for the pages that is in the hard
drive.
So
that second option came to
for the temporary drive? No.
Did I answer your question?
There we go.
What up?
45 minutes.
It's pretty much done by every system.
Windows, Linux, Mac OS all support this
type of
um operation. It's only the
implementation detail is different.
Okay.
Okay. So the problem is this line. If
we're traversing through
the memory access, now think about the
overhead.
Every translation is a memory access.
Every step in the page
table walk
is a memory access. We only want to
access one byte of data. Now how many
access we actually need to trigger?
In the worst case, if we have 4 kilobyte
kilo
If we have 4K pages, then we're actually
accessing the page
4,096
times just for one memory access.
Right?
Now this is That means this is a
terrible design.
Now 4 GB of memory, that's this number
of 4K pages, right?
Just so
uh 4 kilo 4 GB of memory, 4 kilobyte
pages, that means 1,000
1,024
pages that we have to walk in the worst
case. Then that means
it's just the overhead is terrible. Now
we don't want this type of system.
Oh, it's not even one.
It's not 1,000 pages. It's 1 million
pages.
So this is terrible.
Okay? Now we don't want this O(n)
complexity.
Right? If we don't want this O(n)
complexity, what do we How we solve this
problem?
We want We want O(1).
And how we can convert to O(1)?
No.
Yep.
Okay.
Two two different solutions. We're going
to go with two different solutions. But
uh TLB definitely helps. But if you are
considering from a software domain,
then how can you deal with O(n)
complexity? You The immediate response
is you need to change from a list or uh
linked list or array to a hash table.
Right?
This should be the immediate response
for
all software developers.
Now but hardware can feel difficult to
implement a hash table. Now hash table
is too complex.
Now I don't know if you have learned
that even before introducing a hash
table, we want to use something called
direct access table.
Right? So we want to use a direct access
table. What is direct access table? That
means we just allocate a lot of space.
Then we say, "If this is the virtual
address, we just will store it We store
it here.
Never store it anywhere else. We just
store it here."
Okay?
So
that means
we have a region of memory that's
dedicated for the page table.
This region of memory that we have a
fixed location. Like VPN zero is stored
here, VPN one is stored here, VPN two is
stored here
for
every PID.
Okay?
Then
we can simply calculate address by the
initial address of the page table that
belongs to this PID.
Just by adding say if one page table
entry is 8 byte long.
I'm making up. It differs by system by
system.
So if it's by 8 byte long, it's
basically the initial address
then my
my initial address plus the virtual page
number multiplied by the page table
entry size. Right? So immediately we can
find location. Now we know where we can
find this address.
Then So basically see here, we can
directly find the location of the page.
Then we don't need a loop anymore. This
is a O(1) complexity.
At at least in temporal.
Now what is the complexity of spatial
complexity?
Then the spatial complexity here, now we
need to consider
We basically need one to two access per
memory access.
Um
So
consider we have 1 million pages, then
four to eight byte per entry per PID,
then that's four to eight megabytes in
size.
Uh but
remember
we consider the virtual address the We
consider virtual address to be unlimited
in size. Right? So the 1 million
entry is a very optimistic estimation.
So we may have more entries. Now we also
actually somehow set uh artificial
limitation for the virtual address size
if you use this way. So we need to
consider something in between.
Okay.
So
for 64-bit address, now we need 512 GB
page
page table per PID,
which is not acceptable.
Now we for most of the hard drive
for most of memory, we don't have this
size. Well, most of hard drive, we even
struggle with this size.
So what's the actual structure of a page
table?
We do it tier by tier.
Okay?
So
we already have this part.
The PID. According to our PID, we have a
page table base address.
Okay? So we know where is the page
table.
Then in this page table base address,
what we do is we arrange the entries
by a a region within this VPN.
By a section
of the addresses. In in case, it's
bit 35 to bit 22.
Arrange this region
for this table.
Okay? Then
using this part of the address, we can
find okay, it
it match to this one, for example. Then
what it's actually storing is the next
level of page table's address.
Okay? So, we don't immediately tell us
the result, but we can go to the next
region.
Okay? The next next region, we have
address from 0 to 21
bit.
Then here
there's another table that we can
immediately find
the
flag and the PFN there.
Okay? Two levels. Then even by two
levels, you'll find since you're not
covering the whole address range,
you don't really need
these sub tables
for all the address ranges.
Okay? If you're covering the whole
address range, then you basically you're
spending more
spaces.
But for most of time, you're not
covering the whole address, so you only
have a small very small subset of these
sub tables
as compared to the whole
address
coverage.
Okay?
So, in this case, we consider this
region. It's a 4 MB of consecutive
virtual address space
defined by
this number 21.
Okay? So, each sub table requires 32 MB
storage, which is much much better than
the 512 GB of storage. Okay? Just by
separating this thing, then we're
significantly saving some overhead
storage overhead or memory overhead for
memory tables.
Then the disadvantage as compared to
direct map method is we're adding one
extra memory access
to for every layer of the table. And
because we're accessing
we definitely need to access here, then
we access here, we access here. Then we
find the address.
One extra memory address.
So,
in real system,
what are the cases?
So, the common setup are either
four-layer page table or five-layer page
table. Four-layer page table is
organized in this way. 9 + 9 + 9 + 9 or
five-layer is done by this way. It's
just according to address ranges that we
want to cover. Or sometimes that we can
reduce some layers to
number of bit that according to how many
actual bit of address that we want to
use.
Okay? So,
consider this.
For uh
every memory access, how many memory how
many times of memory that we need to
access?
1 2 3 4 5.
Now,
in many system, we can ignore that part
is already memorized there somewhere in
the register. Then for this one,
it's
five times, right?
So,
it just feel weird, right? For one
memory access, we're accessing memory
six times.
So,
five memory access per translation,
which is 200 cycles to 300 cycles. Just
consider the memory is not heavily
burdened. There's not no long queue
there.
Okay?
So,
how we can further reduce this?
And the quick answer is
there's something called memory MMU
caches and TLBs.
Okay? We haven't introduced TLB. We
haven't introduced MMU caches.
So, they typically they're both used for
um
in real systems.
Okay? So, memory
memory memory
memory management unit, they're very
similar to core cores. They just go
through loops and access data. Right?
They just access the DRAM. In this case,
these DRAM are the memory pages. Then
you need to know these the memory pages
the memory table are actually also
stored as part of the
um
as part of the DRAM. So, they're stored
together with the mem with the regular
memory. So, nothing special. Then for a
core,
we have caches. Then the data access
shows some locality. Right? For both
temporal locality and spatial locality.
And for MMU, the locality is probably
even stronger that if we access the
data, then we may access some data
within the same page or within adjacent
pages next. So, we what we want to do is
basically we want to add caches here.
So, for most of the time,
these are regular way associative caches
as if the caches are for
um
data. Nothing special. Just the page
table contents stored there so that when
we access
page table entry, we don't really need
to go to the DRAM. We can go to the
caches. Then it should have a high cache
hit rate.
Okay? Then sometimes there can be this
MMU cache can even connect to multiple
layers of caches. And sometimes that
this MMU cache can be backed by regular
L2 caches or last level caches
there.
Okay? So, in best cases, if we're two L0
hits, then we can reduce the memory
access the or the translation to 50
cycles. Let's assume the cache hit is
if the cache hit is
10 cycles in latency.
Then typical case, then we miss one or
two layer, then we get 60 to 70 cycles.
So, the higher the level, the like the
outermost levels are very likely to hit,
right? The lower levels are less likely
to hit because it spans to a larger
range of address.
In the best case, then hit in last level
cache that in L3 caches, then we can
still significantly reduce the
um the the memory access the memory
translation time. Then the worst case,
all address DRAM access that is
what we have analyzed before all goes to
DRAM. So, if you can this see this,
we're actually actually using a simple
mechanism to reduce the memory
translation time significantly. If you
consider one memory one DRAM access is
about 50 to 60 cycles, then if we can in
the best case or typical cases, we
probably add the overhead
one time overhead.
Right?
Still not acceptable.
Still not acceptable. We want to reduce
it further.
The 100 time overhead is not acceptable.
We want to reduce it further. What we
can do?
And this is something that we have
talked about before. It's called
translation lookaside buffer or TLB for
short.
So, for most of time, they know TLB.
They don't know the full name of
translation lookaside buffer, which is a
cache, but they call it a buffer.
It's the caches for page tables.
Then
consider if a cache if L1 cache
hit for regular memory access. If your
core access a data in L1
cache, remember in our pipeline design,
we consider that's a one cycle thing.
Right? So, for a one cycle thing,
we cannot really compare a regular DRAM
access with this data. In DRAM access,
this is 100% overhead. But
there are caches. For main memory
access, we don't really need 50 or 60
cycles to or 100 cycles to go to the
DRAM. We probably only need one cycle or
a few cycle access latency
in
like L1 cache or L2 caches. Then we
definitely desire a one cycle
translation. How we can support a one
cycle translation?
It's basically
we say we wanted to access the data in
SRAM, a very small SRAM. Then we can get
a one cycle translation latency.
So, what we can do?
Now, we have shown this before. This is
a cache structure.
But I just slightly change it. Remember,
this was the tags before, right?
This time, this is the VPN.
Then our flags and PFN are stored there.
And using the VPN, we just have all the
comparators, then the flags and PFN,
then we just store just output data from
here, then use a control signal to
decide which flag and the
PFN signal then can go through go out
from this TLB.
Okay?
So,
briefly speaking, TLB is nothing special
but a cache.
But how it differs from MMU cache?
TLB caches stores every entry as a page
table entry.
Okay?
MMU cache stores every entry as a
regular cache line. So, it doesn't
really have the concept of page table
entries.
Okay? MMU cache is regular data cache.
TLBs are specialized page table caches
that every entry is a page table entry.
Then for most of time, especially for
CPUs and for L1 on
we typically use fully associative
cache. We have analyzed this one because
every pa-
the penalty of a TLB miss is very high
because we go into the memory
translation. Then this translation may
take tens to hundreds of cycles. And we
consider that's a very high penalty. And
the reward here is very low very high
because we typically do not have many
entries there. Then for L1 TLB is really
a one-cycle latency access.
Okay?
Then but
a key term here is TLB coverage.
So, what is TLB coverage?
TLB coverage is how many bytes
in term of address
that a TLB can cover.
Let's consider
Let's consider the TLB the page size
is 4 kilobytes, okay? Then L1 one L1 TLB
has say eight entries.
What's the TLB coverage?
Then the TLB coverage can be easily
multiply these two numbers together.
Right?
Then four multiplied by eight, that's 32
kilobyte.
That's the TLB coverage in this case,
right? So, TLB coverage is not something
uh
very fancy. Just simply multiply these
two numbers together. But it's a very
important matrix that describe how
powerful this TLB is, right? The larger
the
The lower The larger the coverage, the
more likely that we can
get a hit
in the TLB. Then TLB hit rate is very
very high.
Because
why? Because every entry is 4 kilobyte.
And you probably need to process a very
long time until you move to the next
page, right? Because this is not a cache
line.
A cache line 64 byte or 128 byte at
most.
This is 4 kilobyte. It's a lot.
Right? If you access data sequentially,
it takes a very long time before you
move to the next page.
Okay? Then
let's say
but L1 TLB
because we really want to one-cycle
coverage. And we have a lot of
comparators there. The size of L1 TLB is
typically not large. Then we have an L2
TLB.
Just stay there so that is larger. It's
probably not fully associative, but it's
definitely like 16-way or 32-way
associative.
Okay? In this In this way, we go with L2
TLB. Then we If it's still miss in L2
TLB, some system may even have L3 TLB.
Then we go to MMU. The MMU can
L1 cache, L2 cache.
Many actual layers. Now we really hope
that we can avoid extra DRAM access for
the address translation process.
Okay?
Then TLB also has coherency issue. And
sometimes after a page is migrated from
one allocation to another location. So,
think about migration. You need to move
the data from one place to another. Then
you also need to change the physical
address. You keep the virtual address
unchanged, but physical address changed.
So, how how can that's done? Then it may
require special protocols, but most
likely it's a shootdown based protocol.
Sometimes this shootdown is so stupid
because we don't want to add extra
hardware to TLB. We just say invalidate
everything in this TLB.
Okay?
But if some smarter If you want to
invalidate If you simply invalidate
everything into TLB, there's one-bit
signal. Don't need to tell which address
that we want to invalidate.
But if you want to be precise,
then you really need a complex wires
that go into one TLB to say I want to
shootdown this address.
Right? And sometimes
this L2 TLB because L2 TLB or MMU
doesn't really know if L1 TLB has that
address or not. So, it needs a broadcast
process to shootdown all the L1 TLBs.
So, page migration
can be a very very complex
process. Not because of the memory copy,
but because of shooting down all these
L1 TLBs and the recovering their
data and their context within this TLB.
Okay? That's can add a lot of overhead.
This overhead can be even larger than
migrating data
from one
page one location to another.
Okay? TLB cover coverage.
So, by the way, to increase TLB
coverage, there are two different ways,
right?
Because there are two parameters. One is
you can increase your page size. The
other way is you can increase your TLB
numbers
uh
entry numbers.
Okay? So,
then after introducing addresses virtual
addresses, we need to revisit caches.
Because previously we're just assume we
were just assuming caches uses physical
addresses. No problem. That's totally
okay. So, that means
we just translate before
the accessing the first level of cache.
But if you consider this case,
if my cache has 100% cache hit rate
or close to 100% cache hit rate,
accessing L1 cache is probably less than
five cycles latency, right?
Then even my TLB can provide perfect
memory access. Now I may add one to two
cycles extra overhead, right? Then I
don't really want to pay for this
process.
Can my cache actually use virtual
addresses?
Okay?
Should the
In what case the cache should store
physical address? And in what case the
cache should store
virtual addresses?
Okay? And then the story is a little bit
complex to introduce.
Let's remember one thing. In cache, we
have tags
and the index.
Right? And offset. This is our address.
Offset is easy. 12-bit before
uh not 12-bit. We're considering 64
byte, then the 6-bit. That's a small
size.
Then index.
Index is a few bit that decides which
set we need to go.
Right? Let's say if index is 00, it's
two bit. It's 00, then we can only go to
set one. Or actually I should write set
zero. Let's
bear with me. Then set one. Okay? If
it's
01, then it has to go to set two. Then
we If I know it goes to set two, then I
have two different ways that we can go.
Right? So,
a few bit
typical lower bit that is that
determines which set that my cache line
can go.
Then the rest is the tag. It's upper
bytes. Then we know we eventually need
to match the tags with the tags that
stored
as part of
the cache line, right? The tags here
with the request.
In this case,
we do comparison, then eventually we can
output data.
Okay?
So, by default, we use physical address.
No big problem.
That means we have to do a translation
before
we have to do a translation before the
caches.
Then that means the address translator
is here. It's
logically here. It physically can be
either part of the core or part of the L
L1 cache.
Okay? Then the address translator is
here. It's connecting to TLB and MMU.
That is performing the translation that
has
one extra overhead.
Then
if my L1 cache has very
high cache hit rate. For example, I want
to write L1I is not accidental.
For instruction cache.
Because we especially for GPUs. GPUs
typically run very small programs
repeatedly, right?
So, the L1 cache should be very likely
to cover the whole program.
So, we should rarely have any L1I
instruction cache miss.
That means L1 cache miss is typically
something like
uh
95 or even 99% of cache hit rate, right?
So, if we have very high cache hit rate,
we would don't want to pay the extra
translation overhead.
Because there's no need to do that,
right?
In this case,
we just swap these two.
We use L1 cache. Then everything is
virtual.
The request is virtual. The tags we
store there is virtual. The
index that we have
uh
is also virtual. Okay? Everything is
virtual.
Then does it work?
Then typically speaking, there's no
problem, right? It just can can work.
But there's a special problem problem.
Just one problem.
If you have multiple contexts or
multiple processes, then you swap in
another thread from another
process.
You have a aliasing problem. Aliasing
problem that means you may have
same name for two different things,
right?
That means
for thread one for process one
for P1, you may have this address.
For P2, you may have this address.
They are actually should translate into
two different
addresses. But assuming
if this is in
L1
I
Okay. If this piece of data is in L1 I,
now I swap to P2 and we want to access
this address.
And it's storing virtual address.
I will feel that's a hit.
Now I accidentally access data on that
belongs to another process.
Which is terrible, right?
So how can we avoid these type of
things?
Yep.
Yep. That's one one method. So method
one, do I have method
method written there?
Virtual address.
Yep.
Two different methods.
One method is we can have we can flush
the caches.
I switching.
So when we switch the context, we just
invalidate everything in our L1 cache.
Okay.
Then for everything that is all fresh
from L2 caches. Since L2 caches are
physical memory, no problem.
Then we just
use the data from L2 caches in that
case. The second method is we can
include a PID as part of the tag.
Include a process ID as part of the tag
so that every time we access the data,
we're not only accessing the tag itself,
we're accessing the PID, which requires
a few extra bit that we need to
store. Actually, that's a non-trivial
number of bit.
Um even in most of systems that we have
two bytes, that's 16-bit.
Right? For some system, we may have
32-bit, that's even worse.
That's 32-bit is
probably more than
the tag itself.
Right? So that's a that's some
big part of the overhead.
So I would say for most of the time, if
you do not consider frequent address
switching, then
uh
using this method is very reasonable.
Now for GPUs
for GPUs that may support executing two
threads
from two different processes at the same
time we within one core, then we really
have to use the second method.
Okay.
Remember, GPU doesn't really have a
context switching. That's even within
the same pipeline, different stages may
execute instruction from different
processes from different
warps. Then these warps may come from
different kernels and these kernels may
come from different processes. So we may
access issue two memory
instructions next to each other, but
they come from different processes. In
this time in this case, we don't really
have chance to flush. We have to
add extra
bits to
tell which PID it belongs to.
Okay.
So
we have talked about these two different
cases.
Our index are virtually
our virtual addresses or physical
address or tags also are virtual
addresses, right? So we have been
considered this thing should be either
virtual or physical. Or physical index
and physical tag.
Then
but we probably can look deeper into the
address
composition.
That's a typical case, right? For 64
byte
cache size
we can have 6-bit
offset and 6-bit index. 6-bit index.
That's actually a lot. How many sets are
there? 64 sets.
Right?
That's actually a lot of sets. So rather
reasonable cache.
Then in this case, remember we say it's
just a 48-bit system. Now we have
36-bit as tags.
Now for PFN, we also have another
offset. Now what's the offset size?
Now for a 4K page size, which is the
common page sizes we have 12-bit as the
offset.
So the interesting thing is
this is a perfect match.
Right? So the index can actually fully
hidden within this off offset. If we
don't have a super large cache.
And for L1 caches, this is very
reasonable.
Now L1 caches typically do not have so
many sets.
So what we can do?
We can try this method.
Virtual index and physically physical
tag. So virtual index physical tag or
sometimes we say this is a virtually
indexed physically tagged cache.
So let's see what we do.
In VIPD cache, we first load the data.
We don't even tell if it's cache hit or
cache miss. Just directly load data.
How we load data?
We don't load
a particular
we we don't load a particular cell.
We load multiple cells. And this cell
the number of cells
equals to the number of ways.
Because this data
because we already know the virtual
address, right? We already know the
virtual address.
So this virtual address that we can take
the 6-bit out of that. Now we can
immediately identify which set that this
data may come from.
Right? Just consider
matching the tag is a faster process.
But loading the data in reality
in your SRAM array is a slower process.
So what we do here is that we are we
load the data from all ways within one
set.
Okay, we load all the data from
from all ways within one set.
Then we just directly output them to the
read buses.
Okay, we load we read extra data to
these wires.
Then while this time while we're loading
the data here, we do the translation.
We go through TLB and hopefully we don't
even need to go to the MMU or something.
And since that we say TLB also has a
high chance of hit. Right? So in this
case, we send a VADDR here, then we can
generate physical addresses.
Then
the loading process and the TLB lookup
process can happen in parallel. And the
comparison can also happen almost
immediately. So these have one cycle
overhead
extra time.
Okay. So we're hiding the latency of
these two, then we let them happen at
the same time.
Okay.
So as a summary
PIPT, physically indexed and physically
tagged, we have to translate
then to the cache.
Okay.
VIPT
we don't need to translate at all. We
just directly go with cache.
When there's all talking about cache
hit.
We just go with the cache. And
definitely this looks like a good case.
But we have that aliasing problem. So
it's we it need extra bit or we need
extra flush.
Okay.
VIPT
these two parts happens at the same
time. So we have a good chance that we
can fully hide the translation time.
Okay.
We can fully hide the translation time
if it can be hit by L1 TLB, probably
even L2 TLB.
Then with a extra a little bit cache
time, then we can
complete a cache hit operation. We don't
even have the aliasing problem.
Right? We don't need extra flush, we
don't need extra bit. So it's perfectly
fine.
So that's why
modern CPUs
they really like to use VIPD caches.
Okay. For L1 caches.
So then quick question.
Why L2 caches are more likely to be
PIPD?
What's the hard limit for VI VIPD
design?
Remember this analysis?
The index must be
masked
by this offset region.
Okay.
If we have index that's 7-bit
that means we have 128 sets.
Which is common for larger set larger
caches.
Now our index cannot be fully covered by
the virtual address. We have to have
physical frame number.
Otherwise, then we have the aliasing
problem again.
Right? So the hard limitation is this
index must be
masked by the offset of the page frame
number. Then you can have a few choices.
If you really want to use VIPD, you can
either
increase the page table size the page
size, right? Add one extra bit. Or you
have to reduce the cache size.
Right? If you cannot do anything, you
cannot do neither If you can do neither
of them,
you have to go back to
a PIPT
or a VIVT. Okay? But more likely for L2
caches, we want to do PIPT. Only L1
caches they want to use VIVT.
Okay? Now for super high cache hit rate,
we don't even bother doing VIVT. Now we
just VIVT is good enough.
Okay? Super high cache hit rate and with
without very frequent contact switching,
which is the GPUs
L1 instruction cache.
And so we have it.
Okay?
PIVT
I cannot imagine why it's useful. So
it's not there.
Okay?
So but these three
are all commonly used.
Now VIVT is probably the rarer one.
But at least the VIP T is the high
performance L1 cache.
Now a PIPT is the most common type of
caches, especially for large caches, L2
caches, L3 caches.
Okay?
Then that's all for today's lecture. Any
questions?
Uh other than Okay. So for GPUs,
instruction cache is VIVT.
Okay?
L2 caches are PIPT.
Other L1 caches,
it depends on hardware.
But there's a general trend of moving
from this direction to that direction
in more and more recent version of GPUs.
Then if you talk about early version
GPUs,
like early That means before 2013,
um
what Nvidia is still called their GPUs
GeForce GeForce 256,
something like that.
This is not even a problem. They use
physical addresses.
Okay? So physical addresses in some
cases
is still a
possibility, especially for some
accelerators, because
all these address translation, no matter
how fancy it is, they're considered
overhead.
And we can only reduce overhead. We
cannot go back to negative overhead.
Right? The only way to eliminate this
overhead is to go back to physical
addresses.
Then that will be introduced
other new problems.
Okay, but for accelerators, for GPUs,
especially early stage GPUs, we don't
need to consider contact switching. We
can only render one game.
It's not a problem.
Now later on, we're going to talk about
MPUs, systolic array,
uh
CGRA's, then we're probably going back
to physical addresses. Then you will
find the addressing system is even more
um
weird.
Okay? So that concludes
this part, the cache, the memory system.
Then I won't talk about memory
consistency. I won't talk about DRAM.
Now we have to stop here. Then there are
two different topics,
two modules that we did you for this
semester. One is simulation, computer
architecture simulation. The other one
is spatial programming. So spatial
programming is the thing I would talk
about MPUs and stuff. I think today
is
necessary to introduce this type of
hardware. Then a few years back, it's
probably not that important. So we're
going to allocate at least the three to
four lectures for spatial computing, for
MPUs,
CGRA, tensor and this type of devices,
and non-traditional devices.
Okay? That's the plan for the rest of
the semester. So
uh
I know I owe you one lecture for the
advanced pipeline design. So but let's
finish this part. Let's have the quiz
and the the homework for the memory
system first. Now we Let's see if I have
chance to go back to that point or not.