hello everyone welcome back to mlc this
is episode nine in today's episode we're
going to talk about how we're going to
do high-level computational graph
optimization
to recap a bit um in previous lectures
we learned a lot about you know
different mlc processes that allows us
to transform
among different tensor functions in
particular we have learned about how can
we take permitted cancer operators
represent in an abstraction contains ir
that and how can we you know transform
those programs so that we can get a
program that are specialized to the
highway of interest
um
and along with that we also learned
about this high-level computational
graph abstraction right allows us to
represent
the higher level computations
and
there are a lot of transformations we
can also do on this high level
combinational graphs and always is a
primitive tensor function well on this
particular figure one thing we can do is
we can take
two
uh primitive tensor operators in here
and try to run them and convert them to
a single computational graph node
represented by fusing these two things
together
and another thing we are doing actually
in this particular figure is that we are
trying to
take this linear value and expand a
corresponding lower level loop level
representation so that we will be able
to
run transformation that optimize this
particular loop program further
most of the multi process can be viewed
as transformations among those tensor
functions
and today we are going to dive deeper on
you know right now we are doing it
visually and let's start let's start to
think about how can we write a program
to do this type of high-level
computational graph transformations
okay
so
to begin with
let's start to uh
let's start with a simple example
um
the
so so in here we are trying to evaluate
uh
a specific kind of test programs called
relax
and this program represents a simple
operation right takes in x and y and try
to compute
y
plus
x times
y okay
and we are doing this through two two
operations in here first of all we are
going to multiply
x and y and then we are going to add the
result back on to y in this case this
common two segments of pattern is a very
common pattern appearing in most of the
compilations actually it's called fused
my plan add so in this case uh you know
although we are doing in two steps
usually in a lot of cases they are
accelerated parameters that allows us to
that allows us to do it in one step in
this particular example every you know
at a high level tensor communication is
not necessarily
useful to represent the myopic ad using
a fused version by using we're only
using this example to demonstrate you
know what are
necessary apis we can use to transform
this high-level combination of
computational graph code
okay so before we start to run some of
the transformations let's start to look
at what's under the hood that's backs
what are the things down the road that
backs this particular
uh particular relaxed program in this
python asd form
so uh one thing we can do is we can try
to
get out the relax function here and look
at this type you'll find that this
particular relax function contains a
type of you know
of course relax function
and it contains several fields so you
have a parameter field
that represents effectively the two
parameters that we have in here
and they have a body field that
represents the function body in this
case the function body is of type
sequence expression
and then
the sigma expression will contain a list
of binding blocks that correspond to
this
set of bindings we have previously
and
in this case we have only have one
binding block and this particular
bending block corresponds to this two
segments of operations that contains you
know multiply and n
we can also try to print out
the
bindings uh which contains two wire
bindings and we look at particular one
by binding and chris it contains a
variable
that uh
that shows you know
what other
that shows the left-hand side of a value
and the value that corresponds to the
right hand of the value that you're
buying through
of course we are doing a quick will with
tall of the data structure so it's a bit
it can feel a bit confusing
on you know where you directly go and
run the code so next let's try to look
at
these two data structures from and the
on the left hand side is the original is
original python tbm script code and the
right hand side is a visualization of a
corresponding data structure that we
just walked through forward
so in this case
um you can find that
this particular main function
corresponds to a data structure called
relax dot function
so i'm going going through the code
example again except that you know we're
doing the need in this visualization
right so it contains the two parameter
field that's x and y which corresponds
to these two parts
and then
the particular body of a function is a
what we call a sequence expression so a
second connection will contain a
sequence of
binding blocks in this particular case
uh we only have like one data flow block
actually that's the most commonly um
that's most common case in a lot of
accommodation graph optimizations uh in
other cases if we have like side effects
and multiple data flow blocks we could
have a sequence expression that contains
multiple data flow blocks
so a second solution have a field called
blocks that list all the blocks that
they have
and in this particular case we have one
block
which is a data flow block in here
and data flow block
record that you know data flow block
effect represents a computational graph
where each of the computational graph
node within the data flow block
contains only you know side effect free
computations so that we will be able to
view it as a directly accessible graph
just like a normal computational graph
and then within the infograph we have a
list of bindings in here
and each binding
corresponds to one line
of the left-hand side that uh
that performs in here multiply and n
okay so so if you look at the
visualization on the right it represents
what the overall data structure looks
like to support the
uh the tbm script code on the left-hand
side and finally
for each of our binding they have a
left-hand side right-hand side so the
left-hand side is a variable
a field in here and right hand side
contains
a value field that corresponds to the
value that we're bought into
and in this particular case this value
is a core node
just like we
we are listed out in here so effectively
it is a call node with operation field
um that runs relaxed or multiply
and then it contains two inputs x and y
so this variable corresponds to x and
this variable corresponds to y in this
case
okay
so so one of the things that we want to
ask is you know
can we
take
this
of this uh computational graph on the
left hand side and trying to fuse the
multiply and all add operation together
because we know that you know um we
might be able to get a
more accelerated version or you know for
other reasons we simply want to
fuse it together to demonstrate this
graph transformation so effectively what
we want is we want to be able to take
these two variable bindings
and turn it into you know one a new
variable binding that
effectively performs a multiplier
okay so there are different ways that we
can do it of course one way we can do it
is we can
you know recursively visit the data
structure that we have that represents
this um
high-level conditional graphs
and then we're going to reconstruct
another relaxed function that puts more
into
the the new ast that
makes the makes the two sense fusing
together
this is of course doable because all the
data structures that we have in here
are available in python we'll be able to
build uh
actually it's an interesting exercise if
you know you want to go ahead and do it
from scratch
so another thing that we can do
and this is what we're going to do now
is that we're going to use some
additional data structure and the
toolings that help us to simplify this
process
and in particular we're going to use a
pattern called visitor pattern
to do this for writing
so here's here's a particular code
example that shows how can we
do this fma rewrite using a visceral
pattern i think here relax.high
experimentator is
uh
is a muted class that helps us to do
rewriting okay
so what visitor pattern tries to do is
that it will try to
go ahead and recursively run
and visit
this abstract synthetic on the on the
right hand side
and for each kind of of of the of the
node for you know in this case and this
is a sequence
expert that's the airflow block it's bar
binding and in this case this is a core
node
it will call a what we call visit
function
that that
that allows us to be able to visit this
uh this node
and this particular case is a mutator so
the behavior of mutator is that it's
going to
do call visit that gives you an original
node
and you can try to return a new node
that that you want to that want to use
to replace this particular node example
i in this case when i call visit of
relax. i can try to say i'm going to
return something like relax.multiply
and then
then you know you know the return new
node will get replaced in this location
and you will get something that is gv
equal to x dot multiply
okay so let's take a look at this code
logic in here
on how we're going to implement this
fused my plan at operations
so as a first step what we're going to
do is we're going to call
expert visit post order so this is uh
this is calling the parents uh
definition of physical effectively
that tries to
first of all try to you know uh do some
of the helper functions to remap some of
the variables if my some of my inputs
have already been written so it's a
common thing that we are doing
and after we call this visible sorted we
are going to get a core and one of the
things we are going to do is we are
going to detect whether or not there is
a pattern that we're interested in in
here and it matches the pattern we're
interested in we're going to try to
replace the core otherwise we're going
to return our original code okay
so in here what what we're going to do
is we're going to get
two three operations in here i add all
my pi up and e y fma up these operations
correspond to the primitive operations
that we have in tbm
and and you will be able to pattern
match this uh we we'll be able to use
those to pattern match the particular
code that we're interested in so first
of all we're going to check the current
core
and and because we're interested in
multiplayer add pattern so in fact we're
interested in something like at
l v 0
some result and you want to say l v 0
equals multiply actually before n in
here right so first we're going to check
if the current node is an add node if
not of course the pattern match fill so
we directly return the core value
the second thing we're going to do is
assuming that we already have adding
here
and we have adding here
of two inputs we're going to track the
first input remem uh the
the the value of first input right so in
this case
um
the relaxed program usually um sits in a
form called a normal form which means
that
every input to the
to the detail function is a specific
variable here so if you look at our
original program you'll find that
effectively this lv zero so once we
detect this i want to know like what
does lv0 correspond to
so all we can do is we can do a lookup
mining
that tries to
that tries to give us you know whether
or not if it's being binded in a
previous variable bindings it will give
us the value of that bonding value of
course in certain cases the particular
var uh can correspond to parameter of a
function in this case that's not
correspond to an existing binding being
uh in current data flow block in this
case the value will will return
now
and um okay
so
so in this case uh we're trying to look
up bindings i want to go and try you
know if this particular binding responds
to another chord
okay
if it's corresponding to another core
and
if this value is multiplied then of
course we have a successful pattern but
if you know if we do not if none of the
if neither of the conditions are
satisfied we will need to return the
original top which means that you know
my pattern matching is not successful
at this point
and once we have done this
and at this point all the pattern
matching is successful all we can do is
we can go and construct another core
that contains the new fma of and
and it contains you know true of
arguments the value of r0 variable x1
that corresponds to the the two inputs
of the multiply
and then call of arc one corresponds to
the second input of the add
once we construct it the new call we can
return it
as as a replacement
of the antenna of this visit core
operation
okay
so effectively the ideal visitor pattern
is that we're going to specify for each
of each kind of data structures
we're going to look at certain patterns
and we're going to we're going to say
that whether or not we are interested in
replacing this particular value or
particular node with another value of
interest
so we'll go ahead and run this
you'll find that so here what i'm going
to do is i'm going to instantiate a
version
of this mutator and call visit expert on
a function that we're interested in and
what it's going to do is that you know
this visit expert is going to
recursively transverse
that particular function shown in the
ast
that we just walk through in here and
tries to look into
uh you know each of the each other side
and for each of the cores we're going to
invoke that function
in that particular case when we invoke
visit call on this
node
it's a pattern that's matched right so
so effectively it's going to return the
fma
add operation
it's also going to invoke visit call on
this particular node here
and in this case it's going to multiply
operation
so
remember that then you know this
condition wouldn't satisfy is going to
return the original call and as a result
you know we are not going to touch that
particular
binding values even though we have
called visit call that binding value
so if you look at the end result you'll
find that the second line right get
replaced by eyes fma
x y y which is a desirable result that
were interesting one thing you'll notice
is that actually we still keep the first
line in this case actually this first
line is what called that code because
you know
it's not it's a local uh variable
binding within a data flow block that's
not being referenced anywhere so
actually it's safe to delete this
particular operations
and we can do that by
a
word function called remove r used and
if we do that we can find that the final
operation contains the
eyes fma
that
that takes x and y and multiply them and
add them to y
and you know this is the first uh
first
attempt that for us to write a
computational graph transformation based
on this python visitor pattern
okay
okay so so far we have um
get a taste of
how can we
use the visitor pattern to manipulate
this abstraction texture using relax and
trying to allows us to be able to take
two computation operations and diffuse
them together as a into a new node
let's start to get let's start to try
some other
possible combination graph
transformations that are closer to a
real word set
so in this particular case uh let's
let's first reuse the
models that we use in the past few
lectures the fashion and this model
remember that this particular model
contains
uh several layers right it contains two
fully connect layers in this case
uh and a biased add layer along with a
random layer in between
and uh so we are going to use in this
case we are going to use the block
builder api to view this
and once we create the model uh here is
a high level uh relaxed code that
is used will be done this particular
android model
also you might notice is that in this
case we are again using the high level
computation operations as opposed to you
know
using emit te right that directly give
us the
lower level tensile function cost
actually you know the combination graph
optimizations can work on both settings
and to make things more general after we
encourage writing some of the
combinational graph transformations
based on analyzing analysis of the
of the you know tens ir functions
in in those cases actually analyzing
tensile functions and doing
transformation models can be more
general than those high level operations
for this particular lecture we are
trying to make things a bit more
simplified so you know looking at a
higher level combination graph
operations it's uh it's simpler because
you can directly look at the primitive
operation and pattern match on it so
there are pros and cons but the
techniques that we are teaching here
actually can be applicable to both cases
so what is we are going to do is we are
going to try to do a work called fusion
operation in this case we are interested
in recognize a dance and add pattern so
imagine that we have
input x
w
then you have
add
that takes a bias turn
we're interested in recognizing this
entire
uh computational graph and try to fuse
them onto a single code block in here
and this optimization is commonly
used in a lot of the
higher level combination graph
optimization as a matter of fact you
know um fusion is likely going to be the
most fragmented topic besides like
layout writing and memory planning
and it's one of the most commonly used
combinational graph optimizations for
high level computation
so let's try to do that
and in this case what we are we're
interested in is we want to be able to
recognize a pattern
that contains
dance and add i want to put it together
as a single function
so we're also going to use a similar pi
expert mutator in here
and the idea is we want to go ahead and
detect
a dense operation and an operation and
then we want to be able to
in this case you know
in this case we will not create a new
uh primitive operation called dancing
because if we start to try to create the
permitted operations for all the
possible combinations of fuse operator
it's going to be there are going to be
exponential amount of possibilities
right so instead
what we're going to do is we're going to
just detect
the dance and add and try to isolate
them onto another sub function
that that marks effectively hey i want
to fuse those two operations again
so
if you are a bit confused of what it
means let's go ahead and go through the
code i'm going to show you what's the
end result and you will understand you
know what weigh me exactly
let's go ahead and first run this code
and see the end result before we come
back to the implementation worker
effectively after we run this code
our end goal
is to produce this program
in fact you will find that you know this
program contains two sub functions
fieldness and zero enthusiasts at one
within issue of star functions it
contains a true dance and add operations
except that you know the input shape of
each function is specialized to the
shape of the particular fuse dance and
pattern
so so effectively you can find the
transformation we are doing here
is we are taking
the original computational graph by
detecting the dance and add operations
and we're trying to
turn it into another function right that
we can call into so so these two
uh sub functions naturally marks the
boundary of the of the fusion that we're
interested in
okay
so let's come back to implementation of
this
the implementation is relatively similar
to what we had before
first of all we are going to have uh
in this particular case the dance add
filter will will contain well input ir
module
that's the ir module that we're
originally interested in
this is the transform function that will
return a new ir module that's uh that's
in a transformed version so in here what
we're going to do is we're going to
iterate over original ir modules
find out all the possible relax
functions in this case
we for relax function that contains a
primitive
attribute it's a function that's already
being you know grouped as sub function i
want to skip them we're only interested
in the functions that are non-primitive
and then what we're going to do is for
each of the functions we're going to
call visit expert to update that
particular function
remove all the unnecessary
local variables that are
being
used that are not being used within the
airflow block after updating
and then we're going to update this
particular function
in this case
each of the
mutator contains an internal block
builder that allows us to use them to
build a new
functions that
that we are interested in
and based on original ir module in this
case we are going to update the original
function to with updated version finally
we are going to use the builder.get
that's going to give us the ir module
after the update okay
so here's the transform code and let's
start to look at what's the core code
in this case in a music call call we're
going to try to detect a pattern
that's called dance and app so the first
thing we're going to do
is we're going to define a generic
function called match core
effectively it detects whether a node is
relaxed for node and if the operator
matches together okay
so
so let's start to do pattern matching
because we're trying to detect a dance
and add operation the first thing we're
going to do is we're going to first
detect add operation
to say you know this if there's
something that's available of add
and if not of course we are going to
return our original value because the
patent match fell
if the
if we you know if we match the first
level the second thing we're going to do
is we're going to look up the bindings
of the first
add operations and check if there's a
dance operation okay
and uh if the if the value is dense
operation it constitutes the correct
match otherwise uh it's not uh
effectively you know we're going to
return the original call means that
we're not going to modify this
particular column
okay once we finish the matchings we can
do is you can extract out
all the corresponding values in here
in this case because we are not going to
create a primitive new permitted
function core so it's slightly more
complicated we need to create a
different
we need to create a different functions
right that we're going to add back to
our original set of setup functions in
here
so first of all we're going to create a
new builder to build that new function
and we're going to assign a name and
we're going to use the content to recall
you know what is the set of totally
dance and functions we have so far
and then this particular new function
contains two operations first of all
we're going to
it contains
three parameters w
and
x w and b we're gonna do a dance and add
operation and that's my final outfit
once i get that particular function
i will be able to
take that function and i'm also going to
attach additional
attribute called primitive that marks
that hey this is a lex function that
corresponds to a uh fused group right in
here and it's just a convention that
we're using to mark the corresponding
fuse function
and then we're going to add this
function
to
our current ir module that's being
viewed in this case um you know
after we add it it will give you a
global variable that we can use to
referring to that
particular added function
so after we add this function we can do
relax.cor
to call into that global variable and
this will construct a new
call node if actually that caused on
true that corresponding chris chris
morning fused
dance at operation here
so this is the original mutator that
we're creating and the second thing
we're doing is we're going to react as a
path so here past is just another rapid
data structure that will create
that allows us to be able to you know
that allows us to
create a wrapper that that
that represents you know transformations
among ir module and i have objects so
here we're just taking a module and
we're going to call the dash and
future.transform
that gives us the transform result
so once we have these parts
one thing we can do is we can take an
original module
and then run it through the path
constructor that gets the parse
and then
give us the mop fuse which is the final
return output if you look at the output
again you can find that that gives you a
few stance and operation here
one thing to mention is that you know
what we're doing here is not so typical
if you look at other machine learning
frameworks
most of the cases when people are doing
fusion people are simply detecting
patterns and we are not creating those
sub functions instead
we will directly replace it with
something like relax dot fuse dance add
operation that contains a special
implementation
the reason why we are doing we are
choosing to create a sub function here
is that in instead learning location we
are interested in a lot of generic
fusion patterns but not only were
interested in fusing dance and ad but
also introducing interesting infusing
dance and then relu dance and reload and
and multiply and so on so there are
exponential amount of possible
opportunities that we can do in a lot of
fusion passes
in reality the most powerful powerful
fusion passes will also try to you know
make use of this upgrade opportunities
for example um the mature diffuser will
try to fuse all the possible elements
operations onto a dance operation
regardless of you know what kind of
computations they want
so in order to perform that we can no
longer introduce a specific type of
permanent operations for each type of
use operator
and
this particular
views and dance ad
sub functions help us to represent
effectively here's a fusion group while
containing all the necessary information
for low-level code generator and future
optimizations to be able to leverage and
generate a fuse operation so that's why
we are
following this you know different
convention that's actually more advanced
and help us to be able to represent more
possible fusion patterns in the future
okay so so far we have
done the first transformation that takes
the original function we are fusing the
dense and n operation together
as a second step
in order for us to really create
something that runs on the hour
we still need to be able to map those
operations like you know dance and not
dance and here but at least add
dance
relu those are all high level permittive
operations so i still need to map them
onto something that's runnable on the
hub and in order to measure something
that runnable remember that for
primitive potential functions there are
two approaches we can either map them
onto
the library
that
that correspond to our opaque function
call in the environment
or we can imagine to test ir function
that we can further do transformations
thread bindings and try to do even do
automatic program transformation to
matching on the corresponding power of
interest
so in this case let's let's try to map
those permitted tensor functions
onto tensile articles
and one interesting thing is that we can
also treat that as a computational graph
optimization in this case we are just
going to recursively visit all the cores
that chris want a high level permitted
operations we're going to translate it
onto
a lower level
uh on a low level call onto a tensile
function
so here's the implementation of of this
if you look closely you'll find it looks
very similar to
the original importer that we
implemented in the framework integration
section
because that important factor is
traversing over a combination graph from
pytorch and effectively mapping onto a
combination graph that contains
a
tensor expression operation in this case
we're just going to transverse in a
combination graph represented
being relaxed but with higher level
operations we're going to transverse and
remember onto
corresponding low level operations or
tensile level operations
so this is the parts that this is the
mutator that we're going to write
effectively we are going to do visit
core and for each of course
we are going to look up what we call
operator map
that
specifies for each kind of operator how
we are going to
translate that code okay so this is
something that's not yet to be defined
we're going to look at definitions down
here below
and then this transform function is kind
of similar it's just going to
recursively visit each of the functions
i'm going to
update
the corresponding value with the with
the neo global variable in here
okay
and then here are the mapping functions
that we have so for each of our course
what we're going to do is we're going to
return what we call core te so this is
slightly similar to emit t except that
in this case core t is not going to
return your binding it's just going to
create a tensile function return a call
this is because you know where
transforming the core node that's
already a binding available so i just do
call t e here
and
so in here uh x and y are the input
arguments we're going to do is we're
going to call t e
at pi dot dash this is the test
expression implementation
and
this the first argument is a block
builder in this case uh the
particular visitor have a blog builder
attached to it allows us to
use to construct any new
uh
any any new additional functions that we
might want to add to the current module
during transformation okay
and once we
do
core te under the hood
what it's doing is that the block
builder is going to create a new tensor
function using the test expression and
then generate the core node called tier
node that calls onto that tensilized
function so similarly for add we're just
going to colony topic.net and relu we're
going to call t dot top high reload this
is the corresponding lower level mapping
function that we can we can customize
some sand onto this
lower level tensor translator
okay and again we are going to wrap it
as a path
that allows us to effectively
you know do things in a more unified way
a tbm having structure to to do things
like training process together and
also introspect during passes and so on
so it's just another level of wrapping
to make it more standard
and then we can go ahead and run we can
create this path
that actually leverages this operator
map here and
placing the input
originally fuse the functions in high
level
uh primitive ops and we're going to turn
them on to a low level intensity
function
let's try this
after run it you will find that
you know we still have those
fields there's add operations
and the renault operation is already
turned into a reload operation
uh in here
that corresponds to a
let's say
uh relu operation in here right so that
correct one has our functions and then
for those few stance ad you'll find that
within fuse dance and
i'm holding here
it also turns those high-level permitted
functions into calls onto
the lower level tensile function this is
dense and add operations right each of
them are being implemented separately
this add operation here
and then we also have
interpretation like dance operations in
here in kansai
but one thing we notice is that you know
ideally when we want to really fuse
things together i really want to be able
to perform this dance and add operation
in a single shot as opposed to you know
still doing it in a group sub function
where we are calling true tensile
functions separately right so we really
want to have a
final function that you know fuses those
two things together
so uh
the tvm cr provides an additional path
that turns
those
uh fused dance the ad operation that
contains two years onto a single tensor
function and that part is slightly more
complicated so we are not going to
implement by ourselves i'm going to
invoke this first
called fuse tir
and after this all you'll find is that
the original fusedness add operation in
the lex function disappears and the only
thing that's left here is two core tier
functions to fuse and add one fusedness
at zero and field dance and one
and the fuse net at zero and fuel
sensing at one will correspond to a
cancer function
that fuses the original true continue
function together so effectively you can
you can view this
uh original field as add function as the
input specification to the fuser or you
know hey i really want to fuse those two
card here function together yes how it
groups in in in organic way and then
fused here is going to take that future
decisions and try to generate a low
level function that stitches things
together so in some sense we are
separating the decision of what to fuse
and
and the action of actually fusing them
so they previously we are trying to
writing passes to provide decisions on
what to fuse by creating those
subfunctional groups together then
fields tears going to create a tensile
function that puts things together
in a fuse function
of course in order to generate the most
efficient
use code we still need to be able to
take those code blocks and run
additional transformations like inlining
the addition function if i hold back
onto
background to the matrix multiplication
operations after we compute some of the
blocks of the computations we can do
that using you know automatic scheduling
mechanisms that we introduced in the
past few lectures or if you're
interested you have to go ahead and take
out the function and manually transform
them uh as you will so i'm not going to
go through this but uh
it this basic flow kind of demonstrates
you know uh actually a huge spectrum of
life in terms of
what things can happen during a
computational graph optimization phase
and machine learning compilation phase
so after we get this
transformed field's tier function
in the next step we're going to go ahead
and build and run
this function
and
so we're going to use the fresh admins
models
and here's the back right and we're
going to run through this particular
function
and by putting in the final module
standing here and it predicts back as
expected so in some sense this is a
effective moc process that starts from
car level model creation
transform edge using operator fusions
then we are going to lower that onto a
low level tensile function run fused
here to fuse all those uh fused low
level fuse operator onto really a single
operator and then you will get a
roundabout program so today we are
really experiencing multiple steps of
transformations in our ir module here
okay so in this lecture we have talked
about we'll come back to a common cmo
transformation just like we said the key
idea of mlc is trying to be able to
represent the programs and being
transformed in a flexible way
the few things the future operations we
introduced today is really primitive so
biampo is not as robust in some sense uh
in a lot of fusion patterns like in
certain cases
we might get a fusion pattern like
matrix multiplication that's followed by
two addition
operations in this case our current
fusion path actually will create two
parallel matrix modifications that
creates additional redundant computation
which is not desirable
a robust fusion pattern will detect this
and try to avoid diffusion in this case
an angle fuse in you know uh and not
choose not to fuse actually modify to
the add operation
additionally um you know
currently we're only using what we call
pattern-based fusion which means that
we're detecting a specific pattern like
dancing and add and fuse them together
a more robust user will try to analyze
the patterns even more geologically
foreign you will analyze the addition
and other operations by looking at the
tens ir functions and say hey is this
pattern element wise this is pattern
broadcasting reduction
and make use of those
analyzed patterns to inform our fusion
and in this way you know the fuse is
much more generic so you don't
necessarily have to specify all the
possible excel instances of possible
fusion patterns we can do fusions like
fuse all the element wise operations on
to
a complicated contextual contraction
operations and so on so these are
more powerful optimization that fuses
that support
on the other hand the lessons we learned
today actually can be very useful for
example in certain cases if you want to
go and customize the fusion behavior for
example in certain accelerators maybe
you want to be able to use two dense
operations together in a consecutive
fashion in other cases maybe there are
two concept convolutions that you want
to fuse
while the original fuse is not
necessarily ready to support it
so one thing you can do
is you can go ahead and write a
customized user that makes a
visualization of you know taking the
convolution conversion operation fusion
together
of course you know the customized user
is going to be limited it's only going
to fuse the particular instances of
interest but then what you can do is you
have you can take that fused
operation and run it through the generic
diffuser again which will go ahead and
fuse the rest of the component using
original fusion patterns
and finally this combination of two-step
fusion will gives you a more
interesting fuse patterns that not only
leverages original fusion patterns that
our generative user have but also have
this new interesting behavior that you
can go ahead and customize and you can
first further explore what are the
possible advances you can have by trying
all those fusion patterns
so one key here is again
compositionality right all of those
transformations are transformations
among ir module towards ir module and we
want to be able to leverage the
conversationality to allow us to compose
different transformations together like
you know lowering to tensor ir functions
with fusions sometimes we might want to
lower positive computations on the
libraries then perform fusion and and
the tensor loading or other parts really
want to be able to organically compose
them together so that
it gives us a flexible way to optimize
our machine learning programs
and that's kind of come back to our
overall theme of mlc
okay
so thanks for listening this is the end
of today's episode
and i will see you folks next week