okay welcome back to machine learning
compilation hello everyone so it's dq
again uh in the last two weeks we have
learned the overview of machine learning
compilation and then we in the last
lecture we talked about the or tensor
program abstractions
since last lecture we got some feedbacks
about you know you'll be great to still
have a deeper dive of some of the tensor
program obstructions so in today's
lecture we are going to
do a bit of adjustment and focus on
taking a specific case study of one
cancer program abstraction which we kind
of glimpsed over in the last lecture but
didn't get a chance to deep dive into
and this particular tensor program
abstraction is called cancer
okay so today's lecture is more like a
hands-on experience i'm going to use
this collab notebook to walk you through
some of the key elements in a tensor
program abstraction
and there will be notebooks and
exercises for you in a later part of the
lecture to go through and try things out
and play
those
notebooks by yourself so to begin with
we have a
package that packages up the necessary
dependencies that are needed for this
lecture so we will be able to install
those dependencies in here
before we talk about the specific
tensile orientations
let's start recap
some of the
lessons we learned in the first lecture
when we talk about machine learning
compilation we have discussed that the
ormoc process
is a process that allows us to be able
to
um
you know take the original program and
transform them
um onto a different
tensor program functions and in certain
cases can be on
on different abstractions as well for
example in this particular case we are
transforming
a
existing development form that
start with something on the left that
don't have a detailed implementation
onto something on the right that
contains a more specific implementation
for linear value function and in this
particular case we're also fusing these
two uh
two
tensor operations onto one
and in the last lecture we talked about
tensor primitive functions specifically
we're interested in transformations on a
single unit of computation and in this
case the single unit can be a
linear layer or linear value layer and
how can we enable abstraction to
represent
the implementation of those operators
and how do we make effective
transformation among them
so in today's lecture we're going to
dive a bit deeper onto a specific
implementations on how we might go and
implement
a permittive tensor function
so let's begin
before we talk about
the specific things um we are going to
use uh us
we are going to introduce a specific
example that we're going to use
throughout this lecture
and of course the first step uh in here
is we're going to import
a few of the existing dependencies and
in this case
this lecture is going to talk about tens
ir so it's the latest tesla tensor
program abstraction of the
apache tbm framework
and we're going to do some of the
preliminary importing here another thing
we're going to use today is numpy which
hopefully you are already familiar with
on
we are as a basic tool to do
uh to do linear address on
on matrices and multi-dimensional
tensors
so throughout this lecture we're going
to use one example that
that correspond to a typical tensor
permittive tensor function specifically
let's assume that we have two matrices
a and b
and we're interested in do the following
computation so first of all we want to
do
a matrix multiplication that takes in
a element and these elements and try to
produce a matrix for y
that effectively you know do a matrix
matrix multiplication of a and b and
secondly let's assume that we're going
to take y and perform a value activation
layer that takes y onto and produce
another matrix c
so this is a
example that we're going to use
throughout today's class
to demonstrate you know how we can
implement these two operations using
some of the tensor program abstraction
and what are the possible ways that we
can uh we can transform these tensor
programs a model
and one of the things that i want to i
want to mention that these two
computations closely resemble a typical
tensor program function that we see in
your networks specifically if you're
seeing a neural network that contains
something like a linear layer
followed by
a rectified
rectifier linear unit
this two operations kind of represents a
linear followed by revenue so we
deliberately choose this example for
that purpose
okay
so
um
let's begin by asking how we can
implement these two operations
specifically uh let's begin ask you know
how we can implement these two
operations in in numpy
and the way that we do that
uh would be
quite simple because numpy itself
already offers operations such as matrix
multiplication and in this case element
wise maximum
so what we can do is let's let's try to
allocate two arrays in here a and b
and then we are going to do a matrix
multiplication in this case if you
haven't used numpy at least
this is quite new to me as well if you
use the add operation
a at b is short for effectively numpy
dot matmo
am b
so so effectivate the add operation is a
matrix multiplication operation after we
perform the matrix multiplication we'll
be able to perform lmi's maximum to be
able to
compute the final result
okay
so we'll be able to implement
these two operations using the numpy
coding here and one thing we can try is
you know we will be able to go and run
go ahead and write okay
one of the things that we're going to
talk about today is actually not only
you know the high level matrix form of
implementation which we do here
by introducing something under the hood
so our question that i want to ask we
want to ask you know
what exactly does numpy or other machine
learning frameworks do
when they execute the code under the
hood
and and specifically when we run this a
a numpy at b numpy matrix multiplication
numpy b
and then maximum operations
under the hood the numpy library will
take those operations and trying to
dispassion onto lower level
implementations usually in c or in other
standard libraries such as open blocks
or other libraries
so in this lecture let's try to go a
level deeper on asking now what if we
don't have those matrix operations
already implemented how can we implement
those in a lower level permits
of course we are not going to go with c
since c is not a prerequisite for a
lecture
uh we're going to use a specific form of
python or numpy api which we call a
lower level number okay to implement
these uh to implement this matrix
multiplication and atomized operation so
the specific idea of lower level number
is that we're only going to use a very
restricted subset of numpad specifically
we'll be able to use loops
of array functions
uh loops instead of error functions when
necessary to demonstrate a loop
computation
and when possible we always express the
allocated arrays for
by the numpy empty chord and then
passing around the reason
why we are going to use this convention
is because these two conventions kind of
closely resemble how
lower level programs
are being written most real-world
low-level programs will be are written
in you know explicit loop forms and
usually um there is explicit handling of
allocation in a separate place
then the allocation memory is going to
be be able to pass into the
uh computations to run a specific
computation
okay so if you're still a bit confused
that's fine uh let's start to take a
specific look on
what a low level numpy implementation of
the matrix multiplication and value
might look like
so that's the coding here
uh which is already being typed out
and let's go through line by line on
what's happening here so first of all in
this particular function it's going to
take three arguments
a uh there are three arguments here so a
b
and c
and specifically remember that we are
going to you know take a and b to
measure multiplication on modern and
then do a value and store that to c so
both a and b correspond to my input
and c is my output
and we're going to explicitly pass in
the input output to the function okay
and another thing that we want to do in
here as the first steps we want to be
able to allocate
uh intermediate memory y
to store the temporary load of matrix
multiplication
okay
and this three loop nest is used to loop
over the
the matrix computation we're interested
remember we are interested in y i j
equals sum
over k
a i k
times
b
j k
here
and in order to perform this computation
what we do is we loop over i and j in
here and then we loop over k
um
so in this particular program actually
we write it in a specific way which we
will explain later but this is a valid
way to write matrix multiplication so
what we do is when k equals zero we
initialize the ig location to zero
and afterwards we are just going to do
accumulations to effectively perform
this sum operation and finally this loop
will give us the result of y i j for all
the i j is very interesting
after we compute the y i j what we do
next we are going to take that value and
and do another true level loop to
compute the c value so this is
effectively performing the random
activation that we are doing here okay
so
so here's this is like a one
implementation of the major matrix
multiplication algorithm in what we call
low level number
um and if you look at this program and
then look at the conventions we will
talk about you can find that the first
floor there's uh that there's this this
is a this is the exclusive uh allocation
here that explicitly allocated temporal
memory this is because a lot of
low-level implementations again handles
their allocations by themselves we're
also explicitly passing
the output memories directly onto the
function instead of having the function
allocate the memory and return it back
so that you know in some of the lower
completions we might be able to see
shared memories among
different intermediate results
by passing them
finally
if we look at
these computations we directly write
them in these four forms so that we are
performing scalar operations here so the
reason we are writing this low level
numpy is again you know they usually
correspond to low level implementation
that gives you a good sense of what low
level information might look like
of course you know if you are going to
write this mature magazine value
operation using low-level numpy my guess
is that you are going to write in a
slightly different way than we are now
but
let's just keep that in mind and the
first thing i want to confirm is that
i'm going to pause a bit let's look at
the code and let's make sure that you
know when you look at the code you kind
of can understand what's going on here
and this is the implementation of the
measures coefficient around okay
so once we have this reference
implementation in lower level numpy the
next thing that we're going to do is
we're going to well we'll be ready to
introduce uh the main concept today
which is a tense ir program that
implements a similar piece of logic
but before we do that you know we can
still confirm that hey this is the
implementation we we have done correctly
how do we do that one thing we can do so
we can actually allocate a temporal
memory
uh in this case we allocate the
synthetic here
according to the existing implementation
and now have a testing facility that can
assert
these two results are close to each
other so what it does it will compare
each element of the two results and
compare their relative difference so we
have relative tolerance um in one one to
the power of negative five that means
that you know if there is uh
about two elements whose relative
difference are bigger than this
tolerance it will report in there
and uh right now if we run this
it doesn't report an error that means
that yeah we are we it is indeed the low
level uh l
uh low level numpy computation this
particular implementation
kind of matches the original computation
that we did
uh using the
existing numpy array linear algebra okay
so this is indeed like one correct
implementation
now if we look at this particular code
it actually reviews quite a few
interesting elements that's going to
exist in most of the lower level
lower level tensor program abstraction
first of all you can find that there are
explicit multi-dimensional arrays being
passed around
secondly there are loop computations
that drives those that drives the
corresponding array computations and
finally they are from a compute
statement that carries out the
computation of cells okay with this
bearing in mind let's start to introduce
the tensor ir obstruction
so specifically
this code
is a
is what we call a tvm script
implementation it's uh so so this is the
implementation of a of the same
matrix multiplication value operations
in the ignition objection and the
particular language is called tbm script
which is kind of embedded in python that
allows us to be able to play around and
write the code in this way
and this is a tens ir abstraction
used in tbm to implement the
related tensor communications
of course this specific code looks kind
of similar to the
to the low level number code but they
are not exactly the same
so moving next i'm going to
walk step by step on with you on some of
the key elements by comparing
this tbm script implementation and a
lower level numpy information to just
look let's start looking to what are the
elements
of a tensile programming
okay
and to do that uh one thing i'm going to
do is i'm going to put this
evap script implementation on the left
hand side and lower level numpy
implementation on the right hand side so
that we can have a side to side view but
let's not look at correspondence between
the these two functions
first of all um if you look at the
function arguments you'll find that on
the left level right we have
a b and c
and in here we have a b and c as well
and
the the only difference is that in a
tensor ir part um the a b and c are
explicitly annotated as a type called t
dot buffer which is the specific way
intense ir to be able to represent the
multiple dimensional buffer that we're
going to operate on um
that we are going to compute some of the
input output and intermediate result
similarly if you look at you know y dot
empty here a square bond with a white
dot allocate buffer in here and again
this gives us what we call intermediate
tensor buffer that stores intermediate
memory storage so that's the buffer okay
secondly
we can start to look at loops right so
now after looking input arguments let's
start to look at loops
on the right hand side we have four i j
and k
and in here we also have four i j and k
the this t dot grid is just a sugar so
effectively t dot grid
128 108 100 can just expands to these
three forums so it's just a sugar for us
to
easily
express a deeply nasty photos you will
be able to do tdot grid multiple values
that gives you multiple iterators that
effectively expand to the three fours on
the right hand side so there's a direct
response like remember this one and this
loops corresponding to these loops in
here okay so you can find that that's
quite similar right the third
correspondence if you look at the in in
memory
internal computations you'll find that
here's the computation that we do on the
wise body
and this is the computation that we do
on this body there's also direct
correspondence here if i'm holding if
you look at this in it blocking here
uh what it try to say is that in this
particular case why is trying to do a
reduction or to do a sum because we are
trying to do something over the x is k
right and with initialization condition
effectively translated to if it's the
first term
we're going to see
this value in this reduction loop we are
going to initialize the value with zero
and then this particular update loop
corresponds to the same update looping
here
similarly if we look at this c update
it's corresponding to this c update here
okay
so we can draw a lot of parallels
between these tbm script code and the
lower level numpy coding
of course there are certain elements
that exist on
these left hand side in the tbm script
but does not exist on the right hand
side
specifically we have this concept called
block
that is specific to tbm
to tens ir
and there are a few annotations called v
i v j v k
in here
which does not exist in lower level so
next we're going to walk through this
concept because this concept block is
really critical to the 2d tensor
obstruction
so specifically
the vi vj vk are declarations on
off of three iterators so vi
vj vk there are three lines of
declaration here it declares kind of
three kind of information
the first information is that now we are
declaring three variables in here and
we're trying to bind them onto an outer
loop so in this case v i equals t dot x
is spatial i effectively means that i'm
going to assign the value i to vi so
effectively you can also write it as vi
equals i if you just think about the
perspective where what the value value
that you want to bind vi2 similarly in
this case we are going to do just v j
equals j
and v k equals k in this case
okay
so but that that is not too interesting
right because i said we're just trying
to renaming the loop variables so far
second thing that these
vivjbk do
is that it's trying to declare
what we call block access so in this
case
this particular code is within a block
so so
here's the block
that is marked by
t dot block white
and v i b j v k are called block axis
of these corresponding block
uh the the max the possible iterations
that this block is trying to take
so specifically
uh
let's let's
go into that i'm just going to scroll
down
and talk about
this block probably so specifically
this block axis declaration
is going to be
uh in the form of you know block axis
equals t dot x is the axis type so
spatial spatial reduction axis type the
range of the particular axis and mapped
value of a particular axis
okay
so so if you look at the range 128 here
it says that i'm going to you know mine
vj
to
uh to another uh value and
and i'm also going to declare that the
particular vj iterator it's going to be
in the range of 0 to 128
and this is kind of like very useful
information when we're going to check
certain computations for example in
certain cases it could be possible that
we are going to write a long for loop if
i'm going to write for
j from 0 to 120
i'm going to say you know vj equals t
dot x is a spatial 128 j then it's going
to result in the error because you know
on one hand this vg is expecting that
i'm going to receive a iterator that
that's in the range of zero to 128 but
in reality i'm we're going to minus
something so so this kind of additional
information that can be useful to to
declare about the iterator that involved
in the block itself
the most interesting thing is is this
axis properties so the spatial spatial
reduced
these are properties that that declares
about now what's the relation of the
block axis to the computation themselves
so if you look at the particular block
actually the particular block
um
like let's say so we we have a
visualization here and it might be
useful to also
still look at the code so let me try to
still bring up the code again
in this case
so here is the
so so if you look at that look back at
the code right so the code looks like
let's see
so the code looks like this so i'm going
to draw that visualization so that we
can see the code and the visualization
the same way so this is a block y that
we're interested in so this is a block
in this case this block is going to read
from a and b right so i'm going to read
from a
b i
b k
and b
[Music]
b k
b j
this is block y and and this block is
going to write on to
um
y
v i
v j okay
so you can find that
and and there are three iterations that
that that are key to this blocker we
have v i
v j and v k
which corresponds to three what we call
three broad axis
so if you look at this
you can find that you know in order to
compute
a single value let's say i want i'm
interested in computing v
y
0 and 1.
what we need to do is we need to
you know
we need to we need to set
v i equals zero
v j equals one
and i'm going to go through
v k equals zero dot dot to 127
if i run through that
and execute this particular piece of
statement
through this loop then we'll be able to
get y zero one
and similarly if i'm interested in a
different vi and vg we'll be we'll be
able to do that in a similar process
so you'll find that in this particular
case
vi and vj
uh
directly correspond to the
output spatial location which about you
know which are an output
index right of the of the of the matrix
that
that this particular block produces so
in this case
we say you know we are going to write
through the output region of y
and v i and v j directly corresponds the
spatial location that we're interested
in so that's why
v and v g are called spatial axis
on the other hand in order to get the
result we need to reduce over
vk right we need to run through multiple
vks around that particular you know
operations and be able to accumulate all
the results together
and that is why you know vk is called a
reduction axis or reduced axis here
and
what we're interested in seeing is that
you can find that
when we are looking at
this uh block and we actually analyze
hey what does this block tries to do
right we
start to say hey this block
contains three block axis and here's how
we can operate on those three block axis
we never see what is the outside loop
looks like
this because this is the kind of
specific property of this block
access information the idea is that with
the block and block access information
it's already being self-contained about
the computation that the block supposed
to do
and that computation takes multiple
steps and each of the step is
instantiated by a specific choice of a
block axis so i can know the specific
choice of v i equals 0 v j equals 1 v k
equals zero
i go and run this particular statement
that will help me to make progress
towards what we want
and
and those axis properties kind of marks
you know their relations of
kind of marks the relation between the
between the uh block axis and how we
might want to go and execute the
corresponding computation
if
x is spatial it's likely means that that
particular axis and other axis can be
actually arbitrary ordered form i can do
no i can try to compute y 0 1 then i can
compute y
you know say
5 2
by running
by running v i equals 5
v j equals 2 and v k over the
corresponding range and i will be able
to compute that value
and it doesn't matter on you know which
order of v i v j that we're going to
pick
and that's a very nice property which
means that you know we'll be able to
paralyze over some of those v and v j
dimensions
and similarly if you look at going to
look at reduction it's going to be a
different story we cannot trivially
paralyze over reduction dimensions
because we kind of need to store
somewhere temporal result before we
accumulate them together
so this additional information provides
additional these additional block
properties provide additional
information for us to inform us about
you know what kind of transformation
optimization we can do to the
corresponding program
okay
and this
this specific idea of you know being
self-contained is really something that
that supports a lot of our follow-up
transformations we're going to talk
about in a sense that in this particular
case besides the for loop the block
information contains some of the
information about what computation the
iteration that blocks supposed to
execute out so that we'll be able to see
if i'm in this particular case detect
that you know uh in this case i'm
expecting a iterator
in range 0 to 128 but i'm only going to
be getting at uh iterator from 0 to 127
so that will it will result in a size
mismatching
okay
okay so hopefully so far you have to
understand the overall concept of tens
ir and this additional specific concept
about this block construct that we use
in the tbm script
besides declaring this specific axis you
know separately one thing that you might
find is that in a lot of cases
our internal axis do directly correspond
to
the
to the outside loop nets so there are
sugars as well intense i are to allow us
to ride in a shorter channel version so
we could write things like vi video vk
equals accessory map ijk and it is
equivalent to the following form and
here ssr
means the properties of each of the
mapped iterators so the first one is
spatial second one is spatial and third
one is the reduction axis in this case
so you might also find
the same tensile programs in a following
way where you know we're kind of
short circuiting this uh via vj vk
declarations by simply using t dot
accessory map constructing it
okay so i want to know hopefully we have
walked through most of the elements
of these uh tens ir
program
there are few other elements that are
that are relevant and
but
less important than a block concept
the first one is we do have
what we call functional attributes that
try to record additional information
about this particular function a global
thin boil is the name that
we're going to give to the particular
function after we build it
and the other one is about no alias
properties which means that you know the
arrays that we are going to use don't
have overlapped memory and that helps
some of the compiler optimization as
well
if you are not familiar with those
concepts it's totally fine for you to
skip those the most important thing they
want to learn in this part is the
concept of block and block exits and the
types of long axis
and there are also decorators of ir
module and prime function these
decorators tries to mark the types of
these corresponding modules and
functions specifically after we
run this code we'll be able to inspect
the data types that we get out from
those but until uh
we had a my module before and if you do
type my module this is a type ir module
and here ir module is a helper container
that help us to be able to
mark to be able to you know contain a
collection of cancer permittive
functions
and will be also be able to directly
take out one result from the from a
container
by looking at my module this function
name is mm relu and this is a type
called print function
and this corresponds to
the it stands for permittive cancer
function here
so the kind of idea is that we'll be
able to construct
using tbm script uh ir module
that's going to contain
uh different functions right for example
right now this only contains mm
relu function here
but there are certain instances of ir
module that contains more than one
uh tensor permitted tensor functions for
example you know this is a particular
example that of our module that contains
two tensor program functions the first
one being a measured simplification a
second one being a value function
and we'll also be able to you know
look at those two functions separately
so firewall will be able to do things
like
my module
with two functions
and in this case i can pick out
mn function
and if you look at type of that
it's going to give us
a prime function here
and the value is another function that
is contained within this ion module okay
so up until now just do a quick
checkpoint upon now we have learned
one specific instance of tensor program
abstraction which is called tens ir
that contains some of the key elements
in here so the key elements
include
uh include sayings like
multi-dimensional buffer declaration
which
is in here and here
there are four loops that allows us to
express
the for loops that goes over iterations
most importantly we have
blocks concept of blocks that try to
encapsulate
uh as a part of computation that's
that's to be carried out in certain form
of loops
and additionally there are block axis
properties
that marks the range and the relations
of those block axis
with respect to the computation we're
going to perform
and those block access properties are
going to be helpful for us in some of
the
later transformations we're going to
introduce very soon
and so this is a status checkpoint at
this point i would recommend us to you
know do a recap this uh lecture this
lecture i passive notebook results will
be available online so you will also you
are also more than welcome to go and
check out and try out those concepts and
see if we can really understand the
concept of blocks and other things so
our goal here is by now it's just to be
able to
take a tensile and be able to read the
particular code and understand what's
really going on
okay so hopefully
now we've learned what tensor looks like
now let's start to do something fun
let's start to say you know
let's take a tens of our module and say
you know if we can go and try to change
it in some way and as we mentioned in
earlier part of mlc lecture
the main theme of mlc process is ability
to be able to take existing
collection of tensor function and
transform them onto something equivalent
that hopefully be more optimized
you want to even ground that in the
context of ksir the idea is can we be we
will be able to take our module
like this one
and try to you know transform it to
another another different
ir modules
where where you know some of the
functions get changed okay so let's do
that now
before we do that again one thing to
help explanations let's come back to a
lower level numpy implementation again
so in the beginning we talked about you
know hey it will be really nice to be
able to
implement um
to
it would be really nice to implement
some low level details and trying to
show to ourselves you know what low
level looks like and we do that through
a low level number
but the initial implementation of a
lower level downtime may not be the
implementation that you might expect so
here we're going to
do another slightly different variations
of measures of multiplication using
lower level numpy
and
to to show you that there is indeed the
matrix modulation code you will be able
to we we did run it here
and validate that hey this is indeed a
crack okay
so we'll compare this code and the other
code you'll find that there's only two
different things here
specifically
you'll find that internal loop
computations remains the same right
we're still going to do this loop
computations the only difference is how
how we're going to iterate over j in
here
specifically you can find that we are
splitting these j's iterations onto
outer loop j0 and in the loop j1
and if you look at j0 and j1 you'll find
that it will compose them together it
still covers all the js right if i'm
here if i have
j0 equals
equals 0
and uh
j1 equals one
j0 equals one
sorry zero here j1 equals
um
let me let's do it again so imagine that
we have you know j0
j1
if we do 0 1 0 2 0
3 0 4 and
no
there's no falling here it should be
let's see
it should be
uh
again
j0 j1 if you do 0 0 0 1
0 2
0 3
1 0 okay gotcha that's right and if you
look at the corresponding value of j
you'll find it it's going to be zero one
two three four and etc so so so you can
find that actually you know if we are
going to iterate over j j0 and j1 it's
going to get you the same sequence of j
values except that the order of
iteration is different so that we are
iterating k and then j1 here
but
the the iteration still covers all the
possible iterations we are going to have
and this view gives you the matrix
right matrix multiplication result
i'm going to pause a bit and since it's
kind of
less trivial to be able to
get it
if you try to do it in the first place
but you know let's pause a bit and see
if you can understand that this is
exactly another implementation of major
supplication
okay
and
our question is you know can we
take the original uh my module tensile
function that's implemented in original
form and somehow transform it onto onto
something that resembles this v2 of
lower level numpy implementation
um so in order to do that what we are
going to do
of course one way is we can again write
a similar implementation in tbm script
right but we're not going to do that in
here what we're going to do is we're
going to take the code and try to
directly use some pragmatic
transformation api to transform the code
onto the new form
so before we do that i'm going to
define our three function you don't need
to understand this function so this is
mainly for us to be able to print out
the code during intermediate stage and
what it does it turns
code into a high version that we can get
on html
so to give you example what we can do
here is we can call
uh my script my module.script
that will turn it on to the string form
and i'm going to turn pass into code to
html onto html form and we can use the
html form
so
um let's
let's try to
so first of all we can see let's let's
first see you know what that what does
my module
the script look like
if you're playing now you can find it
just a plain script right and then the
only thing that the that the code html
does is go to use a tool called picture
manual highlight so if you go and run it
it gives you a slightly nice nicer
version that's highlighted
and this is the original code that we
had in my module okay
so what we're going to do next we're
going to go and try to transform this
code
uh specifically what i'm going to do
here is i'm going to
create a r3 class called schedule
that allows us to take in my module as
input
and this is a schedule class that will
help us to go and transform
the the corresponding values
uh the corresponding functions and my
module so in order to do that the first
thing we are going to do is we are going
to try to
grab out
the
want to grab out the corresponding block
and their loop values
so to do that what i what i need to do
here
is i am going to write
i'm going to write block y equals
schedule dot get blocks
y that's going to give me the the
loop the block here specifically this is
going to give me
um this block
and then i'm going to try to get loops
that's around that block in this case i
j k
so the next step i'm going to do i
i'm going to do
i
i j and k
equal schedule
dot
get loops
of this block
why
and this is going to mean it's going to
give us the the loops
that we have here okay
see
okay so this case we need to also supply
the
original
functioning here because there can be
multiple functions and
we're going to get that one
and then once we get this what we can do
is we can start to transform this box
okay so what we can do is do what we
call split
and j factors
equals
and 4
and this is going to split the loop onto
j0 and j1
and by the way at any time point we'll
be able to look at the the result of the
transformation so this result is on
schedule.mode
we know that we can use script to turn
that into a script
and then do
let me just copy paste something
here
so
i will
copy
and i will be able to do
schedule.mode.script
and you will be able to see the program
after the first type of transformation
so you'll find that after the first step
of transformation
the program changes right you instead of
j here is j zero j y in here
and the relation being j zero times four
plus three one equals j one thing that
you can find quite interesting here is
that after we do the transformation it's
actually much easier to introduce the vj
vg vi region vk
because you know the it'll help us to
indicate the relations between the
transform loop and the original loop i
expect right so v i v j v k is already
also always the original loop that we're
expecting and the j zero j y are the
loops that are being
transformed in this case
another thing that you might notice is
that there are additional information
here like reads and writes this will
indeed this is the additional
information generated by the blocks to
indicate you know what are the regions
that we're going to read and write onto
and these are going to be helpful in our
transformation as well
okay
so i'm going to i'm not going to type
the following step transformation but
instead i'm going to use predefined code
but hopefully you'll get idea of this
kind of interactive way of doing
transformations
the next step after we do the split
is going to be
reordering the loops so that the j0 can
sit in the intermediate part
and after reordering
you can find that the loops are in order
g zero k j one
and the loop are in order here and we
can compare that to the previous version
uh
in this case the previous version
shows that a different group order right
so after this loop transformation we are
getting a new
new new uh tensile module that contains
a different viewport and this is kind of
a desired loop order that we are looking
at
if you look at this particular program
right now you'll find that actually it
closely resembles
these uh numpy
value v2
and
what i can do is i can try to copy the
other implementation here and we can try
to do a contrast comparison
of the two
so
if you
you'll find that this is our
expected code and
and then here's a lower level numpy
locators you'll find that order being
i 0 j k j 1 and then here i 0 j 0 k j 1
and
this and there's a direct correspondence
of this assignment and this one and so
on
so one amazing thing here that you can
find is that
you know up until now we have not
write these new programs from scratch
instead we are using a programmatic api
to take the original program and
transform that onto this new form and
this is really something that
that is you know exciting about the
pencil level program obstructions and a
lot that is enabled by the additional
information provided by the by the block
axis and block annotation so so that's
kind of one motivation on why you know
there's this concept of blocks because
they provide additional information that
help us to do this kind of pragmatic
transformations
so this is kind of one variant
we can also continue to transform this
code further to get a different variant
of the program
so
specifically what we're going to do is
we're going to
first of all take this program and one
thing that we notice is that you know
this block c loop
is kind of like a very outside
of this communication and one thing that
we we normally do is you know what if we
just try to put the c computation in
here in somewhere in here where you know
right after we we compute the
corresponding value of y let's go ahead
and compute the corresponding value of c
as well
so what we can do is we can do that
through a royal compute at
uh permit what it does is we'll try to
take the block c
in here
and then
it will say you know i'm going to try to
place it
inserted in in you know after
and after the g0 computation so the
final volume will look like for j for i
j 0 and then the computation of c will
be inserting there okay so let's go and
try and print and do it and print out
and you'll find that in this case
you can find that this is the sales
computation it's already sits under a j0
in here
and you know of course we are still
going to do a reduction that produces
four elements
of y and we're going to do another loop
of four elements that's computer
corresponding c values in here and
here's t dot zero is just
another abbreviation for t dot range so
it's called a serial loop that we're
going to execute in a low level code
okay
and finally
one thing that you might notice so far
is you know during transformations we
always keep the reduction initialization
together in this in this particular
block y
it does not have to be the case actually
in real implementations most of the
cases will try to initialize the y
matrix separately
and in practice actually when we build
the corresponding test our code we also
try to do a transformation that split
out this initialization the reason we
want to keep the initialization here
during transformation is you know during
transformations actually it's helpful to
keep the initialization together with
reduction because a lot of cases they
need to be transformed uh together for
example uh when when we are doing this j
split uh we also kind of need to split
the j on the initialization block and
place them accordingly as well
so one thing we can do is we do we can
actually try to
explicitly get that out and this is
called decomposed reduction
and
what we need to do is we want to first
get block y
in here
and
we're going to do block y equals
equal schedule dot
get block
y
matrix multiplication value
and we can call decompose reduction
to be able to
and then we call decompose reduction and
after that you will find that
you know this
initialization block
is generated separately and there's the
update block that only do the reduction
update okay
so actually this is done automatically
in most of the test ir when we try to go
and really build them so you don't have
to do this but this is a step for us to
explicitly do this and in case you know
we want to do some further operations
among
okay
and actually this final transformed code
corresponds to another lower level numpy
coding here
the roughly have you know seeing here
initialization update block
always in this author and
and
you know this is another thing that we
can go and run and we can validate hey
this does creates more into the real
result okay
so so far in this particular section we
will talk about as we talk about
the
incremental transformations of of tens
ir functions and our modules
specifically and the main takeaway is
now we are going to use the
tesla schedule that help us to be able
to incrementally change the loop
ordering and other other properties of
the things
what very important thing is we don't
have to
we don't have to recreate different
variants of a program right in the case
of a lower level numpy we kind of have
to write
uh variant zero varying one variance
three
being the lower level numpy each of the
term
of course in certain cases i can go and
copy paste and edit them
but still
having this ability to do that from a
program point of view gives us a door
for more further automatic optimizations
because then in official lectures will
have programs to go and guess about what
possible transformations that they might
want to do and some of the transmissions
can lead to better performance so the
high level takeaway message here is that
no we will be able to use some of the
scheduling parameters to do pragmatic
program-based transformations
of the corresponding tensor program
okay
so far we have talked about tens irs and
we have only show
the the output text format like this
right but we have never go and actually
try and run it uh we we did run the
lower level number code so for a given
tensor program we will be able to build
it and run it the way you do that is you
call a tvm build function supplying the
ir module that contains a description of
the original program
and a target and here target describes
you know what is a deployment
environment we are interested in
the llvm means that we're going to use
lvm to compare to a local cpu in this
case this is what we're interested in in
certain later lectures we might
introduce other targets that
that are other than you know the simple
cpu type
in order to run it we will need to
create a new arrays in this case there
are specific tvm on the arrays that we
can create to hold the temporal result
you can you can try to create an array
by copy data from a numpy b numpy and
this is the output and the array that
we're going to hold the result
so once we do the function this library
will contain
a collection of random functions and we
can grab them by the key by the original
function name actually it's the global
symbol name that we have in there
and then we can write using the chris
volunteer if you write you can find a
actually no there's no messages that
means that this assert or close passes
is in available dot mode
and if you build and run that
it's a correct implementation
and the last thing we can do is you know
let's try to compare you know how fast
they run and if you try to compare one
variable information another
uh
on one hand it seems that they are just
changing the order of loops right why
would they correspond to different
performance a different code that runs
that have different performance but
let's try to find out
so the term evaluator corresponds to
a tool that helps us to evaluate the
invocations of of a certain function
and
we're going to run this code
and it shows that the common course of
running original module and this mod you
can run there's almost more than
five times difference between these two
which is kind of like a non-trivial
difference so so actually the
transformed schedule indeed brings
better performance in here
and you know do you know why it is the
case
so so in order to analyze the why let's
take a look at first the tool code again
so this is original code
before transformation
and this is the code
after transformation
your point the only difference in here
is how we compute iterate over j right
so so in the particular case of the of
the codon below we are trying to split
the j onto two parts and we're also
reordering the order of j with respect
to k
and this creates a different kind of
memory access patterns when we try and
access a b
and one and why memory access factor
matters
when we're trying to read things like
um b
bi
v j
the term cost is not caused in most of
the modern mach modern
architectures
so as a matter of fact modern cpus have
different levels of cache hierarchy so
in order to read something here the data
have to be first fetched onto l2 cache
and l1 cache and finally to the
registers
and there are different latencies when
we're accessing them
if my data already sits in l1 cache you
only need 0.5 nanoseconds to access the
data
evenly existing l2 caching into fashion
to l1 cache is much longer term
and if you only assist assisting the
main memories cost me more than 200
times slower compared to fetching the
data on a catch
of course then the the key takeaways
maybe we want all the data in the cache
unfortunately that's not possible
because all the cpu cash have a very
limited sex like l1 cash typically only
have 32 kilobytes or 64 kilobytes
as a result
the strategy that most of the modern
power takes is to try to
fetch the data that you already visited
the fresh data closed by so finally if i
already visited uh a data here and
there's a data close file likely
this entire what we call cache line is
going to be fetched onto the cache so if
you visit this one next time if you're
going to visit something next to it it's
already on the l1 cache okay
so with this in mind let's start to
analyze the loop patterns
that the particular loop have
specifically we are only going to look
at the innermost loop so the innermost
loop contains a k loop that does
reduction and j1 loop that iterates over
some of the values
and if you look at these two loops you
will find that you know
when iterator over k loops is going to
iterate in this way and this way
and j1 it trades over
a certain
stripe right in this case right we are
computing uh a stripe
this in our case the j1 size is four so
we are computing a stripe of four
elements of y
uh for a given k and a different value
of j
we're also going to iterate over
different stripes of j of being here and
one interesting thing you can find is
that by having this strike access
uh if the g1 size is four
then
then you know in the innermost loop
first of all i'm going to visit
i'm going to visit this element right
of j1
and this element of y
and next time i'm going to visit
something next to it
and because of the caching behavior the
next element is already in the cache as
a result you know it will run much
faster
then you know imagine that in the
original program actually can be viewed
as
this j1 size equals one so effectively
that's only one choice and j1 have to
equal zero so so first of all i'm going
to visit this particular element one
element
we are in a more original program case
next time i'm going to move k to the
next location so i have to visit the
next one although it seems that these
two are close to each other they are not
right because
in the memory we are going to lay it out
in this low major fashion so the
distance between this element this
element
is
128 which is which is you know
much larger than
uh a close neighbor
so that's the high-level idea of why you
know changing loop order can affect the
performance after lecture you're more
than welcome to you know do a more
detailed analysis this certainly only
one factor but one takeaway is that that
single factor is already important and
it's really important for us to be able
to explore
those loop ordering and other choices to
get a good performing
performing code
and as an exercise actually we have a
example called here that allows you to
change different j factors and see what
is the running time and that you should
go and play with it to say and feel free
to also play with other transformation
to say if you can get better performing
coding here
so we have talked about the
tensiles and
and
and you know the ways to transform it
uh in this part um we are going to also
talk about you know how can we create
those tensor ir functions right of
course the first way to create lens we
can just write tbm script directly
and there are sugars that we provide to
writing this is one common way actually
it's very common way for us to do quick
development in machine learning
compilation process we are trying to
target a
certain workload of interest
so in practice you know um a lot of
cases we may not directly write tens out
code but we want to be able to
automatically generate lens from some of
a high level source
and there are also tools in tbm and
related infrastructure to help us do
that but
here's one specific instance of domestic
language called tensor expression that
help us to be able to construct some of
these computations of our interest link
using this api and then convert them
onto a tensile function
so in this case what we're going to do
is we're going to declare
a two of the input called placeholder
and then we're going to do what we call
t.compute that describes the computation
and the way it works said you know when
we call t.compute
uh it specifically specifies a lambda
function that that specifies you know
you want to compute each element of y i
j how we're going to compute it and
this code hopefully itself apparent and
you know it
it tries to compute this particular
matrix multiplication formula in here
and after we describe the sequence of
computations what we can do is we can
use a t dot create prime function
supplying the arguments
of the of the tensor function we're
interested in and we can create that uh
function here
so so here if we create it you'll find
that we're getting the same programs as
the manual written cancer program
so in a lot of cases in a high level it
could be possible that you know we we're
looking at uh some of these tensor
expressions and we'll be able to use
these domains based language as a tool
for us to convert them onto the tensori
abstractions then further do some
transformations on top of them
finally because in our case we emphasize
a lot on the ability of to be able to
transform between these tens our
programs as a result you can also get
hands-on functions as a result of
transformations for example in the
future we will talk about
possibilities of fusing two permittive
tensor functions together
that will give us a new tensor primitive
function
and
then we can take that tensile function
and do some transformation later so
there are different ways to obtain and
get those cancer functions
but a high level take away is that you
know we want to be able to
obtain those tests our function
different ways
doing interactive transformation among
them to get better performance in the
future we're also going to talk about
how do we build automated system to do
those transformation
okay so we're getting close to this
lecture there's a lot of content but
hopefully you enjoy so far
uh
so so far if you look at um today we
have learned about hence ir the high
level obstructions and hopefully a
concept of tn script and how do you use
that to describe these loopy
computations with for tanzania algebras
and one of the key takeaway i want us to
get at is is the overall process of
development if you look at traditional
low level numpy development that we have
you can find this kind of a repeat
of this process where i'm going to go
and develop different variable programs
like b0 v1 v2 and then i'm going to run
them to
in in initial case and this is kind of a
traditional form of development
that we're doing most of engineering
on the other hand if you look at the
tens ir development and
this kind of resembles what a machine
learning compilation process should look
like
the idea is that we're going to have
some development again either
through you know ingesting creation
or automatic generation to get some
formal program
in a data structure called ir module
then we're going to run certain
transformations
that help us to do transformations like
loop reordering
trying to you know uh making things
closer
trying to fuse operator together and so
on there's some transformation that gets
us a different variant of program
and then we'll be able to
call build function is a compile
language that gets a deployment
the key in here is that when we talk
about in the first lecture as well
machine learning compilation the key of
machine compilation is the ability to be
able to not only you know take a program
but also be able to transform among
different tensor program functions so
that we can get more optimized version
and this kind of programming model and
program paradise is you know while we're
going to advocating i'm going to come
back again again in future lectures
of course the direct code development is
still very important in a lot of cases
it's still very helpful to develop
library functions and combine that with
some of the transformation-based
approaches and we're also going to talk
about how we combine those two practices
in the future chapters as well
so that's the end of today's lecture and
here's a summary the notebook will be
available and there will also be
exercises for you to go and try out and
hopefully you enjoy a lecture and
and in the next lecture we are going to
talk about how we are going to combine
some of the basic tensor parameter
function together to form end-to-end
neural networks thank you folks and i
will see you folks next week