Last time we were talking about the core
design, right? The CPU core design. Now
we start from the very basic the single
stage core design. Then the key point is
to introduce what are the key components
in a core and how the instruction can be
executed step by step. Um so as a review
this is the
uh the single stage pipeline design.
Let's consider that we want to complete
all these tasks in one cycle time. Now
we start with a PC and PC is the pointer
to the next instruction to execute right
then we put into a instruction memory
and this the instruction memory will
give us the instruction that we want to
execute. Then we split the wires. Then
we fetch 32 instruction 32bit
instructions. Now we feed into different
locations. Let's ignore the control
units for now. Look at the registers.
Now we put a source and destination into
the source register ID and the
destination register ID into the
register file. The input part the input
where's my pointer the input part of our
point of our uh register file. Then
after some time it will just generate
the output for us. Then we can read the
result and this result will be feed into
the alou and there are other some there
are some other data paths for example
sign extension
um we can do not we can skip it this at
this point we talk about why it's useful
it's mainly for calculating addresses or
can consider immediate values but if we
don't consider this part the most
important data path is from the data
uh register data and one and register
data two and this data are fed into the
AOU unit. The AOU unit will do the
calculation. The result will be sent
onto this bus, right? Then this bus will
eventually write into the result either
read the result from the data memory or
write the result into the data memory,
right? So uh so here we can if we are
calculating address then this alou will
feed the address into the data memory
otherwise if we're calculating a value
and go back directly to the result side
then this result will eventually go back
to the right data bus right then this A3
if you consider this A3 has been ready
for quite some time like when we read
the instruction we immediately know the
A3 register but the right data can wait
for a little while until our data is or
result is available. Then we write back
to the register file we get the result
updated.
So uh for one cycle design single cycle
design this is not a problem because
everything can wait and then we only do
this right we only consider this whole
instruction to be completed after the
instru the cycle ends. Um but as you can
see the problem of this design is since
we want to try to do everything in one
cycle this one cycle time needs to be
really really long. Okay then we come up
with this design now um
by before going forward now we have this
control unit. This control unit decide
generates control signals from the
instruction right instruction is only
our only source of truth. Then we gener
we use this instruction information to
generate a control logic and this
control logic controls mainly
multiplexers and au unit. Then you can
consider this is also a multiplexer that
they control which unit is actually
generating the result and this
multiplexer right and also there is
another multiplexer. So this control
signals controls some enable signals
enable signals and some multiplexers to
decide how the whole thing works that
can perform operations of different
different instructions.
Right? So uh another design that we
consider here is the multi- stage
design. So the key point of multi-stage
design is we want to add the add
registers and we put a register there so
that this register can temporarily lock
the data so that we can use in some
later cycles.
For example the instructions is here. So
it locks the this part of the the A1 and
A2 register selection. It also locks A3
register selection. Right? So when we
get the result back, we get the result
back.
Um
yeah, when we get this result back, it
goes back here. Then it goes back from
there's another just wire a connection
goes up from here from the result side.
Now when we have this result back, we
still have the instruction ready. So we
still have 11 to 7 7 to 11 as the
destination register selector. So we
have A3 there. Then even after a few
cycles these two data path is these two
data sources can meet at this point. So
that at this point we can write into the
data. Okay. In this way this control
unit is basically still the same thing.
We have ops funk 3 funk 7 as the input.
Then we generate other control signals.
But this time this control signal is no
longer a combination logic that we
cannot simply just use this input and
generate output. But we need to consider
at which cycle we generate what control
signals. Okay. So it's a multicycle
process.
Then we consider how this control unit
is designed basically by considering a
state machine. Right? This state machine
always start with fetch. Then we go with
decode. Now we call it decode. But other
than decode we also read from the
register file. Then after the decode we
do execution for different type of
instructions.
Then we do memory operations. The memory
read memory write operations. Then if uh
if you consider BEQ the branch
instruction, we can also consider this
as a execution stage. Right? Then
eventually we do the memory write back
and alo write back. It just writes back
from different
um data sources. But eventually what we
want to do at this stage is to write the
result back in the register so that
result can be used in the next
instructions. So write back have S4 and
S7 as write back operations. Right? So
this is a multicycle process. Then the
simplest path is fetch then
decode BQ.
Then that's it right three cycles. The
longest pass is fetch decode memory
addressing memory read and memory
rightback. So five stages. Okay. So it
takes three to five st cycles to
complete one instruction.
So we did a performance analysis. Now
our execution time can be simplified as
the number of instructions. The cycle
the second per cycle or we say this is
frequency right on the other side we
have cycle per instruction. This is CPI.
Then CPI is the metrics that we describe
how efficient this core is. Then using
these three parameters we can roughly
estimate the performance of a core. And
in single stage core design we cannot
change the instructions. We're not
designing software. We're not designing
compiler. We're designing micro
architecture at this state and even our
ISA is fixed right. So our instructions
must stay the same. Then cycle second
per cycle is the frequency in single
stage core design because we try to do
so many things in one cycle. Our
frequency cannot be so high. We or cy or
cycles or period has to be longer. So we
have longer cycle time longer period.
Yeah. But we have one CPI. So that means
we only need one cycle to perform to
complete one instruction or one CPI is
also equals to one IPC one instruction
per cycle. Right? So that describes the
throughput. That's a very ideal
throughput. Now if you consider
multi-stage core design, it takes the
same number of instructions. It takes
shorter number of cycles because we only
do a little bit small task in every
cycle. But it takes 3 to five cycle per
instruction. If you convert 3 to 5 CPI
to IPC, that's basically 0.2 to 0.33
IPC, right? That's the number that's the
throughput. We want the IPC to be the
higher the better. So as you can
probably guess here now definitely we
can control them together. Then ideal
case we can have still have shorter
cycle time and still have one CPI or one
IPC. How we can do that? you almost know
the result. Then in GPUs, we also have
seen that the cores actually runs in a
pipeline style, right? So different
instructions can process different
things at the same at the same time. Now
in when we talk about GPU part we also
talk about this intrinsic conflict and
human standing human understanding or
how we write assembly code we always
assume that executed in a serial mode so
that we execute one instruction after
another one instruction after another we
write add subtract or branch then we
have to execute
add subtract branch we cannot reorder
them right but machine execution or
hardware execution is works in different
ways. There are so many register and so
many groups of control uh combination
logic. Combinational logics all execute
in parallel right so we want them to
execute in parallel so that we can use
we can get the highest performance. So
how we can solve this problem and GPU
takes a way of using
uh thread level parism and CPU uses the
different way CPU uses instruction level
parism. And what is thread level
paradism or data level parism is we
execute different threads or different
part of the data at the same time.
Instruction parallelism that means we
don't really have the choice of multiple
data and we only have a single piece of
data and everything we want to execute
in a serialized way but how we can
execute them in parallel that means we
can execute instructions in parallel. So
you may then you may feel it's much more
natural in the GPU way right in the GPU
way that data parallel data can be
processed in parallel it's almost very
it's just natural it's embarrassingly
parallel programs like vector add
program or matrix modification it's very
natural process then there's no
dependency then so here is just less
natural then for instructions
the instruction are executed in a way
that is just one after another. Then you
get a result of register three then you
will use register three in the next
instruction. So we have to find
opportunities in these instructions and
see how they can execute in parallel.
That's the whole purpose of the general
CPU design. Okay. So CPU tries to use
instruction level parism and CPU tries
to minimize latency. GPU tries to
maximize the throughput. that's their
design philosophy to be different.
So just on another on a side note then
if you consider data parallel then since
there's no restriction in the number of
thread that we can execute in parallel
the only restriction is how large your
die size is how many compute unit how
many aou unit how many lanes are there
in a GPU that's only that's your
limitation but so for CPUs what's your
limitation it's your program right just
consider how many instruction that you
can execute in parallel if you have a
zero single threaded program probably
like five to seven five to 10
instructions
at the most like 20 instructions that we
can execute in parallel without any
dependency then so the opportunity for
CPU to execute in parallel is much
rare and much harder to find okay that's
why you consider CPU performance is not
as high as GPU although there are like
some blending of CPU and GPU that they
borrow ideas from each other. So today
CPU is like after adding a vector
instruction is not a pure um data uh
pure instruction level paradigm
execution engine but we stay with the
simple model. Okay. Then we look at this
design as we analyze that we can clearly
see the stages like the fetch stage the
decode stage and execute stage memory
stage and the rightback stage. Right? So
we can reddraw this figure in this way.
We have the first stage as fetch, the
second stage as decode, then these
stages as execute, then memory stage and
write back stage. So I'm now writing the
back arrow to the fetch state. Once
we're done with the last stage, we go
back to the fetch state. We can execute
next instruction.
So we can also map the circuit, which
part of circuit to each stage, right?
We're already drawing that with that
hint. So here in the five stage what do
we do? We start with a PC right remember
when we talk about every stage we start
with a register structural register we
end with a structural register. So we
start with the PC register then we end
with the this instruction holding
registers
right this is the fetch stage and the
decode stage we started with the
instruction holding registers then we
need to go through the register file
then we get into the this op gathering
registers or the register result
register value registers right it's a
register for the register values
So we start from there and end with this
part. And for XQ stage is basically here
we start with the register holding
registers to the post ALOU registers.
Right? Then the memory stage goes back
to there because we write the memory we
we have only one memory unit for both
the instruction and memory uh the the
memory operations. So we start from this
alou out register. This alou register
may have the address that is calculated
right. So it goes from here to there
right but on the other side if you
consider if we don't really need these
memory registers then we can skip if we
don't need this memory stages we can
skip them. we can directly have this
data have this result to go back to the
uh register right the WD3 port right so
we can in theory we can skip this stage
but if you consider if you want to
design in a pipeline way then basically
we cannot skip this stage we have to
even we don't do anything because some
instruction require this stage other
instruction have to even just wait a
little bit they have to do this stage
but just simply doesn't do anything.
Right? In pipeline design we need a
balanced design. So every stage takes
amount of the same the about the same uh
duration. Then every instruction needs
to go through the same stages.
Then eventually we consider the memory
right back or commit stage. Then it
starts with this data register. Then it
ends with this register file. You can
consider it ends with this register or
you can consider end with the register
file. So this is a relatively light
stage.
Okay. So clearly we have this five stage
design. So we need to slightly modify
our
circuit design to see how this is
possible, how we can enable this.
Okay. So
yeah one point before this. If we
execute in a smartest cycle way then we
can execute this thing like fetch decode
execute memory read write and write
register. Now once we are done with the
first instruction we start with the
second instruction. So either in a multi
multi-stage way multicycle way or in a
single cycle way pretty much we draw the
same type of um timeline figure right
then uh CPU we can use instruction level
parad instruction to execute in parallel
so what we do here is we can pipeline
them pipeline them in a way that when
we're doing decode and write to read we
do fetch instruction
fetch the second instruction. Then we
fetch the third instruction. Then we
compact them together. And we're doing
execute. We do decode for a second
instruction. We do fetch for the third
instruction. And just compare these two
figures. It's a good example. Now here
we can finish the third instruction
basically around the same time. But on
the top on top we only finish the two
instructions. Right? On the bottom we
have three instructions completed. So
our throughput
can increase.
So this is another way of describing
the instruction pipelines a simplified
way. Now remember every stage need to be
separated by registers right. So we
simply go with uh
instruction memory stage. you just call
it instruction memory stage or fetch
stage doesn't matter I im stage right
then we do the instruction memory
suppose this is load instruction then we
put data onto a group of registers now
we go to the register file reg uh
register file stage now why this is
drawn as half gray region is basically
is enabled in the second half of the
cycle so the remember the register file
if we have a register at here another
register here and we want to finish from
the instruction to the register data
register in one cycle. What we can do is
we want this register file to be
triggered by a down edge. Okay, in that
case we write data
we read the data in the second half of
this cycle.
Then we go through the alou stage,
right? Then we go to the data memory
stage. Then we go to the register file
stage. Register file again for writing
the data result. Then look at here. If
we're doing this register file stage
here, then we can do uh we can fetch the
instruction fetch the second
instruction.
Then it's a natural pipeline, right? So
for some of them like the data memory
stage
other than the load and store we
actually don't really need the
we actually don't need the data memory
stage right but still because we want
every instruction to flow through the
same pipeline even they don't need the
stage they probably need an extra delay
they need an extra delay so that we can
have a smooth pipeline execution Just
move forward. Move forward. Right. So
okay.
So this is a high level description is a
mid midle description of how these
things works and how registers works in
between. The register can hold the
result so that we can consider
everything between these registers are
combinational logic. So that we can pass
we can pass the data from one register
to another register in one cycle time.
Right? And the key point is one
structure like a register file. This is
register file for the reading part. This
is register file for the writing part.
Right? For this part
um there you can still consider them as
two different part of the register the
logic. So in this case we can consider
that we uh
we can consider every component is only
used once in a single cycle right just
look at cycle four for example data
memory plus
regular file read and instruction fetch
right or here cycle five
of them or all of all five of them are
being utilized at this cycle time right.
So the idea is in one cycle in in every
cycle every com every component is being
utilized and one component is only being
utilized at once then we can achieve the
highest performance the highest
utilization for hardware and utilization
is a very important word in computer
architecture is because if we have the
resources we want to use it we want to
put it to utilization
okay so what we need to change in this
design. Now we start with we go back to
the single stage design. It's easier
because we have the instruction memory
and data memory separated. Okay, it's
easier otherwise just uh
it's very annoying because they can have
conflict because you can either read the
data or read the the instruction. So we
go back to the single stage. What we do
is basically we consider which part of
the which part of the
uh circuit belongs to which stage. Then
what we simply do here is to add
registers to log them in between.
Okay,
we have registers logging them in
between. We just draw this cycle
boundary registers.
So
it's basically the same as multi-stage
design. So this register holds either
the PC because we need to calculate the
PC value here then or the uh instruction
that is read from the instruction
memory. Then the result is written here.
But every wire that passes through here
even just look at this wire this PC
because we need to calculate PC right we
need to do a calculation for the PC we
cannot let it to directly go to this
point because sign extension may take
some time may take a cycle we want them
to arrive at this stage at the same time
so that these two sources going into
this plus operator this plus aou at the
same time. So we need this register to
split them. Just consider even this wire
is only connecting these two registers
together. It just serve as a delay
purposes. Then we delay it for one cycle
so that two different data path arriving
at one point they can arrive at the same
time.
Um it's the same it's the this is the op
gathering registers and this is the
result registers the
after the data memory this another set
of register then eventually in the
commit stage then we write the data back
then still remember when we talk about
the the problem in the multi-stage
design we have this stage that this A3
will arrive at this point much earlier
than data data um
then right
so what we can do is we need to add a
manual delay
let's compare these two so cycle one we
read the instruction cycle two we
already have the A3 ready
but in which cycle we can have WD3 ready
that's the fifth the fifth cycle
the fifth stage. So
it's the only we can only let the early
one to wait for the later one. We cannot
make the later one to come earlier.
Right? So what we can do is we
intentionally delay this A3.
Then we put this wire just let it to go
through a loop. Delay delay delay and go
back to A3. Then it arrived at the same
time with the WD. If you consider the WD
where it comes, it comes from this RD1.
Then we calculate address. We do the
data memory. Hopefully it can finish in
one cycle then wait for another cycle.
So it waited for
uh
one, two, three cycles then go back to
WB3. They both waited for three cycles
then they turn back to the register file
and they can write it to the register
file. Okay, still I don't want to go too
deep into the circuit level design and
this is probably the last point last
time we see this level of circuit
drawing but I think that's very
important. uh something I want to share
is when I was a PhD student I started I
I I didn't start from computer
architecture I don't know anything about
computer architecture when I start to
study computer architecture I don't even
know which is load and store so then I
started to do research and then
everything I just try to figure it out
myself so I don't know how this five
stage pipeline were designed I only know
the high level architecture like I know
all five stage that uh something similar
to
something similar to this or even later
it's like we only draw the stage names
in a diagram then only when I start to
teach the digital design course I start
to know oh this multi-stage design are
implement in this way right then
registers are holding the holding the
values between the cycle boundaries
is it really useful then do I have to
know these things for complex research
then strictly speaking no you don't have
to know you just know the like how the
pipeline works it's good enough but
still
uh once I know this I just feel much
more comfortable doing research on this
pipeline stage um research that
I feel I know the fundamentals right so
consider if you know this then if you
know how register file internally works
and flip-flops right then how some
extent ion or how multiplexer works or
how a adder works then they are
combination logic no problem then
although you don't know the what gates
are there you know it's possible to
design that it's nothing special but
gates lots of gates and so I want to
just let you feel comfortable when we
talk about
instruction pipelines multi-stage
pipelines then you know oh step by step
how we can drill into the bottom. Then
if you are architects, if you're a
manager, then you can split the work to
groups. Then you basically know how to
have different group of people to work
on different part of the circuit. That's
good enough. Yeah.
Um I I have to say that's a very good
question is this actually used and I my
my general idea this is a classic
textbook pipeline design. So um
if you you say oh I have risk five ISA I
want to design a a circuit I want to
design a core. So what should you do
now? You probably should start with a
single stage right then consider a
three- stage. If three stage what are
the three stages
um instruction load register file is
probably one stage then alou data memory
is another stage then right back is
another stage then it's really up to you
and I know there are like lowlevel cores
there are risk five course or
three-stage design then if you go up one
level you want to go with the five stage
design then if you consider if you work
in a company like Intel or Apple what
they do is they probably have more than
20 stages. Um, so it's much much much
more complex than this design. Okay. So
I would say this is a
textbook example then not auto course
uses this design.
So five stage design is at most what is
used in Apple uh efficient core the low
power core. The performance core is
definitely much much deeper and much
much more complex there
core one
right so one core one pipeline
so this is a core
although it may not be the highest
performance score but this is one core
for GPUs there are so many right then
for CPU one is one. So one core excludes
one thread,
right?
See
if one core is multi-threading. So only
special thing you need to consider is
hyperthreading. Hyperthreading is
earlier Intel terminology.
Intel dropped it. Intel doesn't produce
this course anymore. Then AMD starts to
produce this course. So hyperthreading
is basically a way is similar to a GPU
style. So there are uh two
threads waiting there to be executed.
GPU is a super hyperthreading machine.
So there just consider you have a
instruction memory, right? Rather than
this design you have a instruction
buffer.
you have an instruction buffer. So there
are many many instructions waiting there
to be executed. So if you have one
instruction buffer then that's a one
thread. You have two instruction buffers
that's hyperthreading. Okay. Just say
it's either issue from here or issue
from there that's hyperthreading. That's
one core two thread. Okay. So in that
case if you buy say 32 core machine then
if you look at the something like uh
the htop or top machine then you top
command in Linux then you can see 64
cores there 64 threads there uh but
other than that technology one core one
thread for how CPU can handle
multi-threading other other than
multi-ores is basically by context
swapping context switching that means
PC regular file then we have the program
that executed there right then once the
operating system say oh we have to swap
we have to give some share for other
threads to execute it will write
everything back to the memory through
instructions those are just instruct
through um OS level instruction
privilege instructions they write the
registers and PC and everything else
back to the main memory then they bring
another context, another threats context
and back into the PC and register file
and start from there.
It disrupts the pipeline. Definitely
there are many things disrupts the
pipeline and pipeline is a very very
ideal um scenario. There are many many
things that can
Yeah. Yeah. I will hopefully we'll have
time today.
Okay. So performance analysis now here
instructions are not changed. Uh so
cycle a second per cycle we can keep it
short because we only do a little bit
thing per cycle then cycle per
instruction is one CPI. That's the ideal
case. Um
if everything is moving perfectly, if we
only have ALOU instructions and all
performing operations on different
registers, then we can achieve this CPI.
And just consider this. If you can
achieve this CPI
on a modern computer,
what will happen is it will generate too
much heat.
It will generate too much heat. So the
heat cannot be uh
it the heat cannot the temperature
cannot be reduced and the fun or the
water cooling is not working fast
enough. So what it will do is eventually
it will reduce the frequency and the
voltage so that it can run at a lower
performance. That's what you feel
probably every day with your phone,
right? Like when it's getting too hot,
it just feels so so laggy. So that's
what's happening then. So modern cores
are designed in the typical use case.
That means there's some problem the
pipeline is not working perfectly and
not all of them are performing super
intense calculations. So in a typical
work case it can work at the reasonable
performance. That's the modern core
design.
Okay. So we say this is a perfect
working cases, right? Then there are
many many situations that prevent our
core to work in these perfect cases.
Those are called hazers when pipeline
cannot go perfectly. Now we'll talk
about this header.
So we previously we see this circuit
design. We say this is probably the last
time we see this circuit level design
and we will never see gates in this
course anymore. Then we just draw this
way. This is probably much more
comfortable, much easier to understand.
Right? So we have one instruction we do
fetch. Then the second in uh in second
second cycle instruction one is doing
decoded first state second instruction
is doing the first state the fetch state
and so on this perfect pipeline but we
need to look at what instructions are
there so let's say these are all AO
instructions right
AO instructions are there problems are
there
can we perfectly execute this pro these
programs
This program, these four instructions in
this pipeline determine.
Yeah, S8 is here and S8 is used here. So
the question is when the register can
have the S8 ready.
fetch, decode, execute,
memory, skip, write after the right, we
have the ready, right? When this S8 is
used is the decode state, right? So,
ideally, we want to put the decode stage
in cycle six where at at least the cycle
five so that they can get the data,
right?
Okay. So
there is a hther that this data this
right data
cannot be used by this sub cannot be
used by this or but can be used by this
end. If you want to get the correct
result you have to delay the execution
of this sub and the or in instructions.
Okay. So how we can do that
or
say h what is hazard? Her is situation
that prevents the instruction pipeline
from generating corrector execution
result without interrupting the pro
pipeline execution. So if you don't do
something something dangerous can happen
something bad can happen right. So if we
talk about header there are different
type of header let's focus on data
header for now. So when we talk about
data header then if if this is an
interview asking you what are the type
possible types of data header you just
consider four types okay read after read
write read after right after read right
after right and we learned the binary
number counting so that's the natural
way to do all the combinations
then we immediately filter out read
after read right read after read don't
care it's Okay, so we can read from one
piece of data anytimes there's no
conflict. Now what are are we dealing
right now in the previous case? Which
header that we're dealing
read after right? So if we go back a
little bit, so we are first writing the
data, then we read the data later,
right? Well, at least in terms of logic,
then if we don't change the pipeline
design, we're reading before writing,
right? But we always say this is we
always look at this instructions. This
the we read this data after this write
data. So this is a read after write. We
never talk about read before right. is
always something after something.
Okay, so this is a read after write
hard.
It's the most common type of hert
or at least the simplest type of header.
Okay.
So how we can address this problem?
There are several different ways that we
can address this problem.
First thing is we can inert the first
matter we can inert knop no operation
instructions. Now these are instructions
that are just pipeline holders pipeline
fillers that will take two two slot
space so that they don't do anything.
Then they don't take any registers. So
we don't care about this value. We don't
care about the ops. Then this decode
this read stage will not read anything.
It's okay. So we delay two
two cycle instruction. Then at this
cycle we consider this when this right
has the data we can already read the
data. Remember the right happens at the
first cycle first half the cycle then
the read happens at the second half of
the cycle. So this can happen at the
same cycle. Now if your hardware design
prevent that doing the same cycle data
forwarding you can simply just add three
knobs instructions. It really depends on
your hardware.
Okay. So we at least we add knob
instructions to effectively delay the
execution of the sub or and and
instructions so that they can get rid
the correct result. Then we can move
forward. Right? So you can see this
annoying thing that
instruction level par are not natural.
Right? This is a concrete example
instruction level paradism are not
natural because when we write if human
write this assembly they just cannot
feel this problem they just go oh I do
this then I already have S8 ready now
move forward this is just optimization
now once we really want to apply this
optimization but it may introduce some
side effects some drawbacks then we have
to use more complex logic to deal with
these drawbacks right so instruction
level parism are not natural
So
advantage and disadvantages. Advantage
is this is a really simple design. Now
we don't really need any hardware
changes. The original hardware just
works and it's pure software or pure
compiler. The compiler is responsible
for doing this adding these knob
instructions.
Then
on the other side, what's a
disadvantage? Disadvantage is it's low
performance because it
effectively stall the pipeline. I don't
have this word.
It's stall the pipeline
right the pipeline is actually not
moving really moving in these two
cycles. Now you feel it's moving but
it's not moving. It's not it's not doing
useful things. Or on the other way that
say this word is it adds bubbles
adds two bubbles.
Add two bubbles into this instructions
into this pipeline because where the
bubbles this is a bubble this is a
bubble right add two bubbles into this
pipeline. So these are something that we
want to annoy and another thing is we're
mixing architecture design and micro
architecture design. So our micro
architecture is say or architecture
let's say if we really have this type of
design that means we're not going to
support this at hardware level then
compiler design has to add knobs. So
okay compiler I add this knob design
then one day we start to say oh we want
to design a higher level core a more
performance like higher performance core
we find we have no way because the
knobby instructions are there that we
cannot get rid of right so ideally we
want it to be handled either say we can
have some higher performance method or
we can have some low performance method
low performance method will simply delay
the execution and higher performance
method may do something that we'll see
later, right? So if we do this now, we
we lock the compiler. Then the compiler
has to add these knobby instructions and
our hardware has no flexibility to
design in different performance tiers.
It's a bad design for these things. For
GPU is rather common for this type of
design because GPU doesn't really have
the technical that because it can
involve this in uh ISO rather easy
because AMD is keep involving on its own
because it's controlled by AMD. But for
Intel, they have no choice. they kind of
want to avoid this thing as much as
possible because they need to consider
future compatib compatibility.
On the other side,
do GPUs have the same problem
or how do GPUs solve this problem?
Yeah,
that's right. That's very right. Exact
exactly the answer. So
GPUs execute in this way. So let's say
if one workp or one wave front is
executing this instruction
it can never execute this instruction
right at least in traditional GPU
design. If it's executing this
instruction GPU has a rule the issues
the issue rule if one instruction if one
wave front if a waver has one
instruction in pipeline it cannot issue
another instruction into the pipeline.
So if you look at from the stage the
fetch the code they're all these stages
are all executing from different warps
and the worps cannot communicate easily
right there's no way for words to
communicate so then they have no hazard
there's no dependency then there's no
hazard right so in CPU since we only
have one thread to run then all these
instructions are from one thread they
naturally have dependency so they have
to address this problem for GPU they
address this problem by swiping to
another warp okay that's advantage of
GPU because GPU has so many threads
waiting there to be executed on CPU
since we talk about hyperthreading and
CPU can also do that if it's hyper
threading right so we can have one extra
way by executing the instruction from
another thread to um mitigate this
problem. At least when we need a knob,
we can execute the instruction from
another thread. Okay, that's
hyperthreading.
But CPU I I have only seen two two
thread hyperthreading and never seen
more than two thread hyperthreading. So
that capability is somehow limited.
Okay. The second way if we don't want to
add this knob this is a bad design what
we can do is we can in we can or
hardware can actually detect by putting
some sort of flex are we going to write
into this S8 right this every register
needs to have one extra bit of
information so for every 32 bit adding
one extra bit overhead that's okay we
have a flag saying is it going to be
written into it then once we decode it.
Once we decode once we actually decode
this this instruction, we can actually
write into that bit to say, oh, we're
going to write into this S8 U
register. If that bit is there,
I still have to this.
So, the first time this is a register
file.
Okay, then the first time when we put S8
when we when we put S8
that means in the first cycle after
instruction fetching we have to tell
that we're going to do something with
this destination but here we only set
the flag they say S8 needs to be written
just hold don't read from it right
then
as we're dealing with the second
instruction we need to read
S8 this time. Then we check this flag.
We see this flag says S8 will be
written, right? We say S8 will be
written. Then what we do is
um
we do not allow it to happen. We delay
this decode stage. We say this decode
stage cannot complete then we move
forward. Right? So it's either done by
the register file somehow the register
file can tell the control unit to do
this operation or this
instructions needs to like the control
unit need to decode this instruction and
to automatically control this logic to
insert pipeline bubbles to this
pipeline. So these pipeline bubbles are
inerted in this way that the control
logic prevent it from moving forward.
Now if it's prevented from moving
forward and they will just decode that
instruction then not successful decode
that instruction not success then decode
for the third time and it's finally
successful and can move on. Okay. So
these are pipeline stalls or pipeline
bubbles purely inerted by hardware. Now
we'll talk about how later on we'll talk
about how what hardware architecture
that we can support this type of things
and also other type of hert
but at least this is one method right
you think this method we delay the
execution of this sub instruction so
that we have the data when it's written
into this um the register file
okay advantage is is pure architecture
we're comfortable with this Disadvantage
is still slow performance, right? Uh
because the pipeline bubbles are added
inerted into this pipeline. Then it
requires extra hardware. Then we need to
maintain the maintain the state so that
we at what time we need to insert into
these bubbles extra hardware that
compared to the knob instruction.
The knob method. Okay. The third method
and if you look at from the perspective
of the register
when the register will have the value is
what is at this right stage right but if
you look at the value from the
perspective of the value when we
actually have the value we have the
value at this execute stage
right we have the value at this
execution stage so assume if we can
squeeze this execution ution stage into
the first cycle.
Actually, there's no real hazard,
right? There's no real hazard. If we can
calculate the ALOU, then we can directly
put into the register here
the this value here, then we can
directly use it. Okay. So, actually when
we use it, we use it at this execute
stage, this E stage, right?
So if you look at the value this E will
generate a value and this E will use the
value.
So there's no header in terms of value.
So if we are smart and if we can afford
the hardware what we do is we just inert
through wires.
We just inert through wires. What do we
do here? I mean draw a very
simple figure here.
So this is our register file right
now and after register file we have this
pipeline reg pipeline holding registers
then we have aou
then after the alou we have another
pipeline holding registers right. So
what we do is basically
we can have
add extra wire by going from here
directly to here.
So just automatically adds multiplexer
here. Okay, I'm just not drawing the
multiplexer.
We can add an extra wire loop back.
So the cycle immediately the cycle after
we get the result
we hold it in this register and in the
next cycle we can just put it back
there. Uh actually we don't need this
one. If we want it to be even faster we
can even do this
right.
We can do this. We calculate result. We
don't don't need to wait this one extra
cycle. If we're connecting that way,
we're adding one extra cycle. Don't do
that. We're directly have the result.
Then we add a through wire or loop back
wire that connects to the operand
gathering.
Right? Then we can immediately use it.
So in this method
we are adding more wires there. We're
adding more multiplexer. where any more
complex control logic there but at a
advantage is
it's really fast it's pure micro
architecture and disadvantage is it's
complex more circuit and logic more
energy consumption
then it cannot avoid all this problem
you can avoid this problem here but it
cannot avoid all the problems that we're
going to describe later
okay we're comfortable using this
design.
So CPUs are using like it's really a
historical design that there are many
many
methods added to the CPU so that CPU is
running more and more efficiently there
in the GPU that say we just have a lot
of thread let them run then for CPUs and
they just add this method it doesn't
work perfect add the other method it
doesn't work perfect add another method
and keep appiling methods to the CPUs
then that's why you Understand in CPUs
we really have complex control logics
there right we need a lot of circuit
range region for control logic for GPUs
we don't want to spend dice size for
control logic we want to spend the logic
in regard files and in uh alus that's
the real useful things
simp is still useful it's just different
design philosophy
okay just look One example when is still
used
previously we're saying uh execute
execute
dependency if it's a load use dependency
then the wiring thing may not work right
the through wire thing may not work.
So in this case these two instructions
cannot execute because the memory will
take a whole cycle. It's a very ideal
case it will take one cycle.
Then we need to execute at the same
stage. So even we through wires we have
to at least insert one bubble there.
Right? In this case load use dependency
we have no way to simply use uh through
wires to solve all the stars.
We still need stars there.
Okay let's talk about other types of
header other than data hazard. We talk
about data hazard. Data hazard are only
exist in the registers. So there are
only three type of uh
only three type of headers. So let let
me ask one thing
in this pipeline design is right after
right possible.
Do we really have the hater?
And the quick answer is no. It's not
possible. There's no right after right
header. And do we have right after
reader?
And the quick answer is still no. with
this five-stage pipeline there's no such
header. So why those are still useful
headers? Why we not we're not only
talking about read after write header is
because the pipeline is not only
designed in this way. The pipeline can
be really complex. Then next lecture
we're going to talk about something like
out of order issuing or multipath or
supercaler. Supercaler means some in
like one instruction is executing
integer operations. So one instruction
is executing floatingoint instructions.
The floatingoint instruction may take 20
cycles to execute. The integer may take
four cycles to execute. Then that may
trigger right after right because
they're going to on different routes.
Right? So for now remember if we have in
order pipeline in order textbook level
five stage pipeline
the only header the only data header can
happen is read after write header. It's
no other type of data header that we can
trigger at this moment. Then next
lecture we're going to talk about the
other type of pipelines.
Then we once we introduce new type of
pipelines we have new type of header
that we need to address.
Okay. Other type of hazard. Then we talk
about data hazard and structural hazard
is another type of hert that we need to
consider. What is structural hazard? Is
basically multiple instruction compete
for one hardware one piece of one
hardware resource.
For example, in this case, we see this
instruction data memory in the
multi-stage pipeline design, right? We
want to fuse it in the van architecture.
That's the default type of architecture
that we want to use. Then just look at
this case. The load instruction needs to
do a memory read operation and this end
instruction need to fetch at cycle 4.
We only have one address bus and we also
need to have we almost only have one
read data bus, right? In that case
they cannot be executed in one cycle.
If there if we force them to execute
definitely there's something wrong going
to happen. And this is called structural
hither. That means the hardware
resources does not allow parallelism to
happen. the perfect pipeline to happen.
Right? So what's the solution here? The
most natural type of solution is if you
have one piece of resources and you have
a data header, you either serialize them
to execute in two different cycles or
you provide two different piece of
hardware so that it can happen in
parallel. Okay. So no matter how how
powerful a combination logic is, it can
only process one piece of data in one
cycle. So this talks the difference
between vanoya architecture and Harvard
architecture. So vanoya architecture
have merged and instruction and data
memory. Harvard architecture have
separate instruction and memory. Okay.
So
if you say
um at the early age of binomial
architecture they never really consider
this type of pipeline design really do
not need this type of performance. So
one piece of memory is simple, cheap,
easy to build, easier to build. Then
later on it doesn't work when we start
need to pipeline execution. We have to
separate instruction instruction and the
uh separate the instruction and the data
memory.
Um so this is a this are tricky terms.
Why are tricky? If you say when you say
non nonoan
architecture
do you consider Harvard architecture
typically you consider how architecture
in general is still architecture right
if you talk about non vanoma
architecture is something totally
different
okay but still when you when you talk to
people say oh a core design a CPU core a
GPU core is you generally call it a
binomial architecture. Okay. So there
are not strictly defined terms in
different context they may mean
different things and if you ask say what
architecture does a modern computer use
then a quick way is to say a hybrid
monoma and hover architecture. What they
typically do is in L1 cache they're
separated in L2 or lower level
eventually at some level they're merged
together. Okay, it's hybrid.
Okay, just some knowledge
here. Another hert just consider
registers. There's something that we're
skipping one lecture here the register
file design. So in in register file
design if we consider there are 34 reg
32 registers right so that's basically a
register that takes that say just 32
flip-flops all of them have a wire
connecting to the output then we need a
big multiplexer and a selector with a
selector the addressing input are
selectors right the selector is
controlling the multiplexer so that we
can control which register that we
It's a simplified design. But if you
consider something like a GPU design
when there's so many register there like
several hundreds of register or even
thousands,
you probably don't want to have that
type of multiplexer that's so complex.
So what they do is they use a banked
register file or register banking.
Um typically what they can do is say res
are zero four eight they're in one bank
one five nine they're in another bank
and so on. Okay. So what they're
actually doing is they're actually
nesting multilayers of multiplexers.
So in the first layer register one
register five register nine they're in
one bank right. So we select which
register here then we use a multiplexer
to go through. Then later on we have
another
then after that we have another
multiplexer to select which one to go.
That means in this group of register we
only have one output port to send the
data out. So if we want to read say S0
and S8 together
we have a structural header that we
cannot really finish everything in one
cycle time. Now we have to first read
let's use this example R1 and R5. We
need to in first cycle read from R1
store it in a register.
In the second second cycle we read from
R5 and store it here.
Okay.
So we need two cycles to gather this opt
together to wait for the the register
are ready. In that case, this is another
type of structural header. Now, we can
use an opt gathering operation that is
the operand gathering logic. Before
we're only talking about combination
logic, but this time this is sequential
logic and we may need multiple cycles to
gather opt.
Okay. So you may you may ask then how P6
and S8 can be load in one cycle right
do you have this question
if S8 and S0 cannot be read in one cycle
how ST6 and S8 can be read in one cycle
so just consider this way
this is one bank right
we have only one port output port there
a second bank there several banks there
have one output port then there's a one
multiplexer and there's another
multiplexer they're all connecting to
both multiplexers so there are two
output for the whole register file
okay
in this way
we only have one output from each bank
in one cycle but if our registers are
from different banks we can output in
one cycle.
Okay. So in CPUs this at least in
low-end CPUs this is not common for in
GPUs this is very common. So the
register are banked so they sometimes
cannot be read in one cycle time.
There's there have to be extra delay.
Okay.
Then another type of header is
structural header. So we're mainly
talking about structural header, data
header and
control header.
What is control header? So when we have
control logic like branching I finally
arrived at this point. So we know this
is a branching instruction.
Now we do we f the execution we decode.
Then immediately we should fetch the
next instruction right but which
instruction to fetch
then
we can know uh we can go with the next
instruction we can go pass for
instruction then we can just directly
fetch an index instruction another
problem is on this side we don't even
know where is TG right
we even don't know where is TG target
when we can know where is TG
we can only know after the execution
stage
That's the earliest time that we can
know that know where we're jumping
because this is a basically a BEQ is a
register add instruction right it's a
S1 plus a immediate number and this is a
encoded immediate number so we don't
know where is TG only at this point we
know this is a TG so what we can do
right so shall we Go ahead. If we don't
consider anything, if we don't do
anything, then we just go ahead. We just
simply execute this add instruction sub
instruction,
right? And definitely that will can give
us a result if this branch is taken.
So we cannot do that. So the easiest way
is just wait. That's if we don't know
it, we just wait until the time we know
it. So what we can do is we wait until
this time when we are done with the
execution stage. If it's not taken,
we do fetch.
Now even this, if you consider this,
this is already added through wires,
right? Otherwise, we have to wait until
it the right back stage completes. Then
we can do fetching. This is already
added through wires. But at the earliest
time, we know if it's taken, then we can
do here. If it's not taken, then we just
continue go. We can fetch the
instruction. If it's taken, we already
calculate result. Then we can go with
this.
uh this instruction, right?
So
we added two pipeline bubbles and these
are called branch penalty, right? For
every branch instruction we have to
wait, we have to do this and branch
penalty and in this case it's not too
bad only two pipeline bubbles in more
deeper pipelines more stages. This is
terri something that
the designers really really want to
avoid.