welcome to the machine learning
compilation class everyone so today we
are going to begin the first journey of
this
lecture series my name is tianji chen
you can call me dq
i will be with you together on exploring
this new immersion topic
so
today's lecture is going to come into
two components first we're going to talk
about
what is machine learning compilation
techniques why want to start it
then in the second part we're going to
dive a bit deeper
onto some of the key elements that we
use
we'll be using in the next few part of
lectures
so to begin with why machine learning
compilation
if you look at the software landscape
nowadays you can find that
the software that we are living the age
of artificial intelligence is very
different from a software
that we we use you know a few years ago
you know in the age of web 2.0
so previously
we are looking at softwares that have
wider range of application scenarios
most of them are built on
a smaller set of software libraries and
finally they are running on some of them
called foundational piece
on
a single piece of device usually that's
a general purpose computing device like
for your laptop or on your
desktop and in this case the software
requires to have broad coverage
where engineers handle most of their
performance optimizations and other
cases where and compute is less critical
and it's mainly about how do we get as
wide variety of applications as possible
for your laptop and and for your web
experiences
however if we start to look at the
software landscape and age of artificial
intelligence a lot of things have
changed
specifically the software landscape
starts from what is like a funnel type
onto a more wider range of
um more both the front-end applications
that are specialized as well as the
backhands that we want to run on
first of all in the age of ai
what we are trying to build and run are
machine learning models such as you know
object detection models natural language
processing models in different forms
usually those models will need to ingest
a bigger amount of data there so that we
will be able to you know
fuel them with
ais using
learning from those data sets
and one of the key requirements there is
that we want to be able to
handle
those models on a wide range of power
devices and
environments those devices could include
you know simple settings such as
the normal data center cpus as well as
some other more specific settings like
you know this
this specialized
tpu port
or in certain cases this computing
starts to sit in our pocket like you
know the iphones or other devices that
we'll be using
and this shift of computing paradigm
really requires us to rethink how do we
build software in the age of ai
and
that's where the topic of machine
learning systems in particular in this
lecture the machine learning compilation
jumps in to become
a quite relevant topic that were studied
in in today's age
okay
so what's machine learning compilation
specifically
if we
want to talk about machine compilation
we want to start to think about what
does it involve to take what we say
intelligence application and try to put
them on to
those uh environments we call deployment
environment we are interested in
so
there are as we know in a lot of cases
machinery have been used in a lot of uh
cases and with the recent success of
deep learning there are quite a lot of
smart applications that
become part of a daily life from ho you
know the emerging self-driving car case
will require us to do things like object
detection and production detection
segmentation if we say hi alexa
or you know using other
other smart devices like siri it
involves machinery model that does
natural language processing and speech
recognition
more recently there's also exciting news
that uses ai to be able to fold protein
so that we'll be able to get more
information that help us to to
towards new scientific discoveries as
well as finding you know effective
medicine drugs for some of the new
emerging diseases
one of the key characteristics now is
that now those machine learning models
are running all really wide range of
environments that are interesting for
example in the case of serving driving
cars usually we want to be able to run
those machine learning models the
detection models and some of the
planning modules
on the cars themselves usually that will
involve the specialized computing
devices on the car
in the case of
protein phones maybe we want to be able
to run on data centers so that we'll be
able to fold them we'll be able to find
some other sequences but in other cases
maybe want to run those machining models
on dna sequencers or other specialized
devices if we look at nlp and speech
recognition some of them have to run on
those smart devices such as smartphones
and
some of us some of the
some of the smart speakers
so
there's a quite a bit of gap that we're
looking at actually
between those intelligent applications
and the deployment environment
on the right hand side
now if we if you think about it i want
us to pause a second and think about you
know
what are the possible complications that
involving
to bring some of the intelligence
applications on the left-hand side
to
the deployment environments on the
right-hand side
there are a lot of heavy lifting's going
on and a lot of these are non-trivial
if you want to think about some specific
factors you will find that some more
factors will include things like the
howard choices that might
uh be relevant in this case
what kind of operation systems that
involves you know
in
me running those things the container
execution environment and sometimes the
runtime library variants and you know
whether or not accelerated
all those factors need to be factoring
together to be able to make
that
effort of taking machine learning models
that we viewed in development settings
on through the deployment environments
electricity
previously this process is really you
know usually done in a more manual labor
process so so for each kind of
application scenarios there will be a
dedicated team of engineers that takes
in
these machine learning intelligent
applications and trying to bring them
onto a deployment environment and that
is still the case today
however one of the questions we really
want to ask
as this practice become more uncommon is
that you know is there any way for us to
simplify such kind of machine learning
deployment problem and really help us to
be able to innovate more bringing in a
lot of the latest greatest machine
learning models but also bring them on
to many of the latest greatest
environments that
that we want to put ai to
and that's kind of the main thing of
today's
lecture which is called machine learning
compilation
so specifically machining compilation
refers to the process where
we want to develop our models so there
will be you know machine learning models
in its development form usually if we
look at some of the machine learning
model developments you know the there
will be one engineer or a few engineers
working together on building models
usually on common machine learning
frameworks such as you know high torch
tensorflow objects or other favorite
frameworks like you know extreme boost
and so on
and the question is
how can we take that machine learning
model in its development form
and try to
transform that onto what we call
deployment
in this particular case the deployment
form
refers to you know everything that we
need to be able to deploy that
particular machinery execution
for example you know
on this right hand side here's a
specific example of you know how we can
take one model
from its development form and try to put
that on an android device
and you know this is just illustrative
example but show some of the
complexities in behind the scene
for example first of all i'm going to
put that on there on the android device
you know we kind of need to try to build
the entire application and expose that
to the interface that android you know
accepts usually there's a java developed
environment
um when we are trying to pack
these machinery models it usually comes
with a
you know description for some of
extrusion engines that involves like how
we are going to compute each steps of
the machine learning model
of course in order to compute that we
also need to store the weights that are
learned through the development process
in order to really you know make that
effect effective execution
besides those we also need to be able to
have
relevant libraries that allows us to run
that execution for example in this case
we are only giving a few examples of
what are possible libraries in here that
trying to implement some of the
operations such as matrix multiplication
softmax and other operations that
that common machine learning
models uses
and finally
those libraries will need to be run on
some of the environments that execute
zones
foreign device gpu that comes with the
android devices then we want to be able
to run them on things like android
opencl runtime
or maybe if there's a native
acceleration going on through some of
the accelerators we might need to
leverage some of the native libraries
such as android and api
of course some of those concepts may not
be you know you may not be familiar with
all those concepts that is totally fine
um
this is just an example of illustrating
some of the key components that could be
involved
in deployment form and you can you can
find the key components include both
some of the system component that's
specific to the platform like api
interface
and operation system
operation system interfaces and so on as
well as machine learning model specific
information such as
descriptions and weights
and if you you're not familiar with a
specific term you just need to
understand that you know we need to be
able to
find deployment form in both the the you
know the runtime system specific factors
as well as the machinery model specific
factors
okay
so the machining compilation mlc process
is a process we have not yet defined you
know how we do it but you know
it's a process that help us to transform
the machinery models from its
um
development form on the left-hand side
to the toilet deployment form on the on
the right-hand side
and importantly you know this mlc
process doesn't necessarily have to be
fully automatic well we could say you
know if i'm a developer i'm going to
identify
these
higher level machine learning models
like object detection model i'm going to
you know hand wave
everything and pack them together and
and put the employment form
we still call that process as a machine
learning compilation except that this
compilation is done with engineering
involvement as a matter of fact a lot of
the current practices in the point
machinery models involve that kind of
you know manual process anyway
on the other hand we are also interested
in other automated solutions that help
us to automate some of the solutions
generalizes some of the methods that
that help us to you know transform and
optimize machine learning execution
okay
so here's the higher level on what mlc
means it means that we want to be able
to take models from development form and
trying to do transformations and get
them on to the deployment form
so next we're going to talk about what
are the key goals that we need to
achieve throughout this process what
kmlc brings you
through this process of transforming
from development form good deployment
so the first goal
of mlc
is that
we want to be able to help us to
interrogate together
a lot of the solutions for that develop
deployment form
and also minimize the dependencies
so in this particular case
where on the left-hand side let's assume
that we are trying to build a machinery
model for computer vision
uh we have not shown exactly what the
model is but let's just use this rough
figure to show you know this here's a
model that contains
you know one two three four four layers
and one inputs
and let's build using some of the modern
machinery frameworks like you know
pytorch or tensorflow objects
usually those modern machining
frameworks contains a lot of features
that allows us to
be able to support
all kind of machine learning model
operations such as
in in the case of computer vision
usually involves
convolution that allows us to take local
pixels and try to groups in and find uh
fun patterns in each of the in in a more
translational invariant manner there
will also be softmax activation
functions and other operators so there
are features that are necessary to
support the models
in the meantime they are also
these frameworks also contains features
to support other models foreign lookup
is usually useful for natural language
processing but not necessary for vision
and
is usually used for speech recognition
and so on
so
one of the goal of machine learning
compilation is trying to come up with a
deployment form
such that we can have a minimal set of
um artifacts that allows us to support
deployment specifically one of the
things that mlc might do
is we can analyze
this this uh machine execution we find
that hey only this component is really
necessary so let's also try to come up
with the corresponding component
on the right hand side
that that is minimal to support
the model fusion
so this is kind of related to the go of
dependency minimization in here
besides dependency minimization there's
also this perspective integration
so
this is because in a located forum if
you want to deploy
models onto devices like mobile and
other cases
we might need to leverage libraries and
solutions from different parties for
example this uh two-dimensional
convolution could be implemented by one
team of engineer
while the softmax and value could be
implemented by you know another
engineering team or usually the key
operator convolution are implemented by
vendors who kind of know deeper onto how
exactly to optimize those critical ones
we kind of need a way to be able to
assemble them together and
and making them work together in the
final deployment phase usually this down
by say a common extrusion engine or
interpreter that allows us to plug in
those additional machine learning
operators
so
so for the first part of a goal machine
learning compilation really aims aims to
be able to integrate all those backhand
solutions together and also minimize the
possible dependencies so we can really
come up with a deployment artifact that
is minimal but also sufficient to build
our model execution
okay so that's the first goal
the second goal of machine learning
compilation
is to leverage our native accelerations
so in all the cases we are trying to
bring in machine learning models and
trying to put them onto deployment form
we are looking at cases where
[Music]
those deployment environment contains
contains
how hard acceleration such as you know
nvidia's tensor core
and
google's tpu and other cases
and in those cases we need to be able to
generate deployables that really
leverages those native power backends
when possible
by doing that we will be able to get the
solution that end-to-end but also take
the best use of underlying hub so that's
usually the second goal of machine
learning
compilation
of course in general
our third goal that summarizes
everything else is that you know we are
interested in optimizing in general
in terms of one machinery model you may
have noticed that you know there are
many ways that we can use to run the
same model executions
but each way may come come with
different you know extrusion
efficiencies
and on the goal of machine learning
compilations be able to take the model
from the remote form and trying to do
second transformations
such that it help us to do uh you know
optimization
in in different cases for example one of
a goal could be one to go and minimize
memory usage in other cases we are
interested in improving extrusion
efficiency
or in other cases you know nowadays if
you want to really build bigger models
we are interested in scaling to multiple
heterogeneous devices
so this could be all the goals uh that
machine learning compilation cares about
okay
and coming back one of the things i
don't want to mention is that you know
there's not a strict boundary between
those goals but we can view
this uh dependency minimization as well
as our native acceleration as other form
of optimization it's just like now these
are kind of quite interesting cases that
i want to leave them out and talk about
separately
the term compilation in mlc comes from
analog analogy to traditional compounds
in a sense that if you think about
transitional compiler like gcc
or clan effectively they are taking the
code or program in this development form
being developed by
you know
software developers and compile them
onto executables or libraries or other
forms
that we can use to deploy onto our real
world settings
however
also we call it compilation the
techniques involved with harnessing can
be very different
between these two problems
and that's why we want to take this
specialized
course episode to talk about
some of the
insights for doing machine learning
compilation and trying to use those
techniques to help us to be able to
build
better intelligent applications
uh one of the key thing
that we do want to notice that also we
call compilation this process doesn't
have to necessarily involve code
generation for example in a lot of cases
the deployment form can simply be a
model description and engine that
execute it natively and this is actually
the most common case that we are using
to deploy
machine learning
applications nowadays
however in a lot of cases code
generation do comes to be quite handy
and we will be talking about some of the
tool generation techniques as well
in our later part of lectures
the second thing is that
in some cases a development form and
deployment form can take
uh the same interface
uh for example if we are trying to
deploy on server settings maybe you are
developing tensorflow and you are
directly deployed in tensorflow that is
totally fine
still in that settings actually we will
be able to leverage machine learning
compilation techniques because we will
be able to take in the model
descriptions in its development form and
try to optimize it so that although they
expose the same interface the online
solution is more memory efficient
or being optimized for other metrics
very interested
finally when we talk deployment one
thing i do want to remember
is that
you know
in a lot of cases we are interested in
this scenario of influence which means
that we build a model that comes with
model architectures and modern widths
and we're only interested in taking new
inputs and trying to make prediction
using the model
however the deployment form can also
apply to other settings like training
the model itself
and it has become more and more
increasing popular nowadays when we
start to try to generalize some of our
artificial intelligence applications
from her if you want to be able to build
a smart watch that monitors my health i
would like to you know make learning
local on the device and not letting the
data leaking towards to my providers
because i care about privacy reasons
as a result
likely we are going to build on device
intelligence extrusions
and that process can also benefit a lot
from machine learning compilation as
well because
the the process of developing that
training process and deployment of that
training process can happen at very
different platforms
okay
so here's a generic high-level
reason a hell of a descriptions about
machine compilation and the goals
that we want to achieve through this
compilation process
let's come back and talk about you know
why why do we want to you know
build this course or why do you want to
study of course there are a few reasons
why i want to study mrc
uh to begin with
you know one of the things that is
really important nowadays we want to be
not only building those awesome models
but we also want to deploy them
effectively
and
there are a lot of complexity involved
in bringing machine learning to
production or incorporating normal model
customizations so that you can extend
your machine learning framework to
support the normal model customization
that you want
machine learning compilation really
gives us a set of tools that solve those
problems
and in a lot of cases they really come
in handy so that's reason number one to
study mlc okay
the reason number two
is that you know in all cases
we are developing models and we can just
leverage the underlying machine learning
framework
and however in one piece you'll find
that
those machine learning frameworks are
also increasing start to adopt new
techniques coming from mlc
so understanding machine learning
compilation help us to
understand the harnessing techniques
that we use to provide
to provide those model exclusions and
give us some kind of super power that
you know really help us to understand
how framework works
and sometimes enable us to push novel
model customizations
with good system support so that not
only build a smart model but the model
scales with the underlying system
and that is something that
you know many of the machine learning
scientists would benefit from in a lot
of cases
finally you know if and if you are a
hardware company or you know we are at
the golden age of building power
accelerations
with waves of new environment
innovations coming up
however one of the key problems of all
those uh normal machine learning
acceleration
is a software problem
in a lot of cases we will need to build
software stacks from ground up to keep
new high acceleration features to make
best use of them and also build a
spectrum support for
a novel models that are emerging
really mlc is a way for us to
you know it's it's a systematic approach
for us to be able to build software set
and keep up with all those power
acceleration and model development
innovation
okay so that's reason number three we've
talked about three reasons
and one of the last reasons actually you
know my reason of bringing this course
and working with everybody here is that
machine learning compilation is really
fun
um when was uh when i started studying
computer science one of the really
revealing moment is that
at my i think third grade in
universities i started to understand
what it does take
to
to you know take high-level applications
go all the way through the compilation
process
through low-level assembly and how does
that run from a silicon
and and that is really a satisfying
experience for all when we talk machine
learning is i think it's also
interesting to ask you know hey here's a
set of ai models
how does that translate to the high
level competitions the low level code
and to the bear mental
mechanism that really you know runs and
supports those intelligent applications
be able to get that understanding it's
really what
what what is you know what is really um
self-fulfilling in some sense and also
we can use this tool to solve a lot of
our incoming problems okay
so here are the four reasons that
we can
we can study machine compilation and
also you know bring some use to our
daily lives
okay
so far we've talked about uh key
elements in machine learning compilation
now moving the in the in the next you
know 10 minutes also i'm going to spend
some time
talk about
some of the key elements that are
involved
in machine learning compilation
so in the first part we have already
talked about you know machine learning
compilation is uh
it's a process for us to take uh
high-level model developments
and try to transform them onto the
deployment one that can be
achieved effectively on an environment
of interest
and in order to do that let's let's try
to you know
dive down another level and let's start
to talk about
how does those development form and
deployment form
look like
in practice
specifically if you look at multiple
machine learning models
there are two key concepts that
that i would say you know straight
through
all these um all these machine learning
model executions
and hopefully you know if you have
learned machine learning frameworks you
have already been familiar with some of
the of those concepts
so the first concept is what we call
tensor which is effectively a
multi-dimensional array that stores
this input output and intermediate
results of model extrusion so if i am
calling this particular
case on the left hand side
what it represents is a sequence of
computations where we have
input tensor
that contains you know one by 3072
elements
so it will be
something like you know if you try to
write it out you will have some elements
here that have you know v0 v1 and so on
and there are about 3032
of those elements
in that input and
you know in this in this case is a
multi-layer
perception network and we are trying to
take in a flattened image on the left
hand side so originally it is
i think it's 32 no it's not 32 by 32
yeah 32 by 32 by 3
in images where 3 is an rgb channel and
we're going to flatten that
that become a vector
of 3032 in this case
not only we use this test to store the
intermediate to store the input we are
also using it to store intermediate data
for example in this case you know we
could have a linear layer that tries to
project this to
a tensor of you know
1 by 10 so there will be
10 values here
v0 v1 and 2v10
in this case
and it represents an intermediate result
of that particular layer okay
and in here
these tensors are kind of like
represents the data that we
that we use throughout the machine
learning compilation
through the machine learning execution
sorry
and now
uh the second thing that
that is really important as a part of
the machine extrusion is what called
tensor functions
in this case the tensor functions are
operation that encodes the computation
among those input and output
but i'm holding here
in this particular case this linear
is the tensor function
that help us to be able to take in
input and trying to do a linear
projection so
the result
will be something like you know out
put
will equal
i j
[Music]
sum
over
k
and we have w which is a weight
j k
times imagine what input is x
i k
so this is a linear projection layer
that helps us to be able to take in
an input x here
and a weight here and trying to be able
to do a linear projection so if you try
to draw that out as a neural network
form
it's crisp onto a neural network so that
includes some of the input vectors
as x
and we will have the output
as
output vector and we have ways that are
fully connected to each of the input
okay
so this particular operations help us to
transform
um input x
with w
onto the
output in here
and we call it tensor functions so
effectively it's a set of computations
that
allows us to ingest in some cancers and
output some other cancers
one of the key thing i do want to notice
here is that this tensor function
is not only used to denote a single
boxing here so in this case a single box
could correspond to a linear operator
but we can also use it to denote a
sequence operations for example
in this case if we try to view
you know
what we call subset of computations
so so in this case if you want to look
at you know this sub sub computation
link here that contains two
tensor operations we can compose them
together and that's still a tensor
function that allows us to be able to
you know run the first operation that's
linear projection and apply a non-linear
activation in this case rectifier linear
unit to that
and
the end-to-end extrusion of the model
can also be viewed as a cancer function
in this case
okay
so when we look at machine learning
extrusion you can find that you know
most of the things are about
cancers
and operations that transform among
cancers and that's also the common
abstraction
most of the machining frameworks use to
be able to express some of the machine
learning computations
so now let's take a look at one example
compilation process
in the
specific terminologies of tensors and
tensor functions
so in this in this case on the left hand
side we have the
um
we have the machine learning model thing
is development form where
we have talked about you know this is
the market layer perception that takes
in the input flattened image trying to
apply
one layer of linear transformation
non-linearity and another layer of
linear transformations
and on the right hand side we have a one
instance of
a
development form
that
correspond to
the
corresponding to the outcome of a
possible machine learning compilation
process
so i want us to pay specific attention
to two places
first of all if we look at the
development form and deployment form
you'll find that
on the right-hand side we have this
linear value operations that correspond
to actually this two operations
uh working together so effectively when
i try to you know all these
graphic implementations we are trying to
put those two things and trying to put
them onto a single box
that correspond to the right hand side
and second thing is that
on this deployment form actually we
specifically list out
a specialized implementation in this
case by using python to
to you know to write it out but in uh in
reality usually it is something that
implemented by a lower level code like
cuda or c plus box and so on
okay
so one of the things you can find in
this specific mlc process and this
outcome
is that we'll find that you know in this
process we are trying to transforming
this entire thing
on the left hand side which correspond
to
a tensor
function
that we talked about
in that concept and we're trying to
transform it
to another
big boxing here
which can be viewed as another cancer
function right so and what was
interesting saying is that
you know although they are
different
in certain sense they're also trying to
do the same thing in this particular
example hopefully you can say that you
know they correspond to the same kind of
computations
um so why do we want to do this from
transformation
in reality you know when we're trying to
transforming things from a left side
right-hand side you know it can result
in
different kind of outcomes in terms of
extrusion efficiencies memory costs and
so on for example in this case if you
are trying to
run this code on gpu
using those two operations together into
a single operation here will result in
less memory copies that goes back to the
gpu memory and as a result the
resulting a faster gpu extrusion
you've ever used framework and pytorch
and other things before you might have
you know
uh same things like uh um some some kind
of some kind of fused operators behind
the scene is not necessarily directly
exposed to you but when we use things
like cud and other libraries they
usually come with those fused operators
that we can take benefit of
okay
one of the things that is really
interesting here
is that there are really different ways
to express the same tensor function
so
so usually this is a quite common
concept in systems language we call
abstractions so abstraction refers to
different ways we can we use represent
the same system interface or you know
same same
the same system implementation as a
sentence in this case we are interested
in cancer function that takes in certain
tensor objects and help us to output
other test objects
and
there are really different ways to
represent it from what we could
represent as you know two consecutive
computations where each of the box
represents operations
in certain cases we can represent it as
a you know single linear radical unit
as we have shown in the last part
or in other cases maybe we want to
represent them as like a sequence of for
loops so that we know exactly how do you
carry our computation
in this particular case we can find that
we have three abstract ways
to be able to represent the same tester
computation function
and importantly each problem presents a
different level of details for example
you know certainly this you know higher
level graphical view is certainly in a
more higher level as you might see
than a loop level because you know i
could implement the same linear value
using different ways example if i swap
these two loops
into something like 4 j
and then for i it's going to give me the
same
uh program same same program output for
any of the input terms
so
there are different abstractions some
some of them are more detailed than
others or some of them more specialized
in the machine learning system land we
usually say that those more specialized
version is an implementation
of the obstruction
now this concept of abstraction
implementation is going to be the key
concept we're going to
use through the course of this lecture
series
and in a lot of cases machine learning
compilation is effectively
a way of transforming among
different tensor functions in different
abstractions
so specifically
if we think about machine learning
compilation a lot of the things we're
going to talk about in the next few
part of the
lecture episode is going to be about how
we can take in tensor functions that you
know that computes those among those
tensors and trying to transform them
onto the deployment forms
that are also transfer function but may
sit in different abstractions example in
this case at least two color ways to
represent the tensor function we have
this graphical representation
which we will talk about which is
usually called communication graph we
have this loopy level representation
that represents well in this case python
like program represents how they want to
compute out the
the
uh compute
the the linear value operations
and at least in here there are two
abstractions right all
in that terminological compiler it's
also called intermediate orientations
that we can use to represent the
computation
and usually a machine learning process
compilation process can be viewed as a
transformation among
the tensor functions so we will have we
start with the tensor function in the
development form and then we can
gradually transform them onto another
cancer function that represents more
detailed information such as you know
how i might want to compute the for loop
so on
and
and usually that can also come in
different form of abstractions in this
case another form of obstruction could
be a python code a more ddrc code in
other cases it could be a library
function handle
or the underlying assembly code that we
are going to go and execute on the hub
okay so this high level idea of
abstraction implementation is going to
be something we'll keep revisiting
throughout the course of this lecture
episode
okay
and specifically in our class
we are going to visit four kind of
abstractions you don't have to you know
we wouldn't talk about details about
each of them but i just want to give you
a high level
guidelines so however what we might be
able to talk about so these four
categories includes the competition
graph
tensor programs that correspond to rupee
operations library runtimes that's you
know usually uh how
power vendors try to go and optimize
typical machine learning operations and
at the lowest level there are also power
primitives that we make into
the native
power and
use those primitives to offer
programmable machine learning
acceleration so these are the four
things that we're going to visit in a
later part of the of the lecture series
okay so that's the end of this overview
and i'm going to
end with some of the logistics and
disclaimers so first of all
well we're in luck and it's really a fun
beginning it's the first course of its
kind likely in the world
the materials and content as a result
are still being developed so as a result
sometimes you know we might encounter
issues in content and assignments to
bear with us
on the other hand given this is
something that's really exciting or
difficulty together it's also a fun
topic that we're also exploring together
as a community so i'm really looking
forward to
you know chat more about some of those
ideas and also explore them together
with everyone who you know in the
community to develop this fun problem
in terms of logistics this is the first
episode then we'll be posting recordings
onto youtube and all the and the links
will be posted on course webpage
uh for some of the lectures we are also
going to have code exercise that help us
to be able to understand those detailed
abstraction concepts
most of the code accesses will be posted
on github and you will be able to find
them on the lecture website as well
and there will also be self-contained
test cases that you can fork and try and
self-assess on how you are doing
and after every lecture there will also
be lecture notes that will be posted to
mlc.ai
that correspond to you know written down
explanations of some of the things we
talked about in the corresponding
reaction
finally if you go to mlc.ei there are
also links to the
uh
discuss forums we are going to use
github discuss in this case
and you will be able to you know feel
free to bring any questions or any
thoughts feedback draw course and so on
okay
so this is the end of this episode
um to summarize
machine learning compilation is a
process that helps us to take in
the
machine learning executions in its
development form and while trying to
bring it on to an efficient and compact
deployment form there are several goals
such as interrogation dependency
minimization leverage power native
accelerations and optimization general
we have talked about reasons why i want
to study more compilation
um including things like giving in-depth
view of about deployment
help us to optimize um deployment
optimizations build up software stack
from ground up and importantly have
found through the process
we also talked about key elements of
machine learning compilations
specifically most of machine extrusions
come with cancers and cancer functions
of course in other cases there will be
other objects other than tensor that
goes beyond you know multi-dimensional
intensities but tensors will be the main
object of interest they will come back
and visit
if time permits we might also talk about
other additional
data structure that can also be
interesting such as strings and you know
other form of test data structure but
most of them are going to center around
the tensor and tensor function
obstruction
and importantly we have talked about
this idea of abstraction implementations
and in a lot of cases we are we can
represent the same tensor function in
different form abstractions some are
more specialized than another one
and a multi-process really trying to
figure out how we can take the tensor
function in one abstraction
convert it and transform and optimize it
to another which could sit in the same
abstraction or different obstructions
and throughout this process
being able to not get into an
implementation that
or you know a more detailed obstruction
that that can run on the deployment
platform
and finally give us a deployment form
that is more effective
with dependency minimize
and leverage the howard native
accelerations okay so
that is today's lecture
and thanks everybody for listening and i
will hopefully we'll see you in the
forum and let's begin this journey
together