Okay. So as you may see today we're
going with lecture 13. Then if you
remember last uh this Tuesday was
lecture 11 and it was not a mistake that
I skipped the lecture 12 because lecture
12 I pre prepared to be more advanced
out of order CPU core design. Then I
have some content from last year. Then
this year I really want to rewamp it.
redesign the whole slides and redesign
the whole structure. So it took me
longer than I was expecting to prepare
that slides. So I decided to bring the
next one. So we go into the next um unit
first then we talk about the out of
order core design. Okay, just give me a
little bit more time to prepare that
lecture. So we're going forward a little
bit to talk about the memory system will
be our next unit. Um so as a just just a
general structure of this whole course
we're we started with the basic the
binary logic the combination logic
sequential design that's the first unit
second unit is GPU architecture then we
talk about the CPU architect CPU core
architecture right so CPU core
architecture
should take four lectures then we talk
about the memory system the memory
system should have two system one is the
basic memory system. One is more
advanced memory systems.
Then finally we go to um
the last unit we'll talk about some non
traditional computer architecture. So
we'll talk about spatial computing
systolic array CG is those are basic the
um architecture is powering the MPU the
neural processing network or TPU tensor
processing. uh tensor processing unit
right so those are the these are the
structure of the whole course so we are
about the half of the semester the next
week is our spring break right so after
the spring break we're going to continue
with or the autofolder
lecture but let's bring this memory
system the cache design first okay so uh
when we talk about memory system then
let's first look at the interface
between the processor and the memory
system that trade them as just two black
boxes, right? The processor you can
consider it's a one group of sequential
logic that is controlled by a clock. Now
our memory system is also another group
of sequential logic that is controlled
by the same clock. Um now if you
consider this is a oversimplified
structure then in real situation we have
the cache system and the memory system
as two different systems. So typically
the memory system works to the cache
system have the same clock signal with
the processor the course and the DM has
another independent clock signal but as
a simple case we design in this way we
draw in this way so we have
some we have some buses here those wider
ones are buses so there's a bus that
sends from the processor to the memory
that is the address right so we tell say
which address that we want to write or
which address we want to read
typically for most of case there's a
predefined sizes of the read so we read
a certain size every time we want to
read
if you want to have a memory system that
is slightly different we can have
another bus just send a few extra bit to
say are you do you want to write four
bytes or eight bytes or something Right.
Then uh another thing is the right data
and the read data. Those are data buses.
Now for some system those are separate
buses because they have different
direction. For right data the direction
is from the processor to the memory. To
read data is from the memory to the
processor. In some um circuit design we
can allow birectional communication.
Then the read data and write data shares
the same bus. Uh I want to just
highlight one thing.
So we we talk about the memory system
right. So talking about the address then
so this is the processor
and on the other side we have the let's
say cache for example. So we have a few
different ways to design the interface
here. So for address
that's definitely address that's a fixed
the size typically something like 48 or
something right we have talked about we
don't really need 364 bit address
every bite
then
the first method here is always a cach
line read or write
or at least a fixed size
that means we write we read or write
like 64 bytes, 32 byt or 128 byt every
time we do read and write. That's one
way. The second way is to have sizes
as information
that pass to the destination. Typically
we may need five bit that's probably
good enough. Five bit is more than
enough. We don't want say every site we
want four bytes, eight bytes, a few
options, right? In that case we need a
few bits to to tell say how many how
many bytes we actually want to read or
write at this moment.
A third method that is used by GPU that
we didn't talk about this part is a
dirty mask.
What is a dirty mask?
So a dirty mask works in this way. So
for example, if when we want to write
when we want to read, we always read a
certain size say 64 byt in a unit. Then
when we write data sometimes we don't
want to write say a lot of data. We only
want to write four byte or eight byte,
right? But we don't we also don't want
to pass sizes because that's extra
information. So we pass a dirty mask.
Dirty mask working this way. So they say
every bit represents four byte
information. Okay. So that means where
smallest granularity of writing is four
by inside. Then in that case what we do
is we have a dirty bite dirty mask that
work in this way. 0 0 1 0 0 for them one
bite information. Okay. That means the
first four by 0 to three is clean. We
are not writing this thing. So you can
discard this part of information.
Then this part discard this part
discard. Now only here from 8 to 11 from
12 to 15 these are this part of the data
that we actually want to write to the
main memory.
Okay. So this is a dirty mask that they
say which part of data that we actually
want to write into the memory.
This is another way to um
solve some of this interface design and
this the dirty mask actually works the
best for coherency control. So what is
let me talk a little bit more here. Okay
so coherency control. So
know this is a little bit going towards
the second part of the
memory system design. So this there's a
particular scenario called false
sharing.
What is false sharing? Say this is one
cache line right?
This is one cache line 64 byt. So the
first 32 byt and the second 32 byt. In
one scenario, say one core
needs to work with the first 32 byt and
another core works needs to work with
the next 32 by right. So
but if we have a situation where we have
a fixed size right every time we write
64 byt
there will be a problem right so if I
write 64 byt we actually didn't modify
this part we think we don't okay then we
we just write the original value back to
there right then for the second core we
think the first half is not modified and
we keep this value unchanged right so
then this core writes we change your
So time one
core one
write the purple version. Okay.
Then this part the double curvy line is
the part we modified in time stamp two.
Core two did this.
Okay. So what will happen is this part
is not modified and then this thing is
removed overritten by this the second
core. Right?
So this is a coherency problem and we
have talk briefly talked about coherency
problem. If we have dirty mask, we say
okay this part is dirty. Let me use
this.
This part is dirty.
Then although we carry the data from
this part, don't use that because that's
the part we're not we do not want to
write. And when we write core two, when
the core two writes, we mark this part
as dirty.
Okay? Then we write this part. then
don't use this part. Then we solve that
problem because they're merged together
using dirty mask. Right? So that's why
dirty mask is super convenient for GPUs.
They do not need to consider this type
of coherency nuances in this situation.
Okay. So three different ways that we
always read and write the same size.
Second way is we pass the size as a
extra field a few bits. The third the
third way is to pass a dirty mask.
Right? So you may ask why dirty mask is
al also extra data that's probably have
more data than size field and why dirty
mask is still useful because dirty mask
is good for coherency control especially
suitable for DP
question.
Yeah. Um dirt mask is only used in cash.
Um
um
let's see dirty mask.
I I would say this is a dirty mask is a
matter of memory interface. So it can go
to the memory. So do not really think if
it's actually a cache or memory. It's
just the whole memory system. Okay. As
long as we need merging dirty mask is
helpful. Okay. It can apply to memory.
Okay.
Then
so there are different technologies for
memory and we have talked about this.
There are even more other type of
memories but mainly we talk about SRAMM
and the DRM. SRAMM
is actually flip-flops and registers for
every bit. Now but we need to consider
how many gates how many transistors we
need for every flip-flop. Remember when
we talk about flip-flop then it takes 20
something 20 to 40 transistors but
that's a full flip-flop that requires
read logic and write logic. Then if we
build it in a really compact way then a
big array of flip-flops share some
output ports and share some control
we can reduce it as small as six
transistors. So six transistor is
typically the amount of transistors that
we consider for every bit that we need
to store on chip.
And looking at DM is dynamic RAM. So DM
if we write the DM symbol we typically
write in this way
or the unit that we store in one bit we
typically write in this way.
Okay. What's this? This is a capacitor,
right? Nothing special about a
capacitor.
Um, so how it stores data is it stores
charges
on a capacitor. Let's say if there are
charges, then it's a one. If there's no
charge, it's a zero.
And that makes a problem, two problems.
How do you detect if there's charge or
not?
Basically what you do is you build a
circuit
then you put a
the current meter here right so it
detect if there's
uh electrons flow through this uh
current meter and if it it's not zero
then that means it's charged if it's
zero that means it's not charged.
So what's the problem with this
is every time you need to detect it's a
closed circuit right it's a closed
circuit that means you release the
charges from there so that means every
time you want to read the data you have
to write the data again back to it okay
so that's one reason why it is slower
when this movement is a lot of things on
the other side
if this a capacitor no capacitors are
perfect. So it may lose charge on its
own. So it may store some once then
after some time if you don't recharge it
it will become zero.
That's a that's something that we cannot
accept. Right? So what we can do is we
need to prioritically
read the data and write data back to DM
that and we need to be safe. Right? We
cannot we cannot even lose a single bit
of data. That means although for 99% of
time we can wait for I'm just making up
this number. This for 99% of the time we
can wait for one second but we can
tolerate a possibility of probably
0.00001
chance to lose any bit. That means for
every millisecond or uh 100 microscond
we need to read everything
then write back again right so it
requires refreshing so whenever we need
a refreshing it's like a global hiccup
that everything need to stop we cannot
read to DM we cannot write to DM the
only thing we can do at this time is
refreshing that's why DM is slower
okay so um but what's The advantage of
DM it's a capacitor and every transistor
can double as a capacitor.
Okay, every transistor can double with a
capacitor. That means this is one t we
we call SRM we write SRAM as 60 T six
transistors for DM
we write as one T and we call it 60 T
cell and one T cell. Okay. It only
requires one transistor. This one
requires six of them. Then so that means
this one is slow but we can build really
large ones. This one is fast. We can
build really small ones, right?
So
we want both, right? That's computer
what computer architecture computer
architects do. We want both. Then early
stage we can use DM but later on we
definitely need to consider SRAM. So we
need to combine the advantage that we
want both low latency and high density
or large storage. So what we can do is
we typically build this use SRAMM
technology to build cache
then use DM technology to build memory
but that's a typical design. If in some
special design use if you want to use a
DM to build a cache is that okay? Yes,
it's totally okay. Now for sometimes DAM
can serve as a cache for hard drive.
Right?
This one is even slower but even denser.
So we can use the as a cache for that
one. So we're talking about two
different things. These are electronic
technologies.
These are how we use it, how we treat
it.
Then for cache then typically we
consider this is programmer transparent.
Then for memory this is something that
we can program. Okay.
Okay. So uh yeah those are some
comparisons of different technologies.
Then speed main memory and virtual
memory that's uh virtual memory or
storage that's hard drive.
So we typically draw a cache memory
hierarchy in this way. We have a core
and we have cache and we have memory.
Cache is sits in between and sometimes
we even want multiple layers of cache
because consider if you have a core,
right? So there are always some parts of
the circuit that is closer to the core
and some parts of the c chip is like
have some distance from the core. So the
this the part of the circuit that's
close to core is a scarce resources and
we have to use it smartly. So then we
need to put the the fest cache next to
the core. Then we have multi-level
caches.
Now we want to cache to store frequently
used data. Right? If we keep using this
part of data then we can
have higher effective bandwidth and
lower latency reduce the average
latency. And it's architectural
transparent that means the um ISA
doesn't really define that if you really
need a cache or if you do not have a
cache
then for some systems we have different
level of caches then like remember in uh
when we talk of GPU we talk about there
are two level of caches right the L1
cache is the core side cache L2 cache is
the memory side cache uh for CPUs it's
more common to have three levels of
cache. The L1 cache, L2 cache and L3
cache. L3 cache for CPU or L2 cache for
GPU is also typically called the last
level cache which serves as a proxy for
DM and the bandwidth booster. So in many
cases for every communication that goes
into the DM then we have to go through
the L3 cache.
Then that brings to this terminology
called locality and locality is why
cache is useful.
So um
how we define locality this is a term I
find in the dictionary or Wikipedia that
is a tendency of accessing the same
addresses or closed addresses. Right? If
we have accessed the address
address some data then very likely we
need to repeatedly access this the same
piece of data again and again. Um so
some variables are really hot. Yeah
means hot that means we can keep we need
to keep accessing this data again and
again. Then it also sometimes if I
access this piece of data then immediate
will need to access to process the data
next to it right in a for loop or
something. So that's a also very common
to access closed data. Then
immediately you can see there are two
concepts. One is the same address and
one is the yeah I'm pointing to my my
screen
same address or close address right
there are two different things and so
there are two different terms here. We
classify them as temporal locality and
spatial locality. What is temporal
locality? Temporal locality is if a
program access a main memory a memory
location is likely to exit again soon.
Okay. Or at a later time. So we access
at the same location later on at a
different time we access the same
location. Then that means that that
describes that can be described with
temporal locality.
Now if a program access a memory region
location it's likely to access its
nearby location soon then we're talking
about different locations right in this
case we talk about spatial locality that
means there are different locations
you know for example when we're
iterating array then we're
we demonstrate spatial locality on the
array itself but we demonstrate the
temporal locality on the uh iteration
variable.
Okay. So what's the implication here?
Then one implication is we need to keep
access recently accessed data in the
cache. On the other side spatial
locality is we need to keep nearby data.
Okay. Then
so once we fetch a piece of data we need
to fetch more data than the exact data
that we're accessing. Okay. So on on the
other thing on the other side we talk
about instruction cache and data caches
right for CPUs we have we last time we
talked the CPUs have a hovered
architecture or hybrid vanoma and
hovered architecture that at L1 cache we
have data cache and instruction cache.
L2 cache we merge them together.
So why we need L1 cache and L2 caches?
Then last time we talked about the one
reason is we want these two memory
access to happen at the same time so
that we can pipeline the pro uh
instructions right but on the other side
they have different locality. They have
different access patterns. For for
example, for instruction cache, we
typically do not have
um I say for I want to say we typically
do not have very large instructions,
very large programs and I'm falling in a
trap because I typically research on
GPUs. So GPUs doesn't really have very
large programs. That's true. So the
whole GPU cache can typically be
contained in a um L1 instruction cache.
No problem. Then for CPU program we may
have a much larger instruction cache but
the access more likely to be sequential
one instruction after another. Then for
data then we may have more random
more random access throughout the
program. So they have different
locality. We don't want them to pollute
each other. That's why we can put the
temporal
we don't want them to pollute each other
to interference with each other. So
that's why we have one data cache and
one instruction cache.
Okay. So let's talk about the cache and
starting from as a black box talk about
the interface and the behavior. Let's
say if this a cache right we have a read
a then this read comes from we typically
call it comes from the core but
sometimes you cannot treat this core as
a real core because it can be another
level of cache on top of it. Okay. But
just for simplicity we just say the data
comes from the core or from the upper
side.
So when we read a and we need to
consider two cases one is we read this
address 40 and 44. Why these two number
or at least the y40
for most of the time we consider a cach
line as a size of 64 byt right? So 64 in
hex is 4 zero. Okay, I should read as a
4 zero not 40. So that's so 4 is
basically the second instruction, the
second cach line. Okay, so we may read
40 or 44, but we actually don't really
care about 44 in this time because even
if we read 44, we're actually only
reading 40.
So here we have a data bus. Then the
data bus is uh is transferring the data.
Then cach line can have different sizes
32 by 64 byt or 128 byt. Then
okay in this case we actually if you
consider we don't really need to send
all 64 bit into the as instruction as uh
the address bus into the cache right in
this case we actually if we want to read
the data 44 we actually need to only
pass data 40 the address 40 into the
cache.
So at the beginning the cache is empty.
There's no data in it, right? So it can
only store a subset of the instruct the
the data set. So we have internally we
have a dictionary that contains say what
data is stored here because it's not a
full memory. So it cannot store
everything. So we have to remember what
exactly is being stored here. So that
next time we can look it up. Okay. At
the beginning the cache is cold that
means it has no data in it. Okay. So in
this case this is a cache miss that
means data is not in the cache. The
cache cannot provide the information.
If the cache cannot provide information
where we can get the data from lower
modules right the lower module is can be
another level of cache or can be the
main memory. So we just call it lower
module memory. So but just in mind now
we just talk about caching between so
there may be extra caches on top and
below it.
So we read the data after some time the
data is ready then the data ready signal
returns with the data A.
What happens is we write the address A
which is data in this field internally
at the same time we pass the data back
to
the core. So the core doesn't really
know is communicating with the cache and
just realize oh after some time my data
is ready.
So remember in last time we talked about
the instruction pipeline we say a me is
only one stage right that's a two ideal
case one even L1 cache cannot reach one
level latency like two or two to 10
cycle latency is the typical textbook
level L1 cache then if we're going to
the main memory that can take more than
100 cycles for GPUs in some occasion
cases I can even see more than 10,000
cycles for one memory access if the
memory system is heavily loaded.
Okay. So let's say after the data after
first transaction is completed if we
want to read the data a again then we
know okay a is there
we know a is there so we can in this
case we can directly return a data ready
and that's something we call a data a
cache heat because cache finds the
memory in that can cache finds the data
in that case that's a cache heat. You
don't have to have the slides were cache
heat, but let's go with the cache
mechanum. And here we're only talking
about the read process. Let's only treat
it as a read read only cache. Okay, for
right it can be really complex. Now
we're going to either talk by the end of
this lecture or next lecture.
So let's talk about cache mechanum and
how it works internally dig deeper.
So okay. So this is a the
circuit I don't want to call it circuit
is much higher level than the circuit we
draw. There's no gate here but this is a
some is a somewhere between a block
diagram and a circuit diagram.
This is typically what a computer
architects draw. They do not really
consider at the circuit level. They
consider things at this level. What data
are there? maybe some multiplexer or
just one block called encoder or some
comparator there. Okay.
So what we do here is that we have the
addresses right. The address is the
input.
The address is connected to a lot of
comparators
right. So compare if the data equals or
not.
Let's suppose the first one is equal.
Then this one, this line will be set to
one. Right?
Then this line will be set to one.
How many of them? One, two, three, four,
five, six, seven. I don't know why I
draw seven blocks. But typically, if you
consider cash, then it should be either
two, four, eight. Okay? Nobody will
really build a seven entry cache here.
So if this comparator returns true and
we typically will consider only one
comparator can return true right this
encoder will convert this into a number
right
into a number and this number is
connecting to a multiplexer and the
multiplexer is connect on data the data
fields are always connected to the input
of the multiplexer but we only select
the one that can be connected with the
data field Then this one can just
directly go back then to serve as a
cache heat. Okay, simplified case case
of cache heat. Then this decoder
definitely can determine say oh if
there's all zero then we should trigger
some other logic so that we forward this
address down to the next level then we
can read the cache of the next level.
Okay.
So let's say what is in the attack
then we have a 64-bit address actually
we don't really need a 4 bit 64bit
address we can reduce six bit of cach
line offset right with the address
within the cach line is not necessary
and also there are some very high high
number bits because we're c our memory
is not that long then we can also reduce
so we only need to store 38 bit address
there
only
uh 42 address because we only consider
48 bit address and reduce by six.
So actually one more thing that is not
here at least we need one extra bit
there.
What's that extra bit? It's a valid or
invalid bit. Right? Do can we use this
data? It's a valid or invalid bit. That
means sometimes we may store some
address even we probably need to store
address zero when it's empty. It's
initial case. So we when we store
address zero we need to put say oh it's
not valid. Don't use this part of data.
Okay.
Then there's a problem with this design.
The biggest problem is that for every
entry we need to have a comparator.
Okay, for every entry we need a
comparator. Then for a eight entry cache
is not a big problem. But if you
consider a cache with hundreds thousands
of entries then that will take a lot of
dice size. That's not necessary. So what
do we do? Ideally, can we use only one
comparator, only one equal compar logic?
That's a combination logic to determine
if there's a if any of them is equal.
Okay.
So, what we can do is we can do in this
way.
Uh
so what do we do is we use a few bit
we use a few bits to determine where
this cach line can be stored at right
they say with
the address the lower bit of this
address are always the offset okay here
are always offset right then we take the
next three bit
to represent where in these eight
entries that this cache line can sit.
They say if the three bits are 00 0, it
can only go to this entry,
can only go to this location.
Okay, if these three bits are 001 and it
can only go to this entry
and so on. Okay, that's a some trade-off
that we have to take if we only have one
comparator because we cannot have a for
loop to compare this one, this one, this
one. That's that's a software concept,
right? In software, we do that. We just
have a for loop. But just consider if
you have a a thousand interest, then do
you really take 1,000 cycles to compare
all of them? It's impossible. So, what
do we do is we limit. So, if it's 0 0,
we know it's here. We know it's can only
happen in this location.
So we use these three unit as a
comparator as a signal to send to this
multiplexer. So that means this tag will
be wired to this output and the rest of
the address is compared with
the tag information.
Okay.
Okay. So then this will this comparator
will tell if it's a heat or a miss.
Okay.
Then there's a little bit simplify here.
But this three bit also determines which
um
which entry can provide the data to
upper level.
Okay. But a slight simplification is we
do not say if it's turned on or off.
It's going back signal because uh heat
this determines heat or miss. If it's a
miss, then we simply forward address to
bottom level to lower level. Then if
it's a me if uh if it heats
if it's a miss, we send it to a lower
level. Then we turn off this signal.
Then if it's a heat, we do not send it
but we turn on this signal. Okay? So
that's a trade-off. So the trade-off
means our cache size is still the same
but we have more restrictions on where
the data can be stored.
Then we split the cache into eight sets
in this case eight sets. Then we use a
few bit then typically that's the lowest
bit right before right above the offset
to determine which set that this catch
line can reside.
Then
so which bit are set bits then typically
it's the lowest a few bits right above
offset so that we can provide some inter
limit let's say we access the first cach
line the first catch line will naturally
go here then the next cach line we know
go here go here go here go here until
back here here here okay then it
provides an interl effect so then just
even just look at this cash line this
this line this slot okay this set it can
actually cache unlimited amount of data
it's not really unlimited but it can be
everything what whatever that is
provided in the tag part okay encoded by
this 39 bits
but there's some restrictions on where
the data can read
okay so what's the problem of this
access That's it. Question.
You mean the problem? No. Yeah. You mean
the problem, right? Yeah. The problem is
that just imagine if you're accessing a
matrix that you're accessing this way
like vertically. Then they may have to
say it happens to be in the same cash
line right then you only use 1/8 your
cash line your cash then you're the next
one overrides the previous one the next
one overrides the previous one so they
have more likely to have conflict so
that they evict each other
there's a term called threshing
what is thrashing
threshing is the worst case for hash.
T H R A S H thresh or threshing.
Then threshing means you have like you
are accessing multiple you you are
accessing multiple piece of data
multiple cache lines right when you have
this part of program and that part of
program or you may have multiple cores
or multiple processes or multiple
threads then they may access data. So
this one kicks the data for the other
thread. This thread kicks the data for
this thread or this part of the program.
This a few lines of code. This few lines
of code it kick the data from for the
other part of the data for the other
part of the cache. Then eventually
nobody can get the benefit of cache.
Everyone has to get data from the main
memory. Question.
when the thrashing happens. So thrashing
happen in many many cases. Let's just
consider say
let's have a for loop. Okay, the simple
case for loop. Then we say load A and
load B.
Then definitely there are something some
other real logic. Okay. Then let's say
if load A and load B goes to the same
line.
Then this is a for loop. We need to load
A again load B again. Right? So
if it goes to the same line, this is a
miss.
Then it brings the A back to the cache.
Okay. Then B is a miss again.
But we want to load this data. So this
will kick
A out,
right? Then when we execute A, this will
kick B out.
Okay? This is threshing. Threshing means
they kick each other's cash line out. So
nobody can enjoy the benefit of the
cache. Okay. So I'm I'm just saying
these are two lines of code. So it can
happen with two threads or if two cores
share one cache, it can happen between
course. So just different parts of your
program or even two programs running at
the same time.
So this is likely to have conflict. Can
we have some middle ground?
We don't want
we don't want very high chance of
conflict. We have want to have some
extra room and uh sometimes we also do
not want to have a full set of
comparators.
So what we can do here is we can design
in this way.
Okay, this is a little bit complex. We
can set this as ways.
So in this case
we say we still have eight unit right
finally I changing this to eight set
eight entries.
So let's say we want to have
let's say if our data falls into the
same the the first set set one
we don't want to only limit to one place
that it can go
we can we want to provide an alternative
location that this cash can be stored at
in this way in this sense we put a way
one so this cash line can be either
stored here set one in way one or set
one in way two.
Okay, in way two we put here in way one
we put here but they're both set one. So
in this case for set
bit we only have two bit
right because there are only four sets
that means
only there are only four sets. So
uh one cache line can resides in one out
of these four locations right but let's
say if here we have some data that is
already occupied this location now when
b comes in we don't really need to
threat to kick out a because we have a
alternative location to save it we can
save here the set one of way two
okay so as long as you alternative
location then we have
as long as we have alternative location
we have more chance to prevent
thrashing.
Okay.
So in this way we call this two-way
associate cache
because a
a cash line a certain cash line can
resides in two different locations
within this cache. That's two-way
associative.
Okay. Another way to understand two-way
associative is there are two
comparators. So one comparator is
comparing way one and the other
comparator is comparing way two. Okay.
If you have four-way associative
what do we do is we have four
comparators and the cach line can
resides in four different locations and
if there are eight entries that means
the set is two. There are only two sets.
Okay. Only one bit to determine which
set it locates in.
Okay, there are many things a little bit
intertwined together but way set and set
bit comparator those are related
concepts and you need to understand
their relationships.
Okay.
So
then remember when we start two
different cases
these are special cases right? So one
set is one. There's only one set.
Yeah,
there's only one set. But ways are n
that means a cash a cash line can
resides in all n entries within this
cache.
That means it's fully associative. That
means associative, right? What is
associative with what associative is a
cash line associated with the cash line
slots in a cache. What is fully
associative? That means a cach line is
associated is linked with all the cach
line slots within this cache.
Okay.
What is way associative? That means it
can be associated with only that number
of locations.
Okay, equals to number of ways. Let's
say if it's four-way associative that
means a cach line can only stored in
four different locations within this
cache.
Okay. On the other side, we have direct
mapped. Direct mapped that means it's
one way associative, right? It can only
resides in a single location of this
cache
that's direct mapped. So two extremes
fully associative and direct mapped
there are
two extreme cases of way associative.
Okay. So the set the way is a parameter
that we want to decide. N is a parameter
determined by the cache sites. How many
entries that we can have then
the
okay then set is calculated by n / w
okay I mean given examples
let's calculate a cash size
so let's calculate a cash size okay
let's say it's a four-way associative
We have 16 sets
then 64 byt as cash line size.
How large is this cash?
Yeah, just multiply all of them
together, right? 4 * 16 * 64 that's 4096
byt 4k
4 KB cache
okay that's the cache size so as long as
you know these three numbers you know
the cache size or if you know the cache
size
so anyone is missing you can calculate
So let's talk about advantages and
disadvantages.
Um
fully associative or at least on the
spectrum towards that side. What's the
advantage there
and disadvantage?
will will be a what?
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. So there are so many different
ways you can go. So the cache efficiency
or cash heat rate the cash heat rate is
the likely the likelihood that a cache
can that a piece of data can be found in
the cache. The cash heat rate is the
highest in fully associated cache.
Okay.
What's a disadvantage of fully assertive
cache?
Yeah.
Yeah. There's a lot of comparators. That
means D size and energy consumption,
right? Dice size is large energy
consumption is high. So fully
associative is the most expensive
design.
Okay. So what's the then so the
disadvantage and the advantage are
flipped for direct map the cash is the
cheapest the one but the cash heat rate
is the low uh is the lowest right so
very high chance to get keep get
conflict and the utilization is likely
to be low okay
so there's one thing that I want to tell
you before we talk about the virtual
address thing
So just give you a background. So our
our system uses virtual addresses right
the virtual address and physical
address. So before accessing a memory we
need to do a virtual to physical address
translation.
So
what it happens is typically it go
through something. So this is a virtual
address. Okay. This wire contains
virtual address. Then there's one thing
called TLB.
TLB stands for translation lucasite
buffer.
Um it's basically a cache. Okay. Stores
each entry is not a cach line but a
translation from virtual address to
physical translation.
Then it goes to something called MMU.
The question is so MMU is really slow.
It can take a few hundred cycles to
translate one address. So it's very
expensive, okay, to do this. We expect
the highest we we hope the TLB can have
the highest heat rate.
So which way we need to design the TB?
Yeah. Fully associative, right? So we
want TLB design to be fully associative
because of the cost penalty of missing
one piece of data in TB. So we want we
want to spend the DIY and the
we want to spend the D size and the
u energy to get a higher performance. It
worth it. So
then another thing
in a CPU where there are two level
cache.
Okay.
Which on which direction that we should
put L1 cache and L2 cache? Let's
I just create some sort of numbers here.
Okay, L1 cache is 2 to 10 cycles. L2
cache is 20 to 35 cycles. Memory is 100
to 500 cycles making up in this type of
typical system how we should design L1
cache, L2 cache and main memory. Yeah,
not memory only L1 cache and L2 cache.
So I I just want to tell you tell me you
to tell me should this have high weight
associative or this one have higher way
associative.
So who says L1 will have higher way
and who says L2 will have a higher
weight? Okay, the answer is typically L2
have higher vehicle still. Why
first L1 cache it's a huge penalty to
miss it? Typically no because L2 can
handle it. So even we take 20 to 35
cycle is not terrible as long as we can
avoid this
right. So the penalty is not really
large and also the scar remember I say
the this area around the core is scarce
it's a scarce resources so we need to
save area so in this case we can have
fewer comparators so typically this is
typically two to four way associative
for L1 cache now for L2 the penalty is
large and the resource is not that
scars. Now we have more dice sides here.
So we can have four to 16 way
associative at this level. Okay. So
typical design consideration for L1 L2
caches. The lower level of caches, the
higher the way associivity.
Then TB is another story. We'll talk
about that later. TB is the other way
around.
Okay, let's talk about replacement.
It's a replacement. Replacement means to
find a victim, right? Victim means
someone was in the cash very
comfortable, but we have to kick it out.
That's a victim. So, how we can find a
victim? Then if we have ABC two-way
associative, right? Then ABC, let's
assume they're in the same set. Now we
evict the victim. There are several
different ways that we can evict the
victim. Then the most common way that
you can imagine is the least recent used
or LRU. What is least recent use? That
means if we do ABC, we evict A.
Okay. If we do AB AC, we evict B because
A is evicted
closer to current time. Now why this is
helpful
uh why this is commonly used and this is
actually the most commonly used type of
replacement policy because it follows
the at least our intuition of locality
okay
so I I don't think I need to explain
more but like least recently used is
something that commonly used But it's
not actually not that easy to implement
because you need to per maintain a queue
and uh reordering the queue is a little
bit complex in real system. Now it may
take many cycles. Um so what is actually
happening is there uh typically use some
approximation.
Okay. So what type of approximation?
This is one type of approximation. First
in first out. So first in first out
means ABC evict A. then ab a c evict a
because a comes in so we don't need to
swap it um when a is accessed again we
know a is there then it's okay is the
ear one so we don't reorder the queue
first in first out is another method so
and there are some other usage some
other replacement policies one is random
and one is most recently used.
Okay, random is easy to understand,
right? So most recently used A B C then
we evict B, right? A B A C we evict A.
Most recently used is rather also easy
to implement because we don't need to
maintain a queue. we only need to
maintain a just a single bit or
something or just a just a few a few bit
register to remember which one is the
most recently used right
I want you to consider why most recently
used is even a
common thing or it's okay thing
it's counterintuitive right
in what case it can be useful
Okay, let me give you a concrete
example. Okay, vector add in GPU
or Okay, vector add in CPU. We don't
have to say in GPU vector add. So vector
add we write something like this.
Just an example. It's not something
real. What's really happen
I smaller than N I ++
right? Then
uh C I = B I
+ B
uh A I
okay or simple for loop
there are two piece of data
one is the I so typically a compiler can
put in register no problem okay but just
a small example that just consider
there's something that we need to
process or there's some process before
this and after this they're still useful
right and there's part of data that is
we call the streaming part
what is the streaming part that means we
process data we use it we process once
we use it when we're done we discard it
we never need to access this data again
especially in GPU this is more common
type of data processing because we just
process one data we this card would
never use it again. And for GPUs, the
memory access is super super wide,
right? There are 64 of them combined
together, coales together. So very
likely we're processing the whole cach
line. In this case, this streaming data,
these data are not that important.
We don't we don't expect high cash heat
rate anyway.
What is important is this I and what's
happening before that
right so if they access early we expect
them to be highly useful if they can
survive they can be highly useful they
will keep them we let them stay in the
memory system then we remove the
streaming part the streaming part
because they're most likely to be
recently accessed they're not likely to
be useful
okay so this is a common case for most
recently used. Still, even in this case,
I don't really see any
real hardware that's actually using most
recently used uh policy. But just don't
think this is something trash. It's and
be useful.