okay welcome back to machine learning
compilation this is lecture four thanks
everyone for
keeping with the statues
today we're going to talk about exciting
topics so in the last lecture we talked
about how do we build primitive tensor
functions and different ways of
transforming permanent tensor functions
in today's lecture we are going to focus
in on
like you know how do we combine those
primitive functions to really start
doing end-to-end model execution
and as as of last lectures we are also
going to start to do a hands-on
examples on how we are going to do that
so today's lecture is also going to be a
notebook based
to begin with um you know we can install
some of the dependencies that help us to
run through this lecture i want to i
want us to recap a bit
on the overall mlc process that was the
main theme that we had in the last few
lectures specifically
a mlc process can be viewed
as a way for us to take
a model in its development form on the
left hand side
and trying to be able to transform it
onto a deployment form on the right hand
side
of course depending on the specific mlc
process
the development form and deployment form
can differ and a lot of the
task lectures we have spent on you know
how do we define for example a single
tensor parameter functions and today we
are going to think about how do we
really run model and web
and
you know again throughout the lecture
let's keep the following question in
mind
about you know what are the possible
abstractions that we can use to
represent the tensor functions tensor
functions and what are the possible
transformations among the tensor
functions
okay
so in the past lecture we have been
focusing on this part
and today we're going to focus on more
of this this part of the execution where
you know how do we stitch
uh each of the permitted function
together
okay so to do that we will try to
import some of the necessary
dependencies and help the functions
again we're going to use tbm as
as an example for showing some of the
concepts uh some of course the concepts
we teach in this class generalizes
beyond the tvm framework so to begin
with we're going to define import tbm
and we're also going to
import ipods
what of the things that you might notice
is that there are additional
importations that are slightly different
from previous lectures so first of all
we're going to introduce relax which is
a high-level computational graph
abstraction that help us through
end-to-end exclusions
and then we also need to introduce this
annotation
uh
feature that allows you to default
deferred annotation passing in tv and
script
so
in order to run enter model of course we
want to have a real example but the
example also need to be self-contained
so that
we can really understand the details
behind the scene remember our goal is
not only to be able to run the models
but also really understand what's
happening behind
so we're going to use a small data set
called fashion amnest so in this piece
of code simply downloads uh the fashion
admins data from
torch vision and then we're going to
load it in and you know load the first
image
onto that's randomly selected from
dataset
onto a numpy array and if you run this
notebook multiple times you might find
that you know you will get different
images each time you run a notebook but
that doesn't matter because we are just
going to randomly pick one example and
see and build a model that runs on this
example
okay so the download finishes
i'm going to plot the first image
that we had in here so this is the image
and uh in this particular case it's
classified as t-shirt thought so this is
a well
it seems to be a magical teacher but you
know at least the classifier thinks
at least the label of this picture is
t-shirt top okay
so so what we're going to do is actually
we're going to
uh
we're going to use a pre-chain model
that we build for the purpose of this
lecture i'm going to introduce the
specificities of the model
uh specifically you know we can download
a pico file so this is just going to be
a dictionary that way that way that
contains the model weights
and this is a very simple mode
so
um
so here's the model we're going to use
in this lecture
and we're going to walk through
different ways of building those models
including the low-level numpy that we
use in the last lecture as well as
some of the
tbms abstraction on building this
particular uh particular end-to-end mod
so this is a two-layer neural network
and i'm going to walk you through some
of the components of the model
definition so here's the graphical form
and it contains well depending on how
accounted you can normally it's called
two layer because it contains two
linear layers but other people might
also see like these three layers in here
or you know if you look at the
individual operation being performed it
might be five operations it will
separate the matrix multiplication
and the bioset
so
the way it works is that first of all
we're going to take a flattened vector
so this 78 here is just 28 times 70 784
is 28 times 28 which is the input image
flattened as a vector
we're going to pass it to a linear layer
and this linear layer is
defined as the same linear layer that we
commonly use in pytorch and other
frameworks so it's defined as
for taking input you are going to take a
matrix
vector product
of w0 transpose
and then you are going to plot
a b which is what we call a bias term in
here okay and if you want to draw it out
it's like if you have an input
neurons in here
that's x and you have
now
784 here
and you are going to project it
128 dimensions where you know each of
the
output neuron is connected to the input
neural so it's a fully connected layer
and then we are going to add a bias
turning here to try to offset some of
the computations okay
and after after we do this i'm going to
pass it to
a relu layer
black file linear linear unit layer
and then
and then you know as a second linear
layer here okay so so this is a
visualization of the of the computation
we're going to perform
normally in a two layer neural network
we will end with soft max right that
gives a probability prediction so so
typically there will be a
stopped
max layering here and this is actually
how we train the neural network as well
so originally the neural network does
come with the softmax layer
however for prediction purposes actually
we don't have to you know include this
layer because softmax just normalizes
the predictive score to probability if
we want to just pick the maximum value
we can just skip the soft math step and
the only reason we do that is just to
simplify this example so so that you
know we can really write it down by hand
and and and showing how to run
predictions
okay i'm going to pause a bit and making
sure that everybody understands the
content here uh remember that you know
first of all we have
one by 128 so the this is the batch one
prediction
and then in the in the second layer we
are going to have a
hidden layer of 128
passing by relu and we're going to
project it into
a
10-dimensional vector where each
dimension corresponds to the score of
how likely that
this input image is going to be
classified as a particular object okay
so the first thing we're going to do is
we're going to
uh build a numpy based implementation of
this particular model
and the way you do that is as follows so
so it's
pretty
straightforward so effectively
what you do is you have input data x
you first feed it into
a matrix multiplication that corresponds
to this one
and then you plus a bias in here so so
this line creates more into this first
linear layer
and then you are going to do a value
operation here
and a second
linear operation in here
so effectively this is a
code that
describes the end-to-end model extrusion
of course it is a very simple two-layer
neural network but you know
at least in terms of this course the
first time we ever defined something
that really corresponds to a neural
network
okay another advantage is that you can
really write it in hand you can really
see what's behind using without a lot of
the wrapping behind
okay so now we define the model what you
can do is we can
load the model parameters in this case
this fashion address is just a
dictionary of key to numpy so so we are
going to read it
and
and then we're going to call the
function so the way we call it is we
pass in the input image get reshaped to
the
latin format
and then we're going to pass in
the argument that crisp point to w0
first 0 bias w1 and bias 1 here into
this function and finally it's going to
give us the result remember that the
result have contains
different values i can try to print it
out the results
in here
and you if you look at this
you'll find that the maximum value in
here is this value so so
and that means that the predict current
is going to equal zero
and then we're going to get the
uh class dictionaries that's predefined
of this data set
and then
you look up the class dictionary okay
and we can also print the prediction to
see
if it is really
yes
is zero
as we expected
and if you print it out you'll find yes
indeed pretty kind of equal zero and as
a result it predicts t-shirt pop so yay
it's the first time we ever built a
model and this model gives us the right
prediction that is for that you know
t-shirt top this is the t-shirt top
okay so here is the first numpy
implementation of
of the end-to-end model extrusion
so far so good
now
again for the purpose of this course
we're not only interested in these
high-level array executions if you look
at
this code right
each line corresponds to
kind of a sequence of high-level array
computation described by the numpy api
of course this is the kind of fine
um fine way to implement uh
enter neural network and most of the
time we should do that
one thing that we're really interested
in is now what happens behind the thing
and again
in this case behind the scene the numpy
apis called into underlying array
computation libraries dispatches onto
them
and the usually the framework will also
do things like allocating intermediate
memories trying to tie them together and
the other cases people might try to run
gpu execution
so one of the goal of this course we
want to really not only look at the high
level implementations but i also want to
look at what is really be harnessing and
discuss what are the possible
optimizations and transformation we can
do behind the scene
as a result
just like last lecture we are going to
go through a low level numpy
implementation
of the same model
okay so the way low level numpy works is
not only we are going to
use uh we are trying to avoid array
functions and try to unpack the array
functions using for loops
of numpy the second thing is we always
try to allocate explicitly when possible
this also tries to help us to map onto
the real world
low-level executions that might happen
on the framework
okay
so we have implemented the
tensor permitted function a lot of
lecture using low level numpy so
hopefully you are familiar with that i'm
gonna go through some of the code but
i'm not going to
stay as close as last lecture
you might familiar with those layers
right so first layer you have low level
numpy linear zero that's the first
linear layer
where we do matrix
matrix multiplication in here
and the formula remember the formula is
y equals
x
times w
transpose
and if we write it out
this co there in a you know in our index
form in fact it means y i j equals
sigma over k
x
i k
times w
jk okay
and if you read this code
it corresponds to the matrix
multiplication everyone
and this line corresponds to the bias ad
where where b
is a bias term okay
one thing to remember is that just like
the convention in the last lecture not
only we are going to passing the input
of of the lower level num numpy
primitive functions but also going to
pass output like they in here directly
onto the function as opposed to having a
function express the allocate the output
the reason is that most of the low-level
implementations try to avoid memory
allocation as much as possible and try
to delegate as much as possible of a
memory management through the framework
and machinery framework will be able to
do optimization like italian memory
together and so on so this is kind of a
specific low level conventions that
reflects what's happening behind the
scene in a lot of the ml frameworks
so here's a low-level first layer of
linear
uh here's a regular layer and here's the
second linear layer
also you might notice that you know the
first linear layer second linear layer
looks you know almost same with each
other except some of iteration one are
different
and this one particular way of writing
of course we can try to write a generic
code that works for all the shapes
in other cases of ml compilation might
be useful to specialize so to
specifically generate code for the
particular shape of interest and we are
trying to you know directly write it
down in a way that represents this kind
of like a shape specialized case
okay
so so in this case we have
three low-level
permittive functions that correspond to
the first layer the value layer a second
linear
layer after these three permitted
functions will have this low level numpy
mlp code
that tries to tie things together
so this is also
roughly resembles what a low level
system might excuse
enter neural network mode
what it will do is try to allocate the
intermediate memory in this case
intermediate memory contains lv0 lv1
and of course lvw2 is output memory that
we are interested in
and then what it's going to do is going
to you know
first call low level numpy 0 by passing
the input w by 0 and lv 0 as output
after we call this function we'll get
the result in lv0 and then we're going
to call low level numpy reload variable
0 by passing lv0 and populating the
result of lv1 and so on so hopefully
you know
if you go and read the code you'll be
understanding hey this is really a low
level implementation
of the same two-layer multi-layer
perception
uh that predicts the fashion numbness
model
okay
so and we can try to run it and you know
this is the similar code that we're
taking a low level numpy code you're
passing the data
weights uh first layer waste bias and
second layer waste bios you'll get a
result
you try to use arc max to get result and
then you will get the class prediction
and we can try to run the code
in here
if you run it you'll find that hey this
is
t-shirt top so it seems like you know it
gives us the right prediction yeah
okay
so now we have introduced a low-level
numpy implementation of the end-to-end
neural network solutions
next we are going to come back onto the
topic of you know abstractions for
representing end-to-end models and we're
going to construct a equivalent model
in tbm script
okay
so here is a tbm script code that
corresponds to
the same model same model implementation
is slightly long so i'm going to scroll
a bit
and then we're going to come back to
peak key element
remember that in the last lecture we
talked about primitive tensor functions
and hopefully those functions are look
familiar and they correspond to the
primitive tensor functions
that implements the value
a linear layer and the second layer
linearly
and you know if you are
if you are less familiar with it you
know try to take a look at the
electrical notes of the last lecture
that will contain an important
explanation of the tensor okay
the main topic of ingesto is that we
have this additional function
called outdoor function
that corresponds to a function that
assembles
those permitted functions together and
really assembles the anterior neural
network now we're going to take a closer
look particularly at this at this r
function
so
uh
one thing that might be helpful is for
us to take a look at
both
the r function and low level numpy
function side by side
in this case um we can find that there's
kind of like a
almost one-to-one correspondence between
the low-level numpy function and uh and
and the
r function which is a relaxed function
so relax
is another abstraction in tbm that help
us to be able to compose up those
higher level
model computations by calling into those
primitive cancer functions
so if you look at the figure here you'll
find that that's correspondence right so
lb0
and here correspond to
the extrusions on
linear zero
lv1 corresponds to extrusion on
the linear red layer and this out
corresponds to executions of linear one
so there's really a direct response
between the two now let's try to dive
deeper onto
the elements of the relaxed functions so
that we can you know look into
some of the concepts in here
so first of all besides the code view
it's actually very helpful to draw out
the computational graph so this is more
like a graphical view for us to look
into what's going on right and
we have this figure in the beginning of
a lecture
we have never explained what the
actually we have this figure in the past
few lectures will we have never
explained what they mean but hopefully a
lot of them look self-evident right so
this is a view
called computational graph and
if you have worked on python tensorflow
this is the you know the mechanism
behind this thing that drives all the
computations in deep learning frameworks
specifically
each of the node the box here of a
computational graph corresponds to a
tensor function or tensor operation or
primitive tensor operation that takes in
some inputs and outputs
output tensor and in this case
you will find that you know we can find
direct correspondence of each of the
output to
the variables in here
and each of operations like linear relu
and linear
can expand on through
each of the lines
in the
inner you know relaxed
and relaxed function course so each of
the line actually creates one to
one node in this combinational graph
the interesting property of a
computational graph is that you know
this graph will really help us to
visualize what's going on in the model
right so you will
you will not only visualize uh what are
operations that we're going to perform
on the model it also visualize the input
output dependency so whatever it means
we can see that clearly this particular
operation takes in w0
b0 and x as in as input and outputs lv 0
that feeds into value layer so the edges
of computational graph really specifies
the dependencies and how data flows
from one operation on to another
as a result you know computer
architecture and compilers this graph is
also called normally called data flow
graph because it shows how data flows
from one operation to another okay so
this is like one very useful view
and computational graph is also
the most well-known abstractions in
machine learning compilation as well as
machine learning framework so
you might already learn about this
concept in other classes as well
and and usually
in the in the following lectures we
might intentionally use the term
combinational graphs and relax function
in a sense that rex function can be
viewed as a way to represent the
combination graph
okay
so one of the special thing that you
might notice though is that in this
computational graph that we presented
just before
you'll find that there are some special
constructs here specifically this core
tier
construct which is slightly different
from a possible computational graph that
you might have seen before so in this
case
chord here
takes in a few arguments right you have
linear which is the name
of a lower level tensor primitive
functions will have a list of
actually you if you read carefully
you'll find that the corresponding list
of inputs
to these operations
um this corresponds to the shape
of the output from this operation and
this corresponds to the data type of the
output operations
okay
so why do we have this core tir
constructor called tier construct
this is because it's a way for us to be
able to connect the computational graph
operations with the low level parameter
so to explain what does it mean let's
try to review actually a numpy
implementation of this call tier
function
so effectively this chord here function
can be explained by this implementation
so in here
it will try to you know
in verbal language talk about what
that's called here me effectively what
it means is it will take a function
that
that have a
quite special calling convention so if
you look at the functions that you have
you'll find that most of the layer
function arguments looks like this you
have inputs
and then you have output that follows
the input
so instead of directly returning
the output
the lower level parameter function
usually expects us to be able to pass
single input
and then pass output
together pre-allocated output onto the
function
this is a kind of special style of
calling functions and in a lot of cases
it is called destination passing which
means that we are passing the
destination onto the function itself
so why do most low-level functions
follow this convention the reason is
that again we mentioned it before right
we want to be able to avoid explicit
memory allocation as much as possible
and let higher level framework execution
to be able to handle those so that low
level implementation just focused on
really getting the computation right
instead of thinking about how i'm going
to allocate and manage my memory
so as a result a lot of low-level
library functions kind of
sits in this form where you have
explicit input and express output
so having this designation passing style
on the other hand from a high-level
communication point of view we really
want to be able to get a combinational
graph node that looks like this right so
you have input
you have input and you have output so
that you know from a computational graph
point of view we really want to be able
to have an operation that takes the
input and directly return the output
so how do we convert a destination
passing style through an operation
communication graph
this is the implementation and it's
quite straightforward so all we do
is we're going to first
for taking an input shape here
and d type
we're going to first allocate a result
and we're going to call the prime
function which get passed in that's the
first argument
by unpacking the inputs
and end result together so if you have
not used this before in python
effectively this means
prime function
you know if i my inputs
list as x and y
effectively we'll call the prime
function with argument
x y
and the result okay so it's going to
unpack the input list and chord
and now if you compare this
to this implementation if you expand it
out you'll find that effectively means
i'm going to do result equals
allocation
the corresponding shape
and d type
after allocations i'm going to call the
function
with
x
w 0
b0
result
and then i'm going to return
result as my
as my final result of the argument so
effectively try to wrap
the lower level primitive function
that's destination passing style onto a
computational graph style operations
that directly returns the result okay
hopefully you understand what chord here
mean
and this is actually a very interesting
con interesting course that allows us to
be able to embed those low-level costs
directly onto communication
so
you know
um
and if you if you come and review the
original numpy implementation like this
one you'll find that this lower level
number implementation does not follow
this dial right it still has explicit
allocations
and cost
so so why do we need to introduce chord
here are supposed to directly try to
find something that
try to represent this sequence operation
but we can try that
uh what you'll find is that you know we
have a possible failed attempt so you
know don't really do this but there's
one attempt that we can do to take
this code and directly try to turn it
into a graphical form where each of a
node chris one to a function and the
arrows correspond to the function inputs
and you'll find that it doesn't look
really right right you know although
uh in reality we're expecting tuition
like i'm going to execute this one and
this one and this one
but from the graphical point of view if
you just look at the argument
dependencies
you know there's not really a
topological
order between this first and next
operation okay so the reason
is that actually you know because we are
performing allocations and this lower
level permit function directly right on
to the allocated memory
this piece of code no longer
is pure or you know from a technical
change is no longer side effect free
as a result the computations
no longer enjoys the nice computational
property that combination graph
abstraction enjoys so multiple
competition of graph abstraction we
expect each of the function node
that of course will directly only reads
from its input and only
returns its output without writing onto
any of the inputs and it would have also
wouldn't you know try to increment a
secret global variables that sit
somewhere so it's completely contained
on that particular operation
and that brings a lot of benefit from
how you know we can take a combinational
graph and try to directly transverse it
in topological or they're reordered or
if there are parallel passes in a
combinational graph like you know if
they are
if they are the operations like this
i would be able to parallelize
this operation this operation together
without any problem if you know this is
the computational graph form whatever
requirement of a combinational graph
form is that each of those operations do
not contain a side effect so they should
not be able to write on to any other
input argument they have
okay so if we have our our programs in
this common lower level form that that
have explicit writings on true those
allocated memory then you know we can no
longer have a combination graph that
enjoys such properties of course one
idea is no let's try to enhance this
abstraction let's say you know maybe you
want to for each of our operations we
only introduce a read and write
relations
but that kind of defeats the real
purpose in a sense that you know that's
the more complete abstraction so we will
need to rethink how do we how we're
going to rewrite some of the
transformations associated with that
with that abstraction okay
so instead
what chord here help us is try to bring
it back right try to bring
a
permittive tensor function that
explicitly expects destination passing
back on to a computational graph form
that is here on side effect three okay
and by doing that you know we can also
now we have this numpy version of chord
here we can also you know try to rewrite
our lower level numpy function using
this right so here's the implementation
that looks exactly like
what we had on the
on the relax function
that you know
except that we're going to according to
a lower level numpy code in this case
and if we go
and execute on this
you'll find actually you know this lower
level number code was called also
executes correctly right so one thing
that i want to mention is that you know
this
lower level numpy implementation of
chord here
is just a way for us to demonstrate the
semantics of you know what is expected
behavior of quality of constructing
relax
in reality we are going to build things
onto
low level extrusions of course the low
level extension is still going to
contain memory allocations and other
operations
however when we are doing some of the
higher level transformations for example
sometimes we might want to take two
operators and fuse them together or
other transformations that decides what
things can be parallelized computational
graph abstraction is really useful so we
want to stay in complete combinational
graph as much as possible and that's why
we are going to introduce and use chord
here in this relaxed code
another construct that you might realize
by reading the code is that there's a
r data flow block construct in this
function
this also connects back the
computational graph concept we talked
about before
remember that you know
ideally we want everything to be in a
combinational graph form where each of
operations kind of you know
it can represent as a number of
combinations that read some input and
directly returns output so that we can
connect them onto a direct accept
but of course during the mlc
transformations we can get to a possible
state
where we might need to introduce some of
the side effect operations such reading
from file
generally random variables are
well random variable generation
depending on how you implement it it can
be cited free but sometimes it might
contain side effect
or you know in certain cases maybe
simply do explicit allocation
so in this case
we will need a way to be able to mark
the region so the idea is that
although we cannot
make the entire competition in a
combination graph form want to mark
regions where they can be in
combinational graph form while trying to
you know for the rest of the regions be
more careful so that we do not treat
them as computational graphs
so in this case we might introduce data
block data flow block as a way to mark
the region of convention graph so
specifically remember that computation
graph is also called data flow
graph so a data flow block
kind of marks the region of the
combination graph so within this region
all the computations can be viewed
as a computational graph however there
are other operations outside data flow
block
that need to be executing sequential
order with respect to the data flow
block
so in this particular program we have
two data flow blocks
and one operation outside the data flow
block that need to be centralized so if
you have operation outside data blue
block you can no longer treat them as a
direct active graph you kind of need
excellent order
or you need to do more advanced read
write analysis or in compilers term
called alias analysis to be able to
decide whether or not you can try to
reorder or parallelize certain
operations but within a data flow block
like this one you can still view it as a
in this case it's just a linear layer
with
x
w0
b0 you want to feed it onto the value
layer
and then outputs onto gv0
right so so you can you can definitely
view this particular part
as a computational graph
and the second thing is that we also
need to mark the boundary of
computational graph so that's why we
have the output mark that says that this
gv0 can be seen by the other block so in
this case for example a gv0 is being
referenced by
this this particular combinational block
the other variables like lv0 is an
intermediate variable that wouldn't be
seen by other computational blocks so as
a result maybe in optimization we might
be able to you know rewrite them in
certain ways
in a more effective way
in most of our lectures we are only
going to look at computational graph
optimizations as a result you know
likely
for a lot of cases we're only going to
see a model that contains a single data
flow block but it's always good to keep
that in mind in a sense that although
communication graph is very nice
abstraction we may not be able to
represent everything in combinational
graph so we kind of need to be able to
mark the communication of graph regions
and only apply relevant transformations
onto those regions to be just careful
and of course if we know more advanced
compilation analysis
we can try to do other things that goes
beyond the conditional graph but just to
be extra careful don't treat that as a
graph if that's the case
okay
so
if you are you know a bit confused and
about this that's fine in the you know
one thing we can assume uh for the rest
of lectures is that we're going to only
deal with one data flow block which
effectively means that the entire relax
function corresponds to a single
combination
okay so at this point we've talked about
again the um
uh one machine and compilation
abstraction
about
these entry and model executions that
contains the following element we talked
about the computational graph view we
talk about called tier construct that
takes in the
primitive tensor function that's the
destination path itself and turns into a
combinational graph node we talk about
the airflow blocks that marks the
boundaries of combination
okay moving next what i'm going to do is
we're going to you know so far we have
just talked about hey here's the code
and here's what the code means of course
one of the things we want to do is want
to be able to deploy things so we want
to be able to
build uh crisproni module and run it on
the environment in this case we're just
going to run on the same environment
that we're going to be building in other
in the following lectures we'll talk
about how do we deploy on to other kind
of power
so to begin with we're going to again
use the script function to review the
the input a bit
uh
it's a bit long but remember the main
thing that we care about is
is this main function that have a
quality element
of course the rest of element is also
important we have talked about in the
last lecture and we will still be able
to use the transformations that we
taught in last lecture to change but for
the linear zero and linear ones
implementation
okay so in order to turn this on to
executable module what we will do is we
are going to call a build function uh
actually this build function and relax
are still under development so
you know the apis may sound subject to
change
uh of on that hand our main goal is to
just get familiar with or machine
learning compilation flow
so likely you know the overflow is still
going to be the same
and one thing we can do is we can call
relax vmw in this case that will give us
a virtual machine executable that
contains
both uh
extrusion module that runs on
that runs this overall accumulation of
executions as well as the compiled
libraries that
that you know
that represents those primitive tensor
functions okay
so once we build it what we can do is we
can use it to initialize the virtual
machine in this case want to say that
where do we want to store the
intermediate computations in this case
we are building a cpu module
and then
we are also going to generate
data in tbms and the array so data and d
is input data that you know takes the
input
and converting the tvm and theory and
we're also going to convert some of
these multi-layer perception ways onto a
dictionary okay
once we do that
we can
run the prediction so remember if you
look at the function it's the main
function that contains the list of
arguments
of all the weights and bias what we're
going to do is call this main function
with data and the list of parameters
it's going to give us
the final prediction if we read this
prediction
you will find that
the values 12
0.3 9 7 4
7 same as the previous
numpy implementation if you remember
correctly
and we'll be able to
confirm that
this case is a t-shirt
okay
so so the point that actually we will be
able to take
a ir module in this case that contains
both the relax function that describes
how do we assemble together the
primitive tensor functions
as well as the primitive tensor function
itself to form an end to execution so if
you look at this function actually these
two elements both are important and we
have this
global assembly graph extrusion function
that calls on to each of the primitive
tensor functions and one according to
this one it actually invokes this
particular implementation that that runs
that
linear layer okay
so so the key element of anti-executions
contains those two parts right you have
a high level exclusion which we usually
call communication graph parts as well
as a primitive cancer function part that
supports all the
libraries of course
one question that somebody might ask is
you know right now we are
implementing
almost all these
uh primitive tensor functions in tbm and
intensity
in certain cases one might say that hey
i have a library implementation
like you know c-o-d-n or other
information that's already in place i
would just like to call into
those libraries instead of you know
trying to
call into a tier implementation
effectively we want to be able to
replace those functions
by a library function implementation
and we're going to show how to do that
so in this case this is the alternative
relax module
that calls onto three library functions
so so one thing that you'll find is that
you know instead of calling into a
function within the module it's going to
we are using strings in here so
inside the ir module passing what
happens is that this strings will be
interpreted what we call uh
external function
and in this case the name doesn't matter
we're just picking arbitrary names
environment.linear means that it's just
conventional use you can pick another
string
but the idea is that we are expecting
the target extrusion runtime to contain
those functions like environment linear
environment value that implements the
corresponding operators okay so in here
this r dot called here linear effect
means that we are going to call a
function that hopefully is already in
the environment
which is in the destination passing
convention that we're expecting
and this we're going to get a result
okay
of course we cannot directly execute it
because we don't have those functions on
our environment
so normally what we do is we want to go
and register those functions
in here
we're going to register two functions
the environment linear function and
environment value function
onto a tbm extrusion environment
and this is the implementation
of these two functions
so one thing that we're doing here is
actually we are not implementing them
but we're just piggyback
the implementation onto a pie torch's
implementation
so let me try to walk you through the
code and show you what it means so
specifically torch and other many
machining framework have this function
called from the our pack
so dlpac is a standard exchange protocol
what it does is that it takes
x
which is tbm and the array
that contains you know certain piece of
memories that contains you know data in
here and we're trying to convert it onto
a torch
cancer
by trying to try to exchange the data so
effectively it's a torch transfer that
points to the same piece of memory so
this is very important as i said the dl
pack is a way for different machine
learning frameworks to exchange
the the tensor data structure without
having to invoke copies so effectively
here the output torch
points through the same piece of memory
as out in here okay so if i'm invoking
python operations in here
we are mutating
the original
tvf and theory so deal pack is actually
a quite interesting initiative that
involves you know many frameworks and
friends and i'm also
one of the one of those folks and it's
now part of the array api standard that
means that it's going to be supported by
numpy high torch tvm and a lot of other
machine learning frameworks so you know
you will be able to
make use of this and be able to leverage
a lot of implementation from different
libraries to implement your
uh to implement your machine learning
operation another thing that's useful is
that if you're interested in
building new libraries you also also
implement your
operation and try to you know have an
interface towards the eopac that means
that
other libraries like pytorch and
tensorflow and
tvm
will be able to directly take benefit
from of your library as well
so after we convert those onto torch
function that shares the same piece of
memory we're just going to call matrix
multiplication transpose and add
that implements the measurement location
biasing in this case one thing to
remember is that again
arguments in here follows the
destination passing convention so not
only we passing the inputs but also
passing outputs in here and here's a
value implementation here
okay
so this two function registers an
implementation
using pi torch
in an environment in tbm
now we have those functions ready
actually we will be able to grab them
from the environment directly invoked in
but of course the building module will
also be able to run
um and so what we do is we can build my
module with kernel function call
run it by passing the same list of
arguments
you get the same prediction
so for demonstration purposes we are
registering those environment functions
in python environment
in practice
foreign environment of course we cannot
expect yes there will be pricing right
so so there are many ways for us to
register those environment functions
onto the runtime system as long as they
follow the same
convention of input and output and in
tbm there are languages like c plus plus
and other native language java and other
languages that allows us to register
those environment functions now we're
going to visit that in future lecture as
well so this is just an illustration
example how we might be able to
interrogate our library functions onto
to those long time environment and
leveraging in in relax
of course in practice
you know you might see we have example
that
invokes environment function and we have
another example that you know that
directly called new tier right so in
practice we can have a mixture of both
for important in this case
we have
this function that directly called to a
tier function here and then the rest of
the functions called tooling environment
functions is totally fine we'll be able
to build our module that effectively
first called this linear function
and then call to other library functions
and this is also very common in
development because in certain cases
maybe you want to try to study cases
like you know hey for this particular
operator in my mlc process i'm
interested in
manually optimizing see what are the
possibilities so in that case i'm going
to replace it with an environment
function and i'm going to manually
optimize it see you know how it goes
if it works well maybe you know we want
to bring it back to the compilation
solutions as well right so
having the ability to be able to switch
between
those compilation and library
implementation is really important and
as a result you know we want to be able
to support this kind of mixture
and again you know if you try to
build
and run you'll find that in this case it
actually gives you the same result okay
up until now we have built those uh
entrance model functions
with you know all the input arguments
and parameters right you can imagine
that what if i have a hundred layer
neural network then this parameter list
is going to be get very very long
and it's not too convenient to do that
so there are approaches for us to be
able to bind those model parameters onto
the function themselves as cost
so here's an example
that
takes in the
ir module here in this case by taking
model mixture
and bind the main function
with this nd parameter so what this bind
parameter tries to do
is that it will try to
look up the dictionaries and look at the
function name so in this dictionary
actually we have
you can find that they are w0 w1 b0 wrb
b1 and that dictionary contains strings
like w0
you know really the weights of w0 and so
on we're going to basically that
function is going to match the parameter
name onto this name and try to bind the
constant onto the corresponding function
and we can
run that
and if you look at the result you'll
find that
now
this main function only contains a
single argument
and there are
other things like meta constant so this
is what we call meta array
that stores the metadata parameter in
this case metadata
of this entire ir module we are not
printing out the method that because the
waste can be very big but effectively
you know
it allows us to have a mechanism to
store the data onto the meta dictionary
and this meta dictionary although it's
not printed out it's part of our module
so we'll be able to compile it and the
resulting module will contain the
corresponding constant in this case
so if we go and build this
you'll find that when it invokes the new
main right because in this case the new
main only contains
a single input in here so we just need
to pass in a single input and parameters
already binary
again t-shirt on top
hopefully the threshold is the found
data set and
you know
we are getting the same prediction
result and this is a much more friendly
interface right yeah i get input
directly can output the parameters
embedded anymore it's also very helpful
to do that because in certain
optimizations we might want to be able
to write certain parameters like change
the layout and so we are going to
talk about that in the future lectures
but this is one way for us to be able to
transform
algebra to be able to combine the
constants onto the module
okay so far so good we're getting close
to the end of lecture
what we do what we did today is well we
talked about several ways i think four
or five ways maybe trying to you know
how do we
go and build a low level detailed
abstraction implementation for an
end-to-end neural network model of
course it's very simple as only two
layer perception models but hopefully
you get all the details behind saying of
what
uh machine learning compilation or
machine learning framework might do
executing that low-level models
and
and one thing that
that we noticed is that a lot of the
discussions come back to the discussion
of abstraction and implementation right
a lot of cases we are talking about what
are the possible ways for us to
represent end-to-end model execution in
this case we have ir module that
contains the computational graph part
and calls on to either a tensor function
or a library function both follow the
destination python style another thing
that you realize is that although the
implementation of tsir and the library
might be different they follow the same
interface convention of inputs and
output as long as they follow the same
interface conversion
you can use quarter to call both of them
without modifying the other side of code
this is the power this is actually a
power of abstraction interface right
define clear interface that allows us to
interact
with the computational graph
and as long as the interface is settled
down you don't need to worry about
implementation details
another thing is that we may use
different ways to represent computation
at different stages of mlc process for
example you know it might be useful to
start with a higher level conditional
graph in one case it doesn't not even
necessarily have to crisp one don't call
it here function we are going to talk
about some of the higher level
operations in the future lectures
and at certain stages we're going to say
hey i really want to change this to call
to my favorite library i really want to
change it to my call onto a tier
function then we're going to write those
calls onto call those functions so
again the mlc process is about
representing the programs in different
possible ways and effectively doing
transformations
among them so that we are getting
optimized program
and today's lecture is really about a
way for us to talk about what are
different ways to represent it right we
can certainly think about ways we can
transform it as well example you know in
the last lecture we talked about how we
can transform a tensor ir function
one thing you can try to do is you can
try to take the my model mixture take
that linear layer and use the schedule
api to transform that particular linear
zero function onto a different
implementation and see you know how does
this end-to-end fusion uh
performance difference right so so
that's one possible way of transforming
it in other cases we might want to be
able to transform high-level model
executions on a mixture of library and
function course
so today it really kind of established
overall framework that we're going to
use for future lectures in the future
lectures we're going to focus more on
what are the possible transformations we
can do that gets us better performance
but really everything centered around
ir module that contains a collection of
cancer functions and transformations
among themselves
okay
so that's the end of this lecture
and here's a summary that you can take a
look we're going to post the notebook
onto the website and in a few days
hopefully we'll also post some of a
company exercise that helps you to get
familiar with the concept thank you for
coming to today's lecture that was