Okay. So we can get started. Uh
let's continue with cache. Then that's
the last uh lecture for cache and we're
going to talk about cache coherency
protocols. So before we start then
basically
uh what we have introduced in the cache
part that's basically what or the
textbook that I listed on the website
that can cover at the most. But if you
want to go into a deeper um domain talk
about C memory consistency and cache
coherency now I highly recommend this
book. Then this is a second edition.
There's a first edition. The first
edition is kind of good enough. I don't
think there are much difference between
the first edition and second edition. So
this is the the textbook for cache
coherency and the memory consistency.
It's the probably the book that I find
introducing this topic the best. So this
uh I'm going basically going to follow
this textbook uh for this like today's
lecture but definitely for only one
lecture I cannot finish everything. So
I'm giving you uh the beginning
understanding of cash cache co cash
cache coherency then let's see how it
works when we are dealing with a
multiore system when a lot of cash unit
works together. So let's talk about
cache coherency. So we have introduced
the cache coherency a little bit. Then
uh if we consider a simple case there's
a cache and this DM when we are talking
about a single cache that's the when we
think talk about single core system
that's the hierarchy that we have one
level of cache and one level of memory.
When we are starting to have multiple
processors, things are getting much more
complex. Now we're starting to have
multiple cores and multiple multiple
cores connect to the memory together.
Now if we have a one level cache and we
typically have these dedicated caches
because these two cores are running
different thread and processing
different data that they better to have
different caches so that they have
different they do not conflict with each
other then they fetch their own data and
um and they don't thrash each other then
but one level cache is probably not
enough. Remember when we say the die
size the die area that is close to a
core is a scarce resources we can only
have that much of cache that we really
want to limit the cache latency to be a
few cycles. So then we cannot really
build two large caches that is close to
a core. So in this case we have L2
caches. Now for sometimes L2 caches can
be dedicated and for sometimes L2 caches
can be shared and this is more like a
GPU architecture right. So we call this
type of cache
this type of L2 cache memory side cache
and L1 cache a core side cache because
if we have multiple DM unit L1 cache is
only responsible for the data for the
address that is bounded to that DM
controller.
But when we are getting more and more
coarse things are getting more and more
complex that sometimes we may have this
type of architecture that
uh for there's some cache affinity.
So for core one and core two distribute
course three and core four. So for core
one and for core two there is a L2 cache
that is shared by these two cores. And
for core 3 and core 4, there is another
L2 cache that is
shared by these two cores. So let me
quick quickly ask a question. Should I
call this one memory side cache or core
side cache for this L2 cache?
Yeah.
Yeah. It should be called core side
cache, right? Don't look at which one is
which side is closer, but look at what
addresses it's responsible for. If there
are multiple DMs, this L2 is not bounded
with one DM controller, but this L2
needs to be responsible for the whole
address range. If it's responsible for
the whole address range, it's a
core side cache.
Okay, since there are so many level of
caches, so many cache unit and um
they can store one cache line can reside
in different locations and multiple
different versions. There's immediately
a coherency issue. So that's what we're
looking at how we can ensure cache
coherency.
Okay, so let's look at some examples
when cache coherency can be violated and
when that's why that's something that we
don't want. So let's say in ideal case
right both um cores simply read the
data. So this core reads the data we
have one copy of the data and this core
reads the data we have another copy of
the data and suddenly one core wants to
write the data. Now what happens is this
turns from blue to orange version. So we
call this version state uh we call this
version dirty. That means this is a
newer version than the other um version
that is stored in other caches or in the
dur consider for most of cases
especially for CPU we consider right
back caches. Okay.
So in this case we don't write through
there's no right going to the DM. If
there's a right through then this is
orange this is orange. Both of them are
newer version that one is older version.
Okay. But anyway,
this one has a newer version and this
one has an older version. This one has
an older version. In this case, if we
want to read the data, we have no way to
tell there's a newer version that is
that results in another cache. So, we
read this older version, which is not
something that we expect. We hope that
every time we read the data, we read the
most recent data, then we keep working
from that version. Right? So this is a
cash coherency violation and we want to
avoid these type of situations.
So uh what is the ideal case for um
cache coherency?
It's basically you can consider this is
the requirement. This is something very
similar to the case where you want to
avoid data races in a multi-threaded
program. At one time multiple thread can
read the data at the same time. No
problem. Right? But at one time there's
only one thread can write the data. If
one thread is writing the data, no other
thread can read the data. Right? Right?
Can happen must happen on its own. And
we cannot have multiple writes happen at
the same time. So we want this type of
variation that is called single writer
multiple reader variation. So there are
a few conditions. So first we're talking
about a given memory location. Okay. So
we're not talking about two different
cache lines. We're only talking about a
single cache line.
Then for any given moment in time. Now
we call this epoch. Then epoch is a
heavily reused word. But here this epoch
is more like a logical moment of time.
It's not a single cycle. is mainly
talking about like u iteration in the
read write processing that um we just
when we want to finish one transaction
that we are say when we finish one
transaction we see we say the app is
completed
okay so for a given moment in time then
in this app we want either a single core
writes it or some number of coursees
either one or more cores read Now, of
course, no action is totally okay. So,
this is what we're talking about, right?
This is the ideal case. So, for no, no
matter what type of cache coherency
system, we want to create this type of
ideal cases. Now, we should never have a
memory location that is right by a core
and at the same time is either read or
write by some other course. Whenever
that happens, we say that is cache
coherency violation.
Okay.
uh simple enough to understand. Then so
here we want to talk about granularity.
Then previously we're saying for a given
memory location then this given memory
location can be either a good a big
granularity or it can be a small
granularity. Ideally we wanted to do
bite by byte level coherency right but
it's very hard because remember when you
talk about cache the read and write
process always happen with the whole
cach line so we can only deal with a
cach line level granularity that is a
practicality consideration that all
coherency is maintained at a cach line
level then we have talked about false
sharing
false sharing is
typical consideration and typical
consideration for the performance
optimization that in what does for
sharing mean is let's say this core
writes to the first part of the cach
line and this core writes to the second
half of the cach line
then are there any coherency usual then
basically no right so this core can read
and write the first half of the cach
line and this for can read and write
this part of the cach line there's no
problem. So we just keep going.
There's no performance issue. But since
we're dealing with a whole catch line
level, we consider
there's a conflict. Then we have to keep
kicking this out, kick this out, kick
this out, kick this out. We have to
kicking them out so that they can keep
uh cash line level synchronization.
Right? So that's called a false sharing.
So we feel they're sharing because
they're modifying the same catch line
but they're not really sharing because
they're modifying different parts of the
catch line. So this is something that we
want to avoid when we are designing a
system. Um so what are the method that
we can avoid this thing is basically we
can probably split the cach line by half
or use more flags to control more
details about what which part of data to
to memorize which part of the data is
modified.
Okay. So how we can avoid
um cash coherency problem then don't
forget there are some really really
simple method for cash coherency system.
So for example one method is
just look at this one and ignore force
sharing problem right through is
definitely somehow can help with the
force sharing problem right then another
thing another problem is flush just say
if you have multi multi- threads then
multi if your program has multiple
threads only execute one thread at a
time then swap only swap
the threads from the same context from
the same program from the same
application. They only swap another
thread from the same application. So you
are processing the same group of data
from one core. So then you probably
don't really need to consider any cache
coherency issue or another very
important way is flushing. Flashing
means we mark everything in this cache
to be invalid. then we can switch to
another core to execute. In that way we
don't really have cache coherency
problem. So as you can see these type of
problems are rather fine granularity
that we probably flush the whole core or
we limit a parallelism that we can
achieve.
Eventually what we really want is or
whole core or whole CPU multi-core CPU
different process different cores are
processing threads from the same program
and they're processing the same group of
data then in that case we need some
finer granularity to control what can be
read at the same time and what can be
written at the same time. So that comes
to cash coherency protocol. We need a
group of communication method to avoid
cache coherency issue. Okay.
So let's look at what are cache
coherency problems. Now we start with a
protocol called VI protocol
or valid invalid protocol. Okay. So
before I start we start with a bus
assumption. What is a bus? Then bus is a
term for network on chip. And even if
you consider only there are three
players and when we talk about
coherency, there must be three players.
We consider this a bus. And when we talk
about coherency, we always call this
cache. And this is memory. Although it
can be a next level cache. Okay? Even
it's next level cache, we still call
this memory. Just to simplify that,
consider it's only one level of cache.
Then what is the boss assumption?
Boss means
let me put down this way.
So a bus is a group of wires, right?
So let's say if it's eight bite or
something, it's a bus.
Then bus can allow multiple
cores to connect to this bus. For
example, for multiple input and output
entities to connect to this bus. So we
can do this thing.
This is a register.
Then we have another set of register.
Okay.
Then connect to this set of buses. Then
there's another group I'll draw in this
way.
Just assuming this is a receiver. Okay.
So how does the bus work is basically
they're connected simply by
wires. So
if you are not comfortable with directly
connecting with wires, you can consider
this way.
There's a
multiplexer
one group of registers and one group
another group of registers. There's a
multiplexer.
I'm just directly drawing one wire.
Okay.
There's a multiplexer that can decide
who can send onto this bus.
There's a controller.
There's a control signal.
Now, we typically do not control call
this control signal in this case.
Whenever there's a communication
sharing, we call this a orbiter.
We call this an arbiter. So, we it's
perform the arbitration process. That
means it decides who can send onto this
bus, right? Who can send on this bus?
Then definitely there's no way that two
cores can share can send on this bus.
Then only one can send to this bus. So
the bus is the network that connects the
caches and the course. Since it's a
group of wires,
assumption here is that if I send
something through here, right? So
I will remove this and go back to the
first representation.
It's easier to understand in this way.
Since it's connected in this way, if I
if A sends something to the bus, then B
and C can both hear it, right? Because
they're shared medium. B and C can both
hear them. So if A say oh I want to read
some data then B immediate knows oh
there's someone on the bus is also also
someone on the bus is
someone on the bus wants to read the
data right so we can call this u share
the medium so
everyone every participants on the
medium can hear about can overhear
what's happening that that is on the bus
okay So any participant can overhear any
communication that happens on the bus.
So let's consider concrete cases.
Start with a read. The most simple
simple case read. Then when read
happens,
start with a read miss, right? When read
means happens, we need to send a read to
lower level. Then later on the there's a
data ready comes back and goes back to
here. And then we receive the data. Then
once we receive data, remember last time
we have a flag in the tag array, right?
In the tag array. So if this is a tag
here, we're storing the address. But
there are some flags. So this flag is a
BI flag, valid, invalid flag. we just
simply mark it as valid or not valid at
the beginning it's invalid state because
we don't even have this address right we
don't even have this data in our cache
if we don't have it we just assume it's
I state
then when data ready comes back we say
it's a
we say we say we have the data then it
becomes a v state we say it's valid then
filter read can start to read from this
data. Okay. So the vi immediately comes
from the previous
the previous lectures representation
that we marked
using one bit to represent that the data
is there.
Okay. So we want to draw as a state
diagram. This state diagram is not
necessarily the state diagram that we
use for sequential logic design. is more
like a
state diagram for the cache lines. Then
for every cache line there should be
every cache line at every cache there
should be a state diagram to represent
what state they're in. Okay. So in this
case we have a read we convert from a
invalid state to a valid state. That
means we have this data.
Then
consider this case. If we have the data
that is in V state and this cache also
has the data in V state then we write
the data start from right through and
this is the only time we need to talk
about right through okay
in right through cache we write the data
into L1 cache then it goes to the memory
that means on this bus we have a right
operation this right operation can be
overheard by the second cache. Now what
happens is we call this action a bus
write. Okay, we call this action a bus
right.
Then
this V
needs to be triggered by this bus right
because someone wants to write data that
means there's a newer version. If
there's a newer version what we do is we
convert it back to the I cache.
Sorry, we convert it back to the I
state. So this is the
triggering condition. So we have two
type of triggering condition. One is the
processor the PR.
PR stands for processor
that is what the signal that is sent
from the top. On the other side, we have
a boss
that is a that's a piece of information
that we overheard from another player
that is happening from the bus from the
network.
Then we have read
or write
those are actions. Okay. So we have PR
read
and we can have bus right. Okay. So when
we overheard a bus right we know okay
there's a newer version. What we need to
do is we need to convert from a V state
to I state.
Okay. So this is a previously we have a
state
transition diagram. Then we can write
also write a station state transition
table. So in a V state if there's a bus
read we don't do anything right
draw this here
this is our cache we have this cash line
in this state and we do PR read
what do we do now we it's a cash hit in
the have heat just directly respond with
the data there's no need to do anything
on the bus side just directly respond
with data ready
okay on a PR right what we need to do
on PR right
we write the data we are still in V
state it's a V2V conversion
no state transition
is still valid but we need to tell
others that okay I have a new version
right so it needs to trigger a bus right
to tell others there's a new version
okay
let's keep going the next case bus read
we are in V state
incoming
bus read
when we get when we see others are
reading data is that okay it's okay both
of valid we can still read at the same
time so in this case this terms to V and
this terms to V both are valid the data
is shared at multiple locations no
problem and both of them can keep
reading the data no conflict no
coherency issue both of them have the
most recent inversion.
Okay, next case,
bus right.
When there's a bus, right, we know, oh,
there's must be a newer version on the
network. What we do is we convert from B
state to I state.
That means we no longer have the most
newest version. Next time if you want to
read, read from lower levels. Don't read
from the current value.
Okay.
So this is V2 I conversion. Then I tov
conversion is slightly easier. So I I
don't want to draw every cases. So
I state we convert to V.
Uh
there should be a bus read there which
it there should be a bus read there.
Then from I state then there's a PR
right. um we determine depends on this
right through or right or wrong. We can
end up with a V state or I state. Now if
we're in I state there's a bus read or
bus right we don't care this is a cache
line that has no relationship to this
cache unit so we don't do anything
okay the state transition table trying
to draw everything
so we call this type of coherency
protocols snooping protocols which is
snooping protocols is basically by
overhearing okay or by telling everyone
what's going uh from my side is snooping
protocols. So we need to notify peers
upon action. For example, if I run write
the data, I need to tell one, okay,
there's a new version
that's not in your
table.
If okay so if the question is
if I over here someone else need that
cash line do I need it then
you need to consider for different cases
right so at least this is not a basic
cases if you really want to do something
by overhearing other cach caches then
they need to fetch some data I may need
to fetch some data I would call this
prefetching right I don't need this data
but I fetch it just in case I need to
use it in the future and predicting this
type of uh access is actually very
difficult that it really depends on
program to program and most likely that
for modern computers very likely on one
core you're executing one program on
another processor you're executing
another piece of program so you're
accessing totally different data uh in
that case then you better to ignore it
right and actually you you
so in the in the case of V and V that
means a duplicate cache line this
somethings
you want to avoid right whenever you
have a V and V that is a case that you
really need a lot of communication to
ensure
um that proper invalid validation of
another cach line. Right? When we talk
about more complex and more realistic
cach lines, a cache coherency protocols
um you will see we want to avoid VV
situation.
Okay. So I would say for most of the
case the best choice is just ignore it
and in today's real case in real CPUs
especially large scale CPUs snooping
based protocol is not the protocol that
we're using okay so we'll talk about
that soon
but snooping protocols we mainly
introduce snooping protocols because
it's easier to understand so so in this
case we need to notify peers upon on
action. Now we take action we need to
tell others. Now we need to broadcast
that to send this message to other all
other components. For a bus broadcast is
natural for other type of network or
switches then we say
broadcast is not that easy. So since we
need to know a little bit about this
network on chip terminology
we need let's introduce it. So
let's say we have three players right
and they communicate
they
what are the ways that we communicate
then remember in in uh in electronic uh
circuit if we want to connect this way
then we have to have duplicated wires
here and then have two that means we
have two ports on the receiver side that
is one way but This will require extra
resources on the receiver side. If we
cannot accept that, what we need is we
need a switch
that determines which one can go data
can go here and where is the destination
is a switch. Okay. So there are
different ways can introduce this
switch. Then the first one is a bus. I
just call it a bus switch.
Now we talk about bus switch. The bus
switch is typically just a bus
that the players are all connected to
this boss.
Then there's a a beater
that can control the bus who can send
the signal and everyone can receive the
signal. So we need to have some extra
bit of data to say oh this signal is for
you and this signal is for you. So we
know who is the destination. So it
really depends on the actual system
design here. This is a bus switch. Then
what's the advantage of bus switch is
definitely simple right and the low
latency and it's easy to broadcast. But
what's the disadvantage of bus switch?
Just consider if you have 100 players is
connecting to this bus and basically
everyone is queuing up just waiting
there to grab the medium. Right? So what
we do here is we can have a second type
of a second extreme that we call it Xbar
or crossbar.
Now we have talked about crossbar before
right? What is crossbar? Let's say 3x3
crossbar is this way. They're not
connected as this crossing point. This
is player one,
player two,
player three. Okay, here is player one,
player two and player three.
This is receiver side and this is uh
sending side. So the there's also need
to be aer
PL1 needs to send to PL2 and this one is
connected. PL2 needs to send PL1. This
is connected.
Let's give a better example. PL3 to PL1
and PL2 to PL3. I don't want to PL3 to
send to PL3. So
these are these connections are
programmable. Okay. In this case, we
connect these two wires together. It's
all done by comial logic.
It's effectively connecting these two
wires. So the signal can go this way.
Right? So what's the advantage here is
if we have n players, we can send n
messages in one cycle. Right? So the
bandwidth is much larger. Concurrency is
much larger then but at a cost if you
really want to broadcast it go backs to
a bus, right? So broadcast is really
difficult in these cases.
Um so
then broadcast is something that we want
to avoid when there are lots of players
when there are a lot of different caches
there. When the when the system becomes
a larger scale we prefer a crossbar
other than bus switches. Okay.
Then crossbar also have scalability
problem. When we're dealing with 100
players now probably we don't want a
crossbar. We want multiple levels of
crossbar so that we can
control the communication or just use
some switches to relay the data to the
destination but at the CPU level
crossbar is typically good enough for
GPU level crossbar is not good enough we
need some other method okay so for
snooping protocols since we assume it's
a bus then we have we
can assume we can understand the pros
and pounds. So for small system it's
definitely low low latency that we can
immediately send the result out right
then it's simpler design that we send
the signal then others can overhear it
there's no way there's no need to say oh
I need to send to this one or send to
that one and scalability is a problem
because it's limited by the bus and the
traffic overhead that means if there are
a lot of traffic then the bus can become
the performance bottleneck there
so what is
improvement and what are the solutions
when broadcast is not likely to be
possible is we have this directory based
protocols let's see how it works so when
we have a right signal right we send a
bus right and we don't call this a bus
right because we're not carrying data to
bottom we're only sending a coherency
signal say oh I'm writing the data okay
this is I call it a coherency right
then The memory side the memory
maintains a directory. So we have tax
right we can have V and I we can have
everything. Now we also need to record
who are the owners who owns who have a
share of this data. Now in this case the
owners may have a one and two or a b
right. So we need to have some way to
identify them numbering them. So we need
to remember who owns that. Now typically
if have eight L1 caches now we simply
need eight bit to like if it's zero that
means that one doesn't have it. If it's
a one that means that corresponding L1
cache has it. So it's a mask to remember
who are the owners. In this case we know
oh this is another owner right then we
send a directed signal to the
destination and we call this a shutdown
signal. It's a shoot down that means it
goes from the next level to the top
level. Say was previously in the V state
now I need to change it to I state. You
shouldn't have it. There's a new version
invalid turn to invalid. So the signal
goes from the bottom to the top. Then if
there are multiple owners then we just
send multiple secure down signals to the
owners so that all of them turn from V
state to I state.
Okay.
So as you can see we we say it's
equivalent to a snooping space signal.
Basically it's if the effective are the
same because we eventually shoot down
all the other copies on other level of
caches right then pros and cons is more
scalable. It has higher network
coherency because network concurrency
because of we can use a crossbar there.
We can use some other type of network
but it's more complex and it needs this
extra storage that is stored at next
level of cache and it has higher latency
because we need to send a coherency
signal to the next level cache then the
next level cache will send another
signal back to the top. Okay, this is we
do not consider the bus arbitr
arbitration process. Then if you
consider the bus sharing or the queueing
process of grabbing the bus medium that
may take a even longer time right in if
we're not properly designed so there's
trade-off trade off between directory
based protocol and the u snooping based
protocol so
um it's also something that if you start
to design a multiore system multiore CPU
it's always better almost always better
just to start with snooping first
because it's simple then when it fails
when it really needs scaling then you
start to use directory based protocols
okay direction
based protocol is the typical use for
high-end CPUs
when there are a lot of cores
then
vi I want to also want to say one thing
that is not on a slide So when people
say GPU cache GPUs
uh G what's the coherency protocol that
GPU uses then if I feel it's really hard
to explain I would just tell them GPU
uses a VI protocol
uh because GPU does record if a cach
line is valid or invalid in their cache
but it's a little bit oversimplification
to say GPU also uses VI cache protocol
because there's a lot of similarity,
right? GPU has a like a V state.
GPU has a GPU has a V state. When
there's a V state, we have a right
through. Then this right through serves
as a bus right signal, right? But
actually on GPUs, the other cache
players doesn't really care about the
right. you just write through then it's
okay you write through then if there's a
if we have a VV case then let it happen
let coherency bad coherency happen no
problem then that's a programmer
responsibility to not write that type of
code right so
in theory I would more prefer to say GPU
has no coherent protocol rather than GPU
uses a vi coherency protocol okay so GPU
never overhears another
um a bus right or something. Okay, the
GPU today's GPU even a crossbar is
cannot really fulfill the scalability of
a GPU let alone a box.
Okay. So then talk about the VI
coherency protocol. What's the advantage
and disadvantage of OI VI coherence
protocol? Now we can see it's simple,
right? And it has minimum overhead. Even
if you don't use VI coherency protocol,
you need Vbit or the VI bit
just for the cache itself. So basically
there's no extra state uh storage state,
no extra bit that you need to store. The
cons is every right generate a
broadcast, right? So that basically
makes right back cache not useful at
all. Then you you can implement a right
vi protocol on writeback hash but you
don't need to write back the the data
but you have to write uh you have to
still need to generate a bus write
signal
on the bus so others can overhear this
message. So then that's no there's no
point to have rightback cache because
you eventually have the delay the
latency for right operation right. So
that's something
we want to avoid. So let's see what
other type of coherence protocols or how
we can refine a vi coherence protocol to
make it friendly to
write back caches. Then we have MSI.
So as you can see these cache coherency
protocols are
just keep adding letters there or split
one state into two state.
What is MSI? Basically M and I M and S
are two substate of V state. I state is
still invalid state. It's called
modified shared invalid state. Invalid
cache coherency protocol.
Let's look at this case.
When we read the data
and we read
from here then when the data ready is
back we mark we have the data and
remember it's it should be v state right
but in this case we either have to
select it's a modified state or share
state
it's not modified so it's a shared state
although in this case we don't really
know if other caches are have another
copy of this data. In this case, we
simply mark it as shared.
Okay? Because we don't know. So we mark
it as shared. Shared means the line is
clean and peers may hold it. May or may
not hold it. We don't know.
Okay.
So in this case, if another cache reads
the data, it's basically go through the
same process. That means we the event is
a PR read
the state before is I bus action is a
bus read we need to trigger a bus read
we need a data anyway so we need a bus
read then in this case we have the S
state that also says if we're in a S
state and we overhear a bus read we stay
at S state it's okay right
So
more complex case is right when there is
a processor right what state do we
change to and what do we really what
signal we need to generate on the bus
then can we just simply generate a bus
right
uh in this case if we are in a shared
state right we don't really need a bus
right
because we want to write back cache
but here what we do is we then we we can
convert into a modified state. A
modified state means
others cannot have it
and I am I have a dirty version. I have
a updated version. I have a dirty
version. So that's modified state and in
this case since m represents
since m represents u modified and
exclusive state then exclusive means I'm
the only owner of this cash line there's
no no other copy can exist it's not
shared now I have to say I have to shoot
down other copies in the system. So in
this case although we don't really need
uh read the data or we don't really need
to uh write data to the bottom we send a
signal called bus read exclusive.
The purpose is not mainly for read but
for the exclusive part that means we're
shooting down other cases. If other unit
has this copy they have to convert into
I state.
Okay. So consider if other piece other
modules have M state or S state, they
have to convert it back to I state
because
there's another module on the system
claims exclusive
exclusive um exclusiveness of this cach
line.
do
in this case if we want to do a PR read
again then we generate a bus read in bus
read in this case
um
Sorry.
I need to check this.
Should this state in M state or in
should it convert to an S state?
Okay. So, but a bus read can trigger a
bus rate. No problem. But this bus rate
should be overheard by this one, right?
Uh do I have it bus rate? Bus rate. I
don't even have it. This one should
actually convert from M state to S
state. Okay. But I can confirm this with
you later.
So
in this case, there's a bus read. Now we
actually need to trigger a bus right.
This is a write back operation that can
write the data back to the
memory. Now in this case we can provide
the data back to this side and this side
becomes an S state and this one becomes
to a I to a I state
uh or S state depends on the
implementation.
Okay.
So
there's a there's a situation here. So
as you can see MSI it has a one
situation that
um when this is in a shared state right
when there's a shared state and when
there's a processor right we're
converting from a shared state to a
modified state. Whenever we convert from
shared state to a modified state, we
send a bus read exclusive. And at this
stage, we don't really know if another
cache has a copy or not. It's just to
send this with precaution. We just
always send this exclusive say I wanted
the exclusiveness and others need to
overhear this and to check
do I need to invalidate right now in
this case for many cases if we're
processing this piece of data again
again we write this piece of data again
and again we we read and read this piece
of data and write this piece data again
then this message is redundant we
actually don't need to send this one if
other caches doesn't really even care
about this um cache line. In this case,
we generate a lot of unnecessary
invalidation, right? Unnecessary
validation are in unnecessary signals
sent to the bus and we want to avoid
this situation. So
in this case, we just further expand
this MSI state to MEI message state.
Then we add one extra state called
exclusive.
Let's look at this M state and S state.
So what does M state and S state
represents? They represent if this cach
line is clean or not. In modify state or
cach line is not clean. Right? It means
it's dirty. It has a newer version. in
shared state that means we know lower
level where other sharers they may have
the same version it's okay so it's clean
it's the same version as other sharers
now another type another message is say
is it private that means do I really
have this one the M state represents
it's private we are the only owner and
it's not clean the S state means it's
not private
or we don't really know it can be
private or not private in MS state MS SI
state
okay so there are two dimensions that we
want to record here so there are two
different cases
there four different cases clean and
dirty and private clean and not private
clean and private and not clean not
private okay so in this case we don't
really care about this situation
then so we cross this out and actually
this is useful because we're not going
to introduce this coherency protocol but
there's another coherency protocol
called moisty protocol
you see they just keep adding letters to
this or add state to coherency protocols
m o si
then old state means
not clean
and not private
and we're not going to introduce Moisy
protocol and I can tell you just give
you a quick introduction for how moisty
works why we need old state it only has
one situation that we really need this
moisty pro coherency protocol
let's say this is these are L1 caches L2
cache. We know L2 caches are slow,
right? So in this case, L2 caches are
slower than this L1 cache. If we want
this L1 cache to provide the data and if
this L1 state is in the old state,
then rather than letting L2 cache to
provide data, we can let L1 cache to
provide the data. Okay, that's the only
purpose of the O state. So we're not
going to introduce a moisty coherency
protocol that stayed at let's stay at
Messi MEI and Messi is complex enough
for you to see how coherence protocols
generally work.
Okay, we introduce all these cases all
these state transition diagrams.
So when we want to read the data
then it's a read. So we'll trigger a bus
read right. Then the memory side
can
tell us if you are the only owner or not
the only owner.
How? If it's directory based method. Oh
that's easy right? If all other units
are zero then we can send an exclusive
data ready. So you are the exclusive
owner. You are the exclusive owner of
this piece of data. then it go back to
it can directly go to E state.
Okay. Another situation is if it you
really want to implement this in a
snooping protocol we can allow this to
happen that we can have extra wires. So
when we have a bus read then everyone
needs to update this wire say oh I don't
have this data I don't have this data.
So it can be it's a complex design but
if there's only other one
If there are only two L1 caches, it's
pro is only one wire. It's not very
difficult to implement.
So it can
send a snooping shared signal to say I
don't have this data. If all other unit
send this not shared signal on a
dedicated wire, then we can directly
convert from an I state to a E state.
But if you want to be simple, you don't
want to do directory and you don't want
to add this actual signal, actual wire,
what you do is you can just do it the
same way as say oh I don't know if
others have this data or not. We just
mark it in the shared state. So shared
state means
in this case shared state means the data
is clean others may have it. So just be
caut cautious be cautious when if you
want to write the data. Okay, the
simplest the case now how we can convert
from I state to S state and E state two
different cases
or in other case if you have the
hardware but others say oh they have the
data or the lower level send the data
say others may also have this data then
you still need to convert from I state
to a shared state okay so the basically
What's going on is we're splitting the
MSI state to a the S state, the S state
in MSI to an S and E state or we're
splitting the VI state the V state in VI
protocol to me S state.
Okay.
So if you want to read the data, if we
have a S state or E state, no matter if
it's a S state or E state, it's a read
heat. Whenever there's a read heat, we
don't need to generate a bus signal. Now
we just it's a read heat. No problem.
Now we know this is a fresh data and
just go.
Okay.
So then consider if we're starting from
a I state or S state and we want to
write this P a piece of data what do we
do? So what data that we need to convert
into now and we need to re reh revisit
this table this data is no longer clean
because after we write into this piece
of data right this piece of data is no
longer clean. What we do is we convert
this
um piece of piece of data to M state and
also because M require exclusiveness we
send a bus read exclusive to onto the
bus it just telling I'm the exclusive
owner I'm the only owner of this piece
of data you should invalidate them
okay then in M2M state
because this time we're clear that we're
the solo owner of this
we're the solo owner of this cach line
then we no matter is read or write we
can just keep it in the m state
okay and there's no need to generate a
bus traffic and definitely this time
this is a right back cache and for most
of time we're talking about right back
cache so there in this case one thread
is processing data piece of data again
and again so we don't really need to
communicate across the whole chip.
Then another uni a unique advantage of
the massive coherency protocol is E2M
conversion.
Okay, it's the E2M conversion. Then if
we don't have the E state, then we start
with a S state. The S state means it can
be shared. If we have a s state, we know
others are not really having
um if in east if in if in MSI protocol
we know in in state of MSI protocol we
don't know if others have this data or
not. We can only assume other has this
data. So just be safe then we send this
data we send the invalidation signal or
the bus read X act X out but if we have
a E signal E state right if we have a E
state we know others doesn't really have
this piece of data then we can safely
convert from the E state to the M state
no problem we don't really need to
generate a bus signal we can keep it
local and it a performance improvement
No bus signal required.
Then M2M read on right. This is
something I already talked about. Okay.
Then we need to talk more on
this side.
Uh
if we have a s
this should never happen at the initial
case. S and the C. Just consider this is
start with I. Okay, I and E. So if we
have a I state and we read a piece of
data. In this case we have to tell oh
this the second cache needs to tell oh I
also have this data. I need to send this
signal. What happens is the other side
when start with a E state. Yeah.
When the other side start with a E side
E state and it overheard a bus read then
we have to change to S state we're no
longer exclusive owner of that cash line
then we change to S state in the future
if we want to write into this cach line
we have to send the bus read exclusive
signal to invalidate all other copies in
the system.
Okay. In the M state, then basically in
the M state and also consider this is an
I state. If there's another read into I
state, what happens is no longer not
only we need to share a share the signal
to this side. What we need to do is we
need to have to trigger a right back
signal, right? We really need to first
this one write the new new copy to the
next level. Then we can send the data
back to the
requester.
Okay? Because this one has a newer data.
So then we need to send the right back
signal. Then this one go back to here.
The data the updated back data back to
here. So then they end up with both.
they both end up with a shared state.
Okay.
So I think pretty much I have introduced
all these signals all the state
transitions in a messy protocol. Now
other than sometimes we want to go back
to the I state or in in terms of
invalidation we want to go back to the I
state. Um
so those are pretty much all the state
transitions. Now you can see this is
already quite complex right? all these
state signals then with this type of
state signals and if you really
implement a
cache then you are not only need to
consider this type of signals why
because this type of state because
originally we're saying this happens at
epoch and epoch is a logical time unit
logical moment right in reality you need
to consider cycle by cycle what happens
in every cycle so you also need to
consider the original read and write
back process and invalidation process.
It can be complex. So you really need to
consider something like a transient
state. Say some state like I send out a
read signal. I send out a bus read but I
haven't received the data yet. This
another state you consider this type of
transient state. It's just then later on
if you consider the old state five type
of state then every state you inert it
actually massively increase the state
transition diagram. So it's getting more
and more complex for this whole diagram
for this the whole system design. So
we basically will stop here and just
tell you how messy protocol works. Then
you can forget about how these
directions work, how this state
transition works. But you what you
really need to remember is
to ensure that
to ensure there's only one writer at the
moment. Now we need to send a lot of
coherency signals on the bus and across
the cache systems to ensure to properly
invalidate all other cache unit. And
that's a complex process and require a
lot of redundant traffic extra traffic
to maintain maintain coherency.
Maintaining coherency is not very easy.
It requires a lot of performance
overhead in this whole system and it
makes the cache design much much more
complex.
Okay. So that's why GPU doesn't really
want to introduce this next. Then GPU
focus on the most important parts of the
cache. You want to record data and put
the put the requirement and put this all
the burden to programmer for CPUs then
because they have to consider multiple
thread and read one piece of data then
they have to design the whole coherency
protocol to make CPU work then
there's something that in recent years I
don't know if you have heard of
something called CXL Anyone
have heard of CXL? But at least have you
heard of PCIe,
right? PCIe is a system bus that
connects to the CPU, memory and all
other free peripheral devices. Then like
GPUs or sometimes you can even consider
uh hard drive because the some type of
SSD can be connected to PCIe bus. So
PCIe bus is designed in a rather simple
way that is mainly responsible for
data transfer. Then CXL
is some very ambitious system that it's
basically replacing PCIe.
It's a hot research topic these days and
there are some prototypes there.
I don't really see any commercial
product that's implemented in C CXL.
Probably there are but CS
CXL is very controversial. What does it
want to do?
Let's say
for most of the case when we talk about
cache coherency protocol cache coherency
protocol happens within the CPU because
all the caches are in the CPU chip right
CPU chip this cache coherency all the
caches are in the CPU then it's relative
to communicate them right because onchip
communication is cheap and fast then
they spend a very small amount of uh
cycles to communicate and the energy
consumption is low. But CX what does CXL
want to do? They say CXL wants to do
something like this. These are two CPUs
and two GPUs.
CXL want to create a unified connection
system that can ensure the coherency
between all of them.
Okay.
then
okay so
that I'm a little bit sus um kind of in
doubt of if CXL is a practical design or
not because the communication latency
here is very high. Now if you want to
send an invalidation signal from a CPU
side to a GPU side then that can be
very expensive then can be a lot of
traffic going on. and then the C like
the GPU and the other GPU may need to
wait a lot a long time until this
conflict maybe resolved. This is um
generally very controversial today. But
if they can implement something with
lower head and can still maintain
coherency, then it definitely makes the
GPU programming much easier because we
don't really need to copy the data back
and forth between the CPU and GPUs.
Today um today although there are some
technology called unified memory for
GPUs that means the GPU can read the
data from CPU or GPU can read the data
from another GPU is all done by
something like the
very basic coherency protocol that I
talked at the very beginning. What they
do is
in this GPU if this GPU wants to access
the GP the data on this GPU what they do
is called a page migration process. Page
migration is no longer works at the 64
byt level. They work at the 4k or even
larger 16k kilobyte level. So what they
do is they find all the cache lines that
access within this page range. They
shoot down all of them. there are a lot
of caches. They shut down all of them.
Remove all of them. Then they move the
page from this GPU to this GPU. Okay,
then this GPU can start to access this
data. Just consider how complex this
type of protocol and this is definitely
a valid type of protocol and it's
probably even better than doing fine
grain control between these two GPUs. um
it's probably high higher performance
but the more realistic cases of how we
program these type of GPUs is to keep
the data local process data and once
we're done using something like koda
memory copy to copy the data from this
GPU to another GPU or copy the data from
GPU to the CPU side is today
like 10 years ago it was the
mainstream method to manage data between
CPU and GPU then today is probably still
the mainstream method to manage CPU and
GPU. The only thing that start to change
where the only meth the only time that
we start to see unified memory start to
become a valid thing is when Apple M
series
and AMD
MI3
300 basically 300A to become a real
thing or you can also say a media
gracehopper
that means they start to sell a single
product that have both CPUs and GPUs
right so in that case
they have different type of technology
to connect the CPU and GPUs and actually
all the three different the three
devices have different ways so they have
a product on this product they have a
CPU part and they have a GPU part and
they have a memory
and this bundle going to the memory is
shared by the CPU and GPU and only
starting from these cases we start to
just simply use maloc to allocate that
memory and start to access on the GPU
side. Uh previously we have to do maloc
for the CPU side koda maloc for the GPU
side. Okay. And you can consider these
type of things as a another type of a
high higher level of cache coherency or
memory coherency in general that we want
to how how we can maintain the validity
of multiple share of the same piece of
data. Okay. Then don't ignore flushing
and copying these type of simple
methods. There are still older school
ways but still valid in this large
scopes.
Question.
Yeah.
Okay. I2M is basically when you have a
right. So,
so if I have a starting from I state and
they want to do a PR right
then what we do is we send a bus PR bus
not a PR bus a bus read X.
Remember last time when we talk about
right signals and def right processes
there's definitely a right allocation
that needs to allocate one cach line and
if we're writing no matter if we're
writing a whole cach line or not a whole
cach line in in CPUs here we're mainly
talking about CPUs we're very very
unlikely to write a whole cach line
right so what we need to do is we have a
bus read x then others need to
invalidate invalidate right others need
to invalidate But after the invalidate
uh the memory needs to send a data ready
to the
cache. Then in this cache we need to
merge this right data and the data from
the top then store it here and convert
to m state. Then it's modified and
exclusively own that this piece of data.
Okay, that's why it's called a bus
readx. Then sometimes we need to read
that piece of data. Sometimes we don't
need to read that piece of data
according depends on if we're writing
the whole cach line or not. But for most
of case if we don't write the whole cach
line we really need the right to read
the data and merge it with the
a few bytes that we're writing.
Okay.
So I I can tell you that every time I
need to prepare this lecture, I need to
revisit every connection, every state
transition that will happens. I can
never draw it out of my brain. Then if I
implement a simulator for these cache
lines, it will take forever take a very
very long time to implement all this.
And it's really really difficult for any
simulator to implement everything.
Now luckily we I'm mainly working on GPU
architecture so I don't need to
implement this type of things. Um
it's really annoying that what every
time which which thing which
which unit is sending what signal to
which other unit and what's the unit
that responds to it. Like for example
this case we're saying there's a bus
read X right let's just consider if it's
a directory based protocol and this one
needs to invalid this one and invalid
this one then they all send out then
they will wait for some time to say
invalid done this one go back to say
invalid done it it's just difficult to
maintain all this
just the context of what's going on
especially We're implementing in a state
a state machine. Okay, even we're
implementing a simulator, we're
implementing a state machine. So just
consider this transient cases. Then one
thing that we have never talked about
multilayer of caches, right? The multi
of multilayer of caches will make things
more complex. We cannot really only
guarantee that a group is coherent. We
need to consider whole chip is coherent.
There are multiple layers.
So this
is even more complex.
Uh okay. So the most important thing to
remember is it generates a lot of
coherency traffic and there are several
ways. The more state that we remember
the fewer traffic that we need to
generate and so we're using space or
using dice size in exchange of
performance. more things that we can
remember. Now we have generally higher
performance, less traffic.